<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL192024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>INTERMEDIATE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>4</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>10A</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20241116 12:00:00 AM CST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20241116 06:00:00 AM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20241116060000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>1200 AM CST Sat Nov 16</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1731736800</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL STORM</systemType>
<systemName>SARA</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>16.1</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-86.3</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>16.1N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>86.3W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>45</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>75</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>40</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>999</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.50</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>STATIONARY</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>0</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>0</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>0</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 35 MI...55 KM SW OF ISLA GUANAJA HONDURAS</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 165 MI...265 KM SE OF BELIZE CITY</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT4 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Storm Sara Intermediate Advisory Number 10A
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL192024
1200 AM CST Sat Nov 16 2024

...SARA NEARLY STATIONARY AND PRODUCING TORRENTIAL RAINFALL WITH 
POTENTIALLY CATASTROPHIC FLOODING AND MUDSLIDES FOR PORTIONS OF 
CENTRAL AMERICA...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 1200 AM CST...0600 UTC...INFORMATION
-----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...16.1N 86.3W
ABOUT 35 MI...55 KM SW OF ISLA GUANAJA HONDURAS
ABOUT 165 MI...265 KM SE OF BELIZE CITY
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...45 MPH...75 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...STATIONARY
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...999 MB...29.50 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
None.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* The Northern coast of Honduras from Punta Patuca westward to the
Honduras-Guatemala border
* The Bay Islands of Honduras
* The Caribbean Sea coast of Guatemala
* The coast of Belize
* The coast of Mexico from Puerto Costa Maya southward to Chetumal
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area.
 
Interests elsewhere in the Yucatan Peninsula should monitor the
progress of this system.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 1200 AM CST (0600 UTC), the center of Tropical Storm Sara was
located near latitude 16.1 North, longitude 86.3 West. Sara is
stationary with little net motion expected overnight. A slow
west-northwestward motion is forecast to begin late today or 
tonight. On the forecast track, the center of Sara will continue to 
move near the northern coast of Honduras during the next day or so 
before approaching Belize, and then move onshore in Belize during 
the day on Sunday.
 
Recent satellite wind data indicate that maximum sustained winds 
are near 45 mph (75 km/h) with higher gusts. No significant change 
in strength is forecast before landfall on Sunday.
 
Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 115 miles (185 km)
from the center.
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 999 mb (29.50 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key Messages for Tropical Storm Sara can be found in the Tropical
Cyclone Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT4 and WMO header
WTNT44 KNHC and on the web at hurricanes.gov/text/MIATCDAT4.shtml
 
RAINFALL: Through early next week, rainfall amounts of 15 to 25
inches with isolated storm totals around 35 inches are expected
over northern Honduras. This rainfall will lead to widespread areas
of life-threatening and potentially catastrophic flash flooding and
mudslides, especially along and near the Sierra La Esperanza.
 
Elsewhere across the rest of Honduras, Belize, El Salvador, eastern
Guatemala, western Nicaragua, and the Mexican State of Quintana Roo,
Tropical Storm Sara is expected to produce 5 to 10 inches of rain
with localized totals around 15 inches through early next week. This
will result in areas of flash flooding, perhaps significant, along
with the potential for mudslides.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall associated with
Tropical Storm Sara, please see the National Weather Service Storm
Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/refresh/graphics_at4+shtml/205755.shtml?
rainqpf#contents
 
WIND: Tropical storm conditions are expected in the warning area in
Honduras during the next couple of days. Tropical storm conditions
are expected in Guatemala, Belize, and portions of Mexico beginning
later today.
 
STORM SURGE: Storm surge could raise water levels by as much as 1 to
3 feet above normal tide levels along the immediate coast in areas
of onshore winds along the northern coast of Honduras. Near the
coast, the surge will be accompanied by large and destructive waves.
A storm surge could raise water levels by as much as 1 to 3 feet
above ground level near and to the north of where the center of Sara
crosses the coast of Belize.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 300 AM CST.
 
$$
Forecaster Beven
 
NNNN
 
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
