<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL182024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>INTERMEDIATE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>3</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>5A</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20241104 07:00:00 PM EST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20241105 12:00:00 AM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20241105000000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0700 PM EST Mon Nov 04</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1730764800</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL STORM</systemType>
<systemName>RAFAEL</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>15.8</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-76.9</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>15.8N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>76.9W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>45</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>75</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>40</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>1000</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.53</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>NNW OR 345 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>9</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>15</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>8</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 150 MI...245 KM S OF KINGSTON JAMAICA</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 370 MI...600 KM SE OF GRAND CAYMAN</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT3 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Storm Rafael Intermediate Advisory Number 5A
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL182024
700 PM EST Mon Nov 04 2024
 
...RAFAEL APPROACHING JAMAICA WHERE TROPICAL STORM CONDITIONS ARE 
EXPECTED TO BEGIN TONIGHT...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 700 PM EST...0000 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...15.8N 76.9W
ABOUT 150 MI...245 KM S OF KINGSTON JAMAICA
ABOUT 370 MI...600 KM SE OF GRAND CAYMAN
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...45 MPH...75 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...NNW OR 345 DEGREES AT 9 MPH...15 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...1000 MB...29.53 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
None.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Hurricane Warning is in effect for...
* Cayman Islands
 
A Hurricane Watch is in effect for...
* Cuban provinces of Pinar del Rio, Artemisa, La Habana,
Mayabeque, Matanzas, and the Isle of Youth
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* Jamaica
 
A Tropical Storm Watch is in effect for...
* Cuban provinces of Villa Clara, Cienfuegos, Sancti Spiritus, Ciego
de Avila, Camaguey, and Las Tunas
* Lower and Middle Florida Keys from Key West to west of the
Channel 5 Bridge
* Dry Tortugas
 
A Hurricane Warning means that hurricane conditions are expected 
somewhere within the warning area.  A warning is typically issued 36 
hours before the anticipated first occurrence of 
tropical-storm-force winds, conditions that make outside 
preparations difficult or dangerous.  Preparations to protect life 
and property should be rushed to completion.system.
 
A Hurricane Watch means that hurricane conditions are possible
within the watch area.  A watch is typically issued 48 hours before
the anticipated first occurrence of tropical-storm-force winds,
conditions that make outside preparations difficult or dangerous.
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area, in this case within 24
hours.
 
A Tropical Storm Watch means that tropical storm conditions are
possible within the watch area, generally within 48 hours.
 
Interests elsewhere in Cuba should closely monitor this system. 
Hurricane and Tropical Storm Warnings will likely be required later 
tonight or early Tuesday. 
 
For storm information specific to your area in the United States, 
including possible inland watches and warnings, please monitor 
products issued by your local National Weather Service forecast 
office. For storm information specific to your area outside of the 
United States, please monitor products issued by your national 
meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 700 PM EST (0000 UTC), the center of Tropical Storm Rafael was 
located by Air Force Reconnaissance aircraft near latitude 
15.8 North, longitude 76.9 West. Rafael is now moving toward the 
north-northwest near 9 mph (15 km/h). A more northwestward motion is 
expected to begin later tonight and forecast to continue for the 
next few days. On the forecast track, the system is expected to move 
near Jamaica during the overnight period, be near or over the Cayman 
Islands late Tuesday, and approach Cuba on Wednesday.
 
Maximum sustained winds are near 45 mph (75 km/h) with higher gusts. 
Steady to rapid strengthening is forecasted and the system could 
become a hurricane on Tuesday.
 
Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 105 miles (165 km)
from the center.
 
The latest minimum central pressure recently measured by dropsonde 
data from the Air Force Hurricane Hunters is 1000 mb (29.53 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Tropical Storm Rafael can be found in the
Tropical Cyclone Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT3 and WMO
header WTNT43 KNHC and on the web at
hurricanes.gov/text/MIATCDAT3.shtml
 
WIND:  Hurricane conditions are expected in the Cayman Islands by 
Tuesday afternoon and are possible in western Cuba and the Isle of 
Youth on Wednesday. Tropical storm conditions are expected in 
Jamaica during the overnight into Tuesday morning and are possible 
in central Cuba, and in the lower and middle Florida Keys on 
Wednesday.
 
RAINFALL: Heavy rainfall will impact areas of the Western Caribbean
with the heaviest rainfall occurring over Jamaica and portions of
Cuba through mid-week. Rainfall totals between 3 to 6 inches with
locally up to 9 inches are expected.  Flooding and mudslides could
occur over portions of Jamaica and Cuba.
 
Heavy rainfall will spread north into Florida and adjacent areas of
the Southeast United States by mid to late week.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall associated with
Tropical Storm Rafael, please see the National Weather Service Storm
Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
https://www.nhc.noaa.gov/graphics_at3.shtml?rainqpf
 
STORM SURGE:  Minor coastal flooding is possible in Jamaica tonight.
Storm surge could raise water levels by 1-3 feet above normal tide
levels in the Cayman Islands on Tuesday, and could raise water
levels by as much as 6 to 9 feet above normal tide levels in areas
of onshore winds along the southern coast of Pinar del Rio, Cuba,
including the Isle of Youth.
 
The combination of a storm surge and the tide will cause normally
dry areas near the coast to be flooded by rising waters moving
inland from the shoreline.  The water could reach the following
heights above ground somewhere in the indicated areas if the peak
surge occurs at the time of high tide...
 
Dry Tortugas...1-3 ft
Lower Florida Keys...1-2 ft
 
SURF:  Swells generated by the system are expected to affect much of
the western Caribbean during the next few days. These swells are
likely to cause life-threatening surf and rip current conditions.
Please consult products from your local weather office. Please
consult products from your local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 1000 PM EST.
 
$$
Forecaster Papin
 
NNNN
 
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
