<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL162024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>INTERMEDIATE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>1</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>7A</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20241020 08:00:00 PM EDT</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20241021 12:00:00 AM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20241021000000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0800 PM EDT Sun Oct 20</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1729468800</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>HURRICANE</systemType>
<systemName>OSCAR</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>20.2</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-74.5</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>20.2N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>74.5W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>75</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>120</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>65</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>988</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.18</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>CATEGORY 1</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>WSW OR 240 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>6</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>9</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>5</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 20 MI...30 KM W OF THE EASTERN TIP OF CUBA</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 45 MI...75 KM E OF GUANTANAMO CUBA</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT1 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Hurricane Oscar Intermediate Advisory Number 7A
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL162024
800 PM EDT Sun Oct 20 2024
 
...OSCAR BRINGING HURRICANE CONDITIONS, HEAVY RAINFALL, AND STORM 
SURGE TO PORTIONS OF EASTERN CUBA...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 800 PM EDT...0000 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...20.2N 74.5W
ABOUT 20 MI...30 KM W OF THE EASTERN TIP OF CUBA
ABOUT 45 MI...75 KM E OF GUANTANAMO CUBA
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...75 MPH...120 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...WSW OR 240 DEGREES AT 6 MPH...9 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...988 MB...29.18 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
None.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Hurricane Warning is in effect for...
* North coast of the Cuban Provinces of Holguin and Guantanamo to
Punta Maisi
 
A Hurricane Watch is in effect for...
* North coast of the Cuban Province of Las Tunas
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* Southeastern Bahamas
* South coast of Cuban Province of Guantanamo
* North coast of the Cuban Province of Las Tunas
 
A Tropical Storm Watch is in effect for...
* North coast of the Cuban Province of Camaguey
* Central Bahamas
 
A Hurricane Warning means that hurricane conditions are expected
somewhere within the warning area.

A Hurricane Watch means that hurricane conditions are possible
within the watch area.
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are 
expected somewhere within the warning area within 36 hours.
 
A Tropical Storm Watch means that tropical storm conditions are
possible within the watch area, generally within 48 hours.
 
Interests in the remainder of the Bahamas should monitor the 
progress of Oscar.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor products 
issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 800 PM EDT (0000 UTC), the center of Hurricane Oscar was located 
near latitude 20.2 North, longitude 74.5 West. Oscar is moving 
toward the west-southwest near 6 mph (9 km/h). A turn toward the 
northwest and north is expected on Monday and Tuesday. On the 
forecast track, the center of Oscar is expected to continue moving 
across eastern Cuba tonight and Monday, then emerge off the northern 
coast of Cuba late Monday and cross the central Bahamas on Tuesday.
 
Maximum sustained winds are near 75 mph (120 km/h) with higher 
gusts. Weakening is expected as Oscar interacts with the mountainous 
terrain of eastern Cuba, but Oscar could still be a tropical storm 
when it moves north of Cuba late Monday and then moves across the 
central Bahamas on Tuesday.
 
Hurricane-force winds extend outward up to 10 miles (20 km) from the 
center and tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 45 miles 
(75 km). A weather station at Punta Maisi in eastern Cuba reported a 
sustained wind of 53 mph (85 km/h) and a gust of 81 mph (130 km/h) 
within the past couple of hours.
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 988 mb (29.18 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Oscar can be found in the Tropical Cyclone 
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT1 and WMO header WTNT41 KNHC 
and on the web at hurricanes.gov/text/MIATCDAT1.shtml
 
WIND:  Hurricane conditions are expected in the warning area and 
possible in the watch area of Cuba tonight.
 
Tropical storm conditions are expected in the warning area and 
possible in the watch area of Cuba tonight and Monday. Tropical 
storm conditions are expected in the warning area in parts of the 
southeastern Bahamas and possible in the watch area in parts of the 
central Bahamas Monday into Tuesday.
 
RAINFALL: Through Wednesday morning, rainfall amounts of 6 to 12 
inches with isolated amounts of 18 inches are expected across 
eastern Cuba. Across the southeastern Bahamas, 3 to 5 inches are 
expected, with isolated amounts around 8 inches.  Across the Turks 
and Caicos, an additional 2 to 4 inches of rain is expected through 
Wednesday morning.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall associated with 
Hurricane Oscar, please see the National Weather Service Storm Total 
Rainfall Graphic, available at 
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at1.shtml?rainqpf
 
STORM SURGE: Water levels of 1 to 3 ft above normal tide levels are 
expected along the north shore of Cuba in areas of onshore winds. 
Near the coast, the surge will be accompanied by large and 
destructive waves.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 1100 PM EDT.
 
$$
Forecaster Reinhart
 
NNNN
 
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
