<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL182024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>INTERMEDIATE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>3</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>4A</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20241104 01:00:00 PM EST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20241104 06:00:00 PM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20241104180000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0100 PM EST Mon Nov 04</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1730743200</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL DEPRESSION</systemType>
<systemName>EIGHTEEN</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>15.1</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-76.4</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>15.1N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>76.4W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>35</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>55</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>30</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>1000</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.53</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>N OR 10 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>9</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>15</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>8</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 200 MI...325 KM S OF KINGSTON JAMAICA</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 430 MI...690 KM SE OF GRAND CAYMAN</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT3 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Depression Eighteen Intermediate Advisory Number 4A
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL182024
100 PM EST Mon Nov 04 2024
 
...DEPRESSION NEARING TROPICAL STORM STRENGTH...
...TROPICAL STORM CONDITIONS EXPECTED TO BEGIN IN JAMAICA 
LATE TONIGHT...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 100 PM EST...1800 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...15.1N 76.4W
ABOUT 200 MI...325 KM S OF KINGSTON JAMAICA
ABOUT 430 MI...690 KM SE OF GRAND CAYMAN
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...35 MPH...55 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...N OR 10 DEGREES AT 9 MPH...15 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...1000 MB...29.53 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
None
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Hurricane Warning is in effect for...
* Cayman Islands
 
A Hurricane Watch is in effect for...
* Cuban provinces of Pinar del Rio, Artemisa, La Habana,
Mayabeque, Matanzas, and the Isle of Youth
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* Jamaica
 
A Tropical Storm Watch is in effect for...
* Cuban provinces of Villa Clara, Cienfuegos, Sancti Spiritus, Ciego
de Avila, Camaguey, and Las Tunas
 
A Hurricane Warning means that hurricane conditions are expected 
somewhere within the warning area.  A warning is typically issued 36 
hours before the anticipated first occurrence of 
tropical-storm-force winds, conditions that make outside 
preparations difficult or dangerous.  Preparations to protect life 
and property should be rushed to completion.system.  Additional 
watches or warnings could be required today.
 
A Hurricane Watch means that hurricane conditions are possible
within the watch area.  A watch is typically issued 48 hours before
the anticipated first occurrence of tropical-storm-force winds,
conditions that make outside preparations difficult or dangerous.
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area, in this case within 24
hours.
 
A Tropical Storm Watch means that tropical storm conditions are
possible within the watch area, generally within 48 hours.
 
Interests elsewhere in Cuba and the Florida Keys should closely
monitor this system.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 100 PM EST (1800 UTC), the center of Tropical Depression Eighteen 
was located near latitude 15.1 North, longitude 76.4 West. The 
depression is moving toward the north near 9 mph (15 km/h). A 
northwestward motion is expected to begin later today and forecast 
to continue for the next few days. On the forecast track, the system 
is expected to move near Jamaica late tonight, be near or over the 
Cayman Islands on Tuesday, and approach Cuba on Wednesday.
 
Maximum sustained winds remain near 35 mph (55 km/h) with higher
gusts. Steady strengthening is forecast, and the depression is
expected to become a tropical storm later today or tonight, and a 
hurricane by Wednesday.
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 1000 mb (29.53 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Tropical Depression Eighteen can be found in the
Tropical Cyclone Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT3 and WMO
header WTNT43 KNHC and on the web at
hurricanes.gov/text/MIATCDAT3.shtml
 
WIND:  Hurricane conditions are expected in the Cayman Islands by
Tuesday afternoon and are possible in western Cuba and the Isle of
Youth on Wednesday. Tropical storm conditions are expected in
Jamaica by late tonight and are possible in central Cuba on
Wednesday.
 
RAINFALL: Heavy rainfall will impact areas of the western Caribbean
with the heaviest rainfall occurring over Jamaica and portions of
Cuba through mid-week. Rainfall totals between 3 to 6 inches with
locally up to 9 inches are expected. Flooding could occur over
portions of Jamaica and Cuba, with mudslides possible.
 
Heavy rainfall will spread north into Florida and adjacent areas of
the Southeast United States during mid- to late week.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall associated with
Tropical Depression Eighteen, please see the National Weather
Service Storm Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
https://www.nhc.noaa.gov/graphics_at3.shtml?rainqpf
 
STORM SURGE:  Minor coastal flooding is possible in Jamaica tonight
and the Cayman Islands on Tuesday. Storm surge could raise water
levels by as much as 2 to 4 feet above normal tide levels in areas
of onshore winds along the southern coast of Pinar del Rio, Cuba,
including the Isle of Youth.
 
SURF:  Swells generated by the system are expected to affect much
of the western Caribbean during the next few days. Please consult
products from your local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 400 PM EST.
 
$$
Forecaster Cangialosi
 
NNNN
 
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
