<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL052024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>ROUTINE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>5</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>17</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240815 05:00:00 PM AST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240815 09:00:00 PM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20240815210000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0500 PM AST Thu Aug 15</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1723755600</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>HURRICANE</systemType>
<systemName>ERNESTO</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>26.1</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-68.9</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>26.1N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>68.9W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>85</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>140</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>75</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>972</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>28.71</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>CATEGORY 1</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>N OR 360 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>13</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>20</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>11</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 495 MI...795 KM SSW OF BERMUDA</systemGeoRefPt1>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT5 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Hurricane Ernesto Advisory Number  17
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL052024
500 PM AST Thu Aug 15 2024
 
...CONDITIONS IN BERMUDA EXPECTED TO DETERIORATE BEGINNING FRIDAY
AFTERNOON...
...HIGH RISK OF DANGEROUS RIP CURRENTS ALONG U.S. EAST COAST BEACHES
THIS WEEKEND...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 500 PM AST...2100 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...26.1N 68.9W
ABOUT 495 MI...795 KM SSW OF BERMUDA
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...85 MPH...140 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...N OR 360 DEGREES AT 13 MPH...20 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...972 MB...28.71 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
None.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Hurricane Warning is in effect for...
* Bermuda
 
A Hurricane Warning means that hurricane conditions are expected
somewhere within the warning area.  A warning is typically issued
36 hours before the anticipated first occurrence of
tropical-storm-force winds, conditions that make outside
preparations difficult or dangerous.  Preparations to protect life
and property should be rushed to completion.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 500 PM AST (2100 UTC), the center of Hurricane Ernesto was
located near latitude 26.1 North, longitude 68.9 West. Ernesto is
moving toward the north near 13 mph (20 km/h).  This general motion
is expected to continue today, followed by a slower northeastward or
north-northeastward motion on Friday and Saturday. On the forecast
track, the center of Ernesto is expected to pass near or over
Bermuda on Saturday.
 
Maximum sustained winds are near 85 mph (140 km/h) with higher gusts 
based on data from a NOAA Hurricane Hunter aircraft.  Strengthening 
is forecast during the next day or so, and Ernesto could be near 
major hurricane strength by Friday.  Ernesto is forecast to be a 
large hurricane near Bermuda on Saturday.
 
Hurricane-force winds extend outward up to 60 miles (95 km) from the
center and tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 265 miles
(425 km).
 
The estimated minimum central pressure based on a dropsonde
observation is 972 mb (28.71 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Ernesto can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT5 and WMO header WTNT45 KNHC
and on the web at hurricanes.gov/text/MIATCDAT5.shtml.
 
WIND: Hurricane conditions are expected on Bermuda Saturday, with
tropical storm conditions likely beginning Friday afternoon.
 
STORM SURGE: A dangerous storm surge is expected to produce
significant coastal flooding on Bermuda in areas of onshore winds.
Near the coast, the surge will be accompanied by large and
destructive waves.
 
RAINFALL: Ernesto is expected to produce total rain accumulations of
6 to 12 inches in Bermuda with isolated maximum amounts up to 15
inches.  This rainfall may result in considerable life-threatening
flash flooding.
 
SURF: Swells generated by Ernesto are affecting portions of the 
Turks and Caicos Islands, and the Bahamas. These swells will spread 
toward Bermuda later today. Swells are expected to reach the east 
coast of the United States tonight and continue into the weekend. 
These swells are likely to cause life-threatening surf and rip 
current conditions. Please consult products from your local weather 
office, and stay out of the water if advised by lifeguards.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next intermediate advisory at 800 PM AST.
Next complete advisory at 1100 PM AST.
 
$$
Forecaster Bucci/Onderlinde
 
NNNN
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
