<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>EP112024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>ROUTINE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>1</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>9</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20241003 03:00:00 PM CST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20241003 09:00:00 PM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20241003210000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0300 PM CST Thu Oct 03</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1727989200</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>REMNANTS OF</systemType>
<systemName>ELEVEN-E</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>15.7</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-94.6</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>15.7N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>94.6W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>40</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>65</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>35</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>1006</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.71</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>N OR 360 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>7</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>11</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>6</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 55 MI...85 KM SE OF SALINA CRUZ MEXICO</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 125 MI...205 KM E OF PUERTO ANGEL MEXICO</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPEP1 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Remnants Of Eleven-E Advisory Number   9
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       EP112024
300 PM CST Thu Oct 03 2024
 
...DEPRESSION DEGENERATES TO A TROUGH...
...REMNANTS TO PRODUCE HEAVY RAINS WITH FLOODING AND MUDSLIDES
IN PORTIONS OF SOUTHERN MEXICO...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 300 PM CST...2100 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...15.7N 94.6W
ABOUT 55 MI...85 KM SE OF SALINA CRUZ MEXICO
ABOUT 125 MI...205 KM E OF PUERTO ANGEL MEXICO
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...40 MPH...65 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...N OR 360 DEGREES AT 7 MPH...11 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...1006 MB...29.71 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The Government of Mexico has discontinued the Tropical Storm
Warning for the coast of Mexico.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
Ther are no coastal watches or warnings in effect.
 
Although the warnings have been discontinued, interests in
southeastern Mexico should continue monitor the progress of this
system.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 300 PM CST (2100 UTC), the remnants of Eleven-E were located near
latitude 15.7 North, longitude 94.6 West. The remnants are moving
toward the north near 7 mph (11 km/h), and a northeastward to
northward motion is forecast through Friday. On the forecast track,
the remnants of the depression should move inland over the Isthmus
of Tehuantepec later today or tonight.
 
Satellite wind data indicate that maximum sustained winds are near
40 mph (65 km/h) with higher gusts.  Weakening is expected, and the
remnants are forecast to dissipate over Mexico on Friday.
 
Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 60 miles (95 km)
from the center, mainly in offshore flow to the north and west of
the remnants.
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 1006 mb (29.71 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for the Remnants of Eleven-E can be found in the
Tropical Cyclone Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDEP1 and WMO
header WTPZ41 KNHC.
 
WIND:  Gusts to tropical-storm force are possible along portions of
the coast of the Gulf of Tehuantepec this afternoon and tonight.
 
RAINFALL: Additional rainfall of 3 to 6 inches, with localized 
amounts up to 8 inches, is expected across portions of the Mexican 
states of Chiapas, Oaxaca, Veracruz Tabasco and coastal Guerrero. 
This rainfall may lead to areas of flooding and mudslides. 

For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall associated with 
the Remnants of Eleven-E, please see the National Weather 
Service Storm Total Rainfall Graphic available at 
hurricanes.gov/graphics_ep1.shtml?rainqpf
 
STORM SURGE: Minor coastal flooding from storm surge is possible in
areas of onshore flow.
 
SURF:  Swells generated by the Remnants of Eleven-E are affecting 
portions of the coast of southern and southeastern Mexico. These 
swells are likely to cause life-threatening surf and rip current 
conditions. Please consult products from your local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
This is the last public advisory issued by the National Hurricane
Center on this system. For additional information on the remnants 
please see forecasts issued by the Meteorological Service of Mexico 
and High Seas Forecasts issued by the National Weather Service, 
under AWIPS header NFDHSFEPI, WMO header FZPN02 KWBC, and on the web 
at ocean.weather.gov/shtml/NFDHSFEPI.php

$$
Forecaster Beven
 
NNNN
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
