<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL042024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>ROUTINE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>4</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>23</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240807 11:00:00 PM EDT</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240808 03:00:00 AM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20240808030000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>1100 PM EDT Wed Aug 07</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1723086000</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL STORM</systemType>
<systemName>DEBBY</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>32.9</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-79.5</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>32.9N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>79.5W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>60</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>95</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>50</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>994</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.36</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>NNW OR 345 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>3</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>6</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>3</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 25 MI...40 KM ENE OF CHARLESTON SOUTH CAROLINA</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 65 MI...105 KM SSW OF MYRTLE BEACH SOUTH CAROLINA</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT4 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Storm Debby Advisory Number  23
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL042024
1100 PM EDT Wed Aug 07 2024
 
...CENTER OF DEBBY ABOUT TO CROSS THE COAST OF SOUTH CAROLINA...
...MAJOR FLOOD THREAT CONTINUES FOR PORTIONS OF THE CAROLINAS...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 1100 PM EDT...0300 UTC...INFORMATION
-----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...32.9N 79.5W
ABOUT 25 MI...40 KM ENE OF CHARLESTON SOUTH CAROLINA
ABOUT 65 MI...105 KM SSW OF MYRTLE BEACH SOUTH CAROLINA
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...60 MPH...95 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...NNW OR 345 DEGREES AT 3 MPH...6 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...994 MB...29.36 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The Tropical Storm Warning has been discontinued south of Edisto
Beach, South Carolina.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* Edisto Beach, South Carolina to Surf City, North Carolina
 
A Tropical Storm Watch is in effect for...
* North of Surf City, North Carolina to Beaufort Inlet, North
Carolina
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area.
 
A Tropical Storm Watch means that tropical storm conditions are
possible within the watch area.
 
Interests elsewhere along the southeastern coast of the United
States should monitor the progress of this system.
 
For storm information specific to your area, including possible
inland watches and warnings, please monitor products issued by your
local National Weather Service forecast office.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 1100 PM EDT (0300 UTC), the center of Tropical Storm Debby was
located near latitude 32.9 North, longitude 79.5 West. Debby is
moving toward the north-northwest near 3 mph (6 km/h). This 
general motion is expected to continue through Thursday, bringing 
the center across the South Carolina coast during the next several 
hours. A faster motion toward the north and north-northeast across 
the Carolinas and the U.S. Mid-Atlantic states is expected later on 
Thursday and on Friday.
 
Maximum sustained winds are near 60 mph (95 km/h) with higher gusts.
Weakening is forecast to begin on Thursday after the center moves 
inland. Debby is expected to merge with a frontal boundary over the 
U.S. Mid-Atlantic states on Friday or Friday night.
 
Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 185 miles (295 km)
mainly to the east of the center. NOAA buoy 41013 near Frying Pan 
Shoals, North Carolina, recently reported sustained winds of 38 
mph (61 km/h) and a wind gust of 45 mph (72 km/h).
 
The estimated minimum central pressure based on surface 
observations and Air Force Reserve Hurricane Hunter aircraft data 
is 994 mb (29.36 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Debby can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT4 and WMO header WTNT44 KNHC.
 
WIND: Tropical storm conditions are expected to continue along the
coast of South Carolina within the tropical storm warning area
through Thursday. Tropical storm conditions are expected within the
tropical storm warning area and possible within the tropical storm
watch area in North Carolina tonight through Thursday.
 
STORM SURGE: The combination of storm surge and tide will cause
normally dry areas near the coast to be flooded by rising waters
moving inland from the shoreline. The water could reach the
following heights above ground somewhere in the indicated areas if
the peak surge occurs at the time of high tide...
 
South Santee River to Ocracoke Inlet including the Neuse and
Pamlico Rivers...1 to 3 ft
 
For a complete depiction of areas at risk of storm surge inundation,
please see the National Weather Service Peak Storm Surge Graphic,
available at hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?peakSurge.
 
RAINFALL: Debby is expected to produce an additional 3 to 9 inches
of rainfall with locally higher amounts, leading to maximum storm
total amounts as high as 25 inches in eastern South Carolina and 15
inches in southeast North Carolina with considerable flooding
expected across portions of eastern South Carolina and southeast
North Carolina through Friday.
 
An additional 1 to 2 inches of rainfall with locally higher amounts
is possible across southeast Georgia through Thursday, bringing
overall storm total amounts as high as 15 inches, which may
aggravate any ongoing flooding conditions.
 
From the piedmont of South Carolina northward across portions of
Virginia, 3 to 7 inches with local amounts to 10 inches, are
expected through Friday. This rainfall will likely result in areas
of considerable flash and urban flooding, with river flooding
possible.
 
From Maryland north through Upstate New York and Vermont, 2 to 4
inches, with local amounts to 6 inches, are expected through
Saturday morning. This will likely produce considerable flash and
urban flooding as well as river flooding.
 
For Long Island and the remainder of New England, 1 to 2 inches,
with local amounts to 4 inches, are expected into Saturday.
Scattered instances of flash flooding are possible.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall and flash flooding
associated with  Debby, please see the National Weather Service
Storm Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?rainqpf and the Flash Flood Risk
graphic at hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?ero.
 
For a list of rainfall observations (and wind reports) associated
this storm, see the companion storm summary at WBCSCCNS4 with the
WMO header ACUS44 KWBC or at the following link:
www.wpc.ncep.noaa.gov/discussions/nfdscc4.html.
 
TORNADOES: A few tornadoes may occur over parts of eastern North 
Carolina overnight. The risk of tornadoes will shift northward on 
Thursday into central North Carolina and central Virginia.
 
SURF:  Large swells will continue to affect the Southeast U.S.
coast through the end of the week. These conditions are likely to
cause life-threatening surf and rip current conditions. Please
consult products from your local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next intermediate advisory at 200 AM EDT.
Next complete advisory at 500 AM EDT.
 
$$
Forecaster Beven
 
NNNN
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
