<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL042024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS WEATHER PREDICTION CENTER COLLEGE PARK MD</issuingUnit>
<messageType>ROUTINE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>4</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>27</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240808 11:00:00 PM EDT</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240809 03:00:00 AM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>202408090300</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>1100 PM EDT Thu Aug 08</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1723172400</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL DEPRESSION</systemType>
<systemName>DEBBY</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>36.2</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-80.2</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>36.2N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>80.2W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>30</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>45</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>25</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>1001</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.56</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>NNE OR 20 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>26</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>43</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>23</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 80 MI...135 KM NNE OF CHARLOTTE NORTH CAROLINA</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 90 MI...140 KM WNW OF RALEIGH NORTH CAROLINA</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC NFDTCPAT4 ALL
TTAA00 KWNH DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Depression Debby Advisory Number  27
NWS Weather Prediction Center College Park MD   AL042024
1100 PM EDT Thu Aug 08 2024
 
...MAJOR FLOOD THREAT CONTINUES FOR PORTIONS OF WESTERN VIRGINIA...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 1100 PM EDT...0300 UTC...INFORMATION
-----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...36.2N 80.2W
ABOUT 80 MI...135 KM NNE OF CHARLOTTE NORTH CAROLINA
ABOUT 90 MI...140 KM WNW OF RALEIGH NORTH CAROLINA
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...30 MPH...45 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...NNE OR 20 DEGREES AT 26 MPH...43 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...1001 MB...29.56 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
Flood Watches and Warnings are in effect for portions of....
* South Carolina
* North Carolina
* Virginia
* Eastern West Virginia
* Maryland
* Pennsylvania
 
A Flood Watch is in effect for portions of...
* Upstate New York
* Northern Vermont
* Northern New Hampshire
 
A Tornado Watch is in effect for portions of...
* Eastern North Carolina
* Northern and Eastern Virginia
* Maryland
* District of Columbia
* Eastern West Virginia
 
Coastal Flood Advisories are in effect for portions of...
* Eastern North Carolina
* Areas surrounding the Chesapeake Bay and Potomac River
* Central New Jersey Coast
 
A Gale Watch is in effect the coastal waters of...
* Rhode Island
* Southeastern Massachusetts up through Cape Cod
 
Wind Advisories are in effect for portions of...
* Western Virginia
* Eastern Maryland
* Delaware
* Eastern Pennsylvania
* New Jersey
* Southern New York
* Southern Connecticut
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 1100 PM EDT (0300 UTC), the center of Tropical Depression Debby
was located near latitude 36.2 North, longitude 80.2 West. The
depression is moving toward the north-northeast near 26 mph (43
km/h) and this motion is expected to slowly increase and shift to 
the northeast over the next day.
 
Maximum sustained winds are near 30 mph (45 km/h) with higher gusts.
Little change in strength is forecast during the next 48 hours. 

The estimated minimum central pressure is 1001 mb (29.56 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Debby can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT4 and WMO header WTNT44 KNHC.
 
RAINFALL: Debby is expected to produce an additional 3 to 6 inches
of rainfall with locally higher amounts, across portions of
southeastern North Carolina leading to maximum storm total amounts
as high as 15 inches.  Additional rainfall of 1 to 3 inches over
portions of eastern South Carolina will bring maximum storm total
amounts as high as 20 to 25 inches. Considerable flooding is
expected across portions of eastern South Carolina and southeast
North Carolina through Friday.
 
From central North Carolina northward across portions of Virginia, 3
to 7 inches with local amounts to 10 inches, are expected through
Friday. This rainfall will likely result in areas of considerable to
locally catastrophic flash and urban flooding, especially in the
terrain of western Virginia, with river flooding also possible.
 
From portions of Maryland north through Upstate New York and
Vermont, 2 to 4 inches, with local amounts to 6 inches, are expected
through Friday night. This will likely result in areas of
considerable flash and urban flooding as well as river flooding.
 
For the remainder of northern New England, 1 to 3 inches, with
local amounts to 4 inches, are expected into Saturday.  Scattered
instances of flash flooding are possible.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall and flash flooding
associated with  Debby, please see the National Weather Service
Storm Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?rainqpf and the Flash Flood Risk
graphic at hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?ero.  For a list of
rainfall observations (and wind reports) associated this storm, see
the companion storm summary at WBCSCCNS4 with the WMO header ACUS44
KWBC or at the following link:
www.wpc.ncep.noaa.gov/discussions/nfdscc4.html.
 
TORNADOES: A few tornadoes may occur tonight from eastern North
Carolina into Virginia and Maryland. The threat for tornadoes will
shift northward into parts of New Jersey, eastern Pennsylvania and
southeast New York on Friday.
 
SURF:  Large swells will continue to affect the Southeast and the
Mid Atlantic coast for another day or so. These conditions are
likely to cause life-threatening surf and rip current conditions.
Please consult products from your local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 500 AM EDT.
 
$$
Forecaster Pereira/Gallina/Chenard
 
NNNN
 
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
