<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL022024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>INTERMEDIATE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>2</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>22A</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240704 02:00:00 AM EDT</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240704 06:00:00 AM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>202407040600</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0200 AM EDT Thu Jul 04</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1720072800</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>HURRICANE</systemType>
<systemName>BERYL</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>18.3</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-80.1</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>18.3N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>80.1W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>125</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>205</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>110</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>965</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>28.50</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>CATEGORY 3</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>WNW OR 285 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>21</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>33</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>18</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 110 MI...175 KM SE OF GRAND CAYMAN</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 500 MI...800 KM ESE OF TULUM MEXICO</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT2 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Hurricane Beryl Intermediate Advisory Number 22A
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL022024
200 AM EDT Thu Jul 04 2024
 
...STRONG WINDS, DANGEROUS STORM SURGE AND DAMAGING WAVES EXPECTED 
ACROSS THE CAYMAN ISLANDS OVERNIGHT...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 200 AM EDT...0600 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...18.3N 80.1W
ABOUT 110 MI...175 KM SE OF GRAND CAYMAN
ABOUT 500 MI...800 KM ESE OF TULUM MEXICO
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...125 MPH...205 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...WNW OR 285 DEGREES AT 21 MPH...33 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...965 MB...28.50 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
None
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Hurricane Warning is in effect for...
* Jamaica
* Grand Cayman
* Little Cayman and Cayman Brac
* The coast of the Yucatan Peninsula of Mexico from Puerto Costa
Maya to Cancun, including Cozumel
 
A Hurricane Watch is in effect for...
* The coast of the Yucatan Peninsula of Mexico south of Puerto
Costa Maya to Chetumal
* The coast of the Yucatan Peninsula of Mexico north of Cancun to
Cabo Catoche
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* The coast of the Yucatan Peninsula of Mexico south of Puerto
Costa Maya to Chetumal
* The coast of the Yucatan Peninsula of Mexico north of Cancun to
Campeche
 
A Tropical Storm Watch is in effect for...
* Coast of Belize from south of Chetumal to Belize City
 
A Hurricane Warning means that hurricane conditions are expected
somewhere within the warning area.  Preparations to protect life
and property should be rushed to completion.
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area within 36 hours.
 
A Hurricane Watch means that hurricane conditions are possible
within the watch area, generally within 48 hours.
 
A Tropical Storm Watch means that tropical storm conditions are
possible within the watch area, generally within 48 hours.
 
Interests elsewhere in the northwestern Caribbean Sea and the
western Gulf of Mexico, including southern Texas, should closely
monitor the progress of Beryl.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 200 AM EDT (0600 UTC), the center of Hurricane Beryl was located 
by Grand Cayman and Air Force Hurricane Hunter radar imagery near 
latitude 18.3 North, longitude 80.1 West. Beryl is moving toward the 
west-northwest near 21 mph (33 km/h). A westward to west- 
northwestward motion is expected during the next day or two, taking 
the core of Beryl just south of the Cayman Islands overnight and 
over the Yucatan Peninsula early Friday. Beryl is expected to emerge 
over the southwestern Gulf of Mexico Friday night and turn 
northwestward.
 
Maximum sustained winds have decreased to 125 mph (205 km/h) with 
higher gusts.  Beryl is a category 3 hurricane on the Saffir-Simpson 
Hurricane Wind Scale.  Some weakening is forecast during the next 
day or two, however, Beryl is forecast to be at or near major 
hurricane intensity while it passes by the Cayman Islands.  
Additional weakening is expected thereafter, though Beryl is 
forecast to remain a hurricane until it makes landfall on the 
Yucatan Peninsula.
 
Hurricane-force winds extend outward up to 45 miles (75 km) from
the center and tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 185
miles (295 km).
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 965 mb (28.50 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Beryl can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT2 and WMO header WTNT42 KNHC.
 
WIND: Hurricane conditions are expected to reach the Cayman Islands
within the next several hours, with tropical storm conditions 
starting soon.

Hurricane conditions are diminishing across Jamaica.
 
Hurricane conditions are expected in the hurricane warning area on 
the Yucatan Peninsula late today or early Friday morning.  Winds are 
expected to first reach tropical storm strength later today, making 
outside preparations difficult or dangerous.
 
Hurricane conditions are possible in the hurricane watch area along 
the east coast of the Yucatan Peninsula as early as late today.
 
Tropical storm conditions are expected in the tropical storm warning
area of the Yucatan Peninsula late today.
 
Tropical storm conditions are possible in the tropical storm watch 
area along portions of the coast of Belize by late today or early 
Friday.
 
STORM SURGE:  Storm surge could raise water levels by as much as 2 
to 4 feet above normal tide levels in areas of onshore winds along 
the immediate coast of the Cayman Islands.
 
Storm surge could raise water levels by as much as 4 to 6 feet
above ground level in areas of onshore winds along the east coast of
the Yucatan Peninsula within the hurricane warning area and by as
much as 1 to 3 feet above ground level along the west coast of the
Yucatan Peninsula in the tropical storm warning area.

Near the coast, the surge will be accompanied by large and
destructive waves.

Storm surge should be gradually subsiding in Jamaica.
 
RAINFALL:  Beryl is expected to produce rainfall totals of 4 to 8
inches with localized amounts of 12 inches across Jamaica through
this morning. This heavy rainfall is expected to cause life- 
threatening flash flooding and mudslides.
 
Beryl is also expected to bring rainfall totals of 4 to 6 inches
over the Cayman Islands through today. Over the Yucatan Peninsula
into northern Belize, Beryl is expected to produce rainfall totals
of 4 to 6 inches with localized amounts of 8 inches late today
through Friday. Scattered instances of flash flooding are
anticipated.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall and flash flooding
associated with Hurricane Beryl, please see the National Weather
Service Storm Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at2.shtml?rainqpf
 
SURF:  Large swells generated by Beryl are currently impacting
portions of the coast of Jamaica, Cuba, and the Cayman Islands.
These swells are expected to spread to the Yucatan Peninsula and
portions of Central America later today and to eastern Mexico and
much of the Gulf Coast of the U.S. by late Friday. These swells are
expected to cause life-threatening surf and rip current conditions.
Please consult products from your local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 500 AM EDT.
 
$$
Forecaster Blake
 
NNNN
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
