<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL182024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>ROUTINE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>3</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>12</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20241106 10:00:00 AM EST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20241106 03:00:00 PM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20241106150000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>1000 AM EST Wed Nov 06</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1730905200</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>HURRICANE</systemType>
<systemName>RAFAEL</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>21.4</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-81.9</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>21.4N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>81.9W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>110</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>175</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>95</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>960</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>28.35</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>CATEGORY 2</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>NW OR 320 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>14</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>22</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>12</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 60 MI...95 KM ESE OF THE ISLE OF YOUTH</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 130 MI...205 KM SSE OF HAVANA CUBA</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT3 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Hurricane Rafael Advisory Number  12
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL182024
1000 AM EST Wed Nov 06 2024
 
...RAFAEL EXPECTED TO BECOME A MAJOR HURRICANE BEFORE LANDFALL
IN WESTERN CUBA...
...LIFE-THREATENING STORM SURGE, DAMAGING HURRICANE-FORCE WINDS,
AND FLASH FLOODING EXPECTED IN PORTIONS OF WESTERN CUBA...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 1000 AM EST...1500 UTC...INFORMATION
-----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...21.4N 81.9W
ABOUT 60 MI...95 KM ESE OF THE ISLE OF YOUTH
ABOUT 130 MI...205 KM SSE OF HAVANA CUBA
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...110 MPH...175 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...NW OR 320 DEGREES AT 14 MPH...22 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...960 MB...28.35 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The government of the Cayman Islands has discontinued the Hurricane
Warning for Little Cayman and Cayman Brac.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Hurricane Warning is in effect for...
* Cuban provinces of Pinar del Rio, Artemisa, La Habana, Mayabeque,
Matanzas, and the Isle of Youth
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* Cuban provinces of Villa Clara, Cienfuegos, Sancti Spiritus,
and Ciego de Avila
* Lower and Middle Florida Keys from Key West to west of the
Channel 5 Bridge
* Dry Tortugas
 
A Hurricane Warning means that hurricane conditions are expected
somewhere within the warning areas.  Preparations to protect life
and property should be rushed to completion.
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area.
 
For storm information specific to your area in the United
States, including possible inland watches and warnings, please
monitor products issued by your local National Weather Service
forecast office. For storm information specific to your area
outside of the United States, please monitor products issued by
your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 1000 AM EST (1500 UTC), the center of Hurricane Rafael was
located near latitude 21.4 North, longitude 81.9 West. Rafael is
moving toward the northwest near 14 mph (22 km/h).  A general
northwestward motion is anticipated over the next day or so,
followed by a gradual west-northwestward turn in the Gulf of Mexico.
On the forecast track, Rafael is expected move near or just east of
the Isle of Youth during the next few hours, and make landfall
in western Cuba later today.  Rafael is forecast to move into the
southeastern Gulf of Mexico tonight.
 
Maximum sustained winds have increased to near 110 mph (175 km/h) 
with higher gusts.  Additional strengthening is expected, and
Rafael is forecast to be a major hurricane when it makes landfall 
in Cuba later today.  Rafael is forecast to weaken over Cuba but is 
expected to emerge into the southeastern Gulf of Mexico as a 
hurricane.
 
Hurricane-force winds extend outward up to 15 miles (30 km) from the
center and tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 115 miles
(185 km).
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 960 mb (28.35 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Hurricane Rafael can be found in the Tropical
Cyclone Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT3 and WMO header
WTNT43 KNHC and on the web at hurricanes.gov/text/MIATCDAT3.shtml
 
WIND:  Hurricane conditions are expected in western Cuba and the 
Isle of Youth today.  Tropical storm conditions are expected in 
parts of west-central Cuba and the lower and middle Florida Keys 
today and tonight.  Tropical storm conditions are possible farther 
east in central Cuba today.
 
RAINFALL: RAINFALL: Heavy rainfall will impact areas of the Western
Caribbean through early Thursday, particularly across the Cayman
Islands into western Cuba. Rainfall totals of 4 to 8 inches are
expected across portions of western Cuba, with isolated higher
totals up to 12 inches anticipated across areas of higher terrain.
This will lead to areas of flash flooding and mudslides. Across the
Cayman Islands additional rainfall of 2 to 4 inches is expected.
 
Rainfall totals of 1 to 3 inches are expected for the Lower and
Middle Florida Keys.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall associated with
Hurricane Rafael, please see the National Weather Service Storm
Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
https://www.nhc.noaa.gov/graphics_at3.shtml?rainqpf
 
STORM SURGE: Storm surge could raise water levels as much as 9 to
14 feet above normal tide levels in areas of onshore winds along
the southern coast of Cuba in the Hurricane Warning area, including
the Isle of Youth.
 
The combination of a storm surge and the tide will cause normally
dry areas near the coast to be flooded by rising waters moving
inland from the shoreline.  The water could reach the following
heights above ground somewhere in the indicated areas if the peak
surge occurs at the time of high tide...
 
Dry Tortugas...1-3 ft
Lower Florida Keys...1-2 ft
 
TORNADOES: A couple of tornadoes are possible through tonight over
the Florida Keys and far southwestern Florida mainland.
 
SURF: Swells generated by Rafael are expected to affect much of the
western Caribbean during the next day or so and will also spread
across most of the Gulf of Mexico from east to west late this week
into the weekend. These swells are likely to cause life-threatening
surf and rip current conditions. Please consult products from your
local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next intermediate advisory at 100 PM EST.
Next complete advisory at 400 PM EST.
 
$$
Forecaster Brown
 
NNNN
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
