<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>EP092024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>ROUTINE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>4</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>1</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240912 08:00:00 AM MST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240912 03:00:00 PM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20240912150000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0800 AM MST Thu Sep 12</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1726153200</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL DEPRESSION</systemType>
<systemName>NINE-E</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>19.2</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-107.6</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>19.2N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>107.6W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>35</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>55</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>30</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>1002</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.59</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>NW OR 325 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>7</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>11</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>6</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 295 MI...475 KM SSE OF CABO SAN LUCAS MEXICO</systemGeoRefPt1>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPEP4 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Depression Nine-E Advisory Number   1
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       EP092024
800 AM MST Thu Sep 12 2024
 
...TROPICAL STORM WARNINGS ISSUED FOR PORTIONS OF THE SOUTHERN
BAJA CALIFORNIA PENINSULA OF MEXICO...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 800 AM MST...1500 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...19.2N 107.6W
ABOUT 295 MI...475 KM SSE OF CABO SAN LUCAS MEXICO
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...35 MPH...55 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...NW OR 325 DEGREES AT 7 MPH...11 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...1002 MB...29.59 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The government of Mexico has issued a Tropical Storm Warning for
the southern portion of Baja California Sur from Santa Fe southward
on the west coast and La Paz southward on the east coast.
 
The government of Mexico has issued a Tropical Storm Watch along
the east coast of Baja California Sur north of La Paz to San
Evaristo.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* West coast of Baja California Sur Mexico from Santa Fe southward
* East coast of Baja California Sur Mexico from La Paz southward
 
A Tropical Storm Watch is in effect for...
* Baja California Sur Mexico north of La Paz to San Evaristo
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area within 36 hours.
 
A Tropical Storm Watch means that tropical storm conditions are
possible within the watch area, generally within 48 hours.
 
Interests elsewhere in the Mexican states of Baja California Sur,
Sinaloa, and Sonora should closely monitor the progress of Tropical
Depression Nine-E.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 800 AM MST (1500 UTC), the center of Tropical Depression Nine-E
was located near latitude 19.2 North, longitude 107.6 West. The
depression is moving toward the northwest near 7 mph (11 km/h) and
this motion is expected to continue through early Friday, followed
by a turn toward the north and a slight decrease in forward speed.
On the forecast track, the center of the cyclone should pass near
or over Baja California Sur Friday or Friday night before emerging
over the southern Gulf of California late Friday night.
 
Maximum sustained winds are near 35 mph (55 km/h) with higher gusts.
Some strengthening is forecast during the next 24 to 36 hours, and
the depression is forecast to strengthen to a tropical storm later
today, with some slight additional strengthening possible before
the system reaches the southern Baja California peninsula.
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 1002 mb (29.59 inches).

 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for the depression can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDEP4 and WMO header WTPZ44 KNHC.

RAINFALL: Tropical Depression Nine-E is expected to produce 4-6
inches of rain with localized higher amounts up to 8 inches across
the coastal areas of Michoacan, Colima, and Jalisco through early
Friday. From Friday through Sunday, the system is forecast to
produce 4-6 inches of rain, with localized higher amounts up to 8
inches, across southern Baja California. For northwest coastal
Sinaloa, the system may produce between 6-8 inches of rain with
localized higher amounts up to 12 inches.  This heavy rainfall will 
bring a risk of flash flooding and mudslides to portions of the 
area. 
 
WIND: Tropical storm conditions are expected to first reach
the coast of the southern Baja California Peninsula within the
warning area by early Friday, making outside preparations difficult
or dangerous. Tropical storm conditions are possible within the
watch area by late Friday night or early Saturday.
 
SURF: Swells generated by Tropical Depression Nine-E will affect
portions of the coast of west-central Mexico during the next day or
so, and will spread northward along the coasts of the southern Baja
California Peninsula and mainland Mexico beginning tonight. These
swells are likely to cause life-threatening surf and rip current
conditions.  Please consult products from your local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next intermediate advisory at 1100 AM MST.
Next complete advisory at 200 PM MST.
 
$$
Forecaster Hagen
 
NNNN
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
