<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>EP092024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>INTERMEDIATE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>4</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>4A</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240913 05:00:00 AM MST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240913 12:00:00 PM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20240913120000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0500 AM MST Fri Sep 13</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1726228800</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL STORM</systemType>
<systemName>ILEANA</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>21.8</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-109</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>21.8N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>109.0W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>45</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>75</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>40</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>999</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.50</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>NNW OR 335 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>10</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>17</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>9</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 95 MI...155 KM SE OF CABO SAN LUCAS MEXICO</systemGeoRefPt1>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPEP4 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Storm Ileana Intermediate Advisory Number 4A
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       EP092024
500 AM MST Fri Sep 13 2024
 
...CENTER OF ILEANA MOVING TOWARD BAJA CALIFORNIA SUR WITH LITTLE 
CHANGE IN STRENGTH...
...TROPICAL STORM CONDITIONS EXPECTED TO REACH THE COAST LATER THIS
MORNING...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 500 AM MST...1200 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...21.8N 109.0W
ABOUT 95 MI...155 KM SE OF CABO SAN LUCAS MEXICO
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...45 MPH...75 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...NNW OR 335 DEGREES AT 10 MPH...17 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...999 MB...29.50 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
None
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* West coast of Baja California Sur Mexico from Santa Fe southward
* East coast of Baja California Sur Mexico from San Evaristo
southward
 
A Tropical Storm Watch is in effect for...
* East coast of Baja California Sur Mexico north of San Evaristo to
Loreto
* Mainland Mexico from Topolobampo to Huatabampito
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area, in this case within
12 to 24 hours.
 
A Tropical Storm Watch means that tropical storm conditions are
possible within the watch area, in this case within 36 hours.
 
Interests elsewhere in the Mexican states of Baja California Sur,
Sinaloa, and Sonora should closely monitor the progress of Ileana.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 500 AM MST (1200 UTC), the center of Tropical Storm Ileana was
located near latitude 21.8 North, longitude 109.0 West. Ileana is
moving toward the north-northwest near 10 mph (17 km/h). A slower
north-northwestward to northward motion is expected during the next
few days. On the forecast track, Ileana is expected to move across
the southern portion of the Baja California peninsula today and over
the Gulf of California this weekend.
 
Maximum sustained winds are near 45 mph (75 km/h) with higher
gusts. Little change in strength is forecast before Ileana reaches
the Baja California peninsula. Weakening is expected over the
weekend, and Ileana is forecast to dissipate by early Monday.
 
Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 60 miles (95 km)
from the center.
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 999 mb (29.50 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Ileana can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDEP4 and WMO header WTPZ44 KNHC.
 
RAINFALL: Through this weekend, Tropical Storm Ileana may produce
rainfall of 4 to 6 inches, with localized higher amounts up to 8
inches, across southern Baja California Sur. For northwest coastal
Sinaloa, Tropical Storm Ileana may result between 6 to 8 inches with
localized higher amounts up to 12 inches.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall associated with
Ileana, please see the National Weather Service Storm Total Rainfall
Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_ep4.shtml?rainqpf
 
WIND: Tropical storm conditions are expected to first reach the
coast of the southern Baja California Peninsula within the warning
area this morning. Tropical storm conditions are possible within the
watch area by early Saturday.
 
SURF: Swells generated by Ileana will affect portions of the coast
of west-central Mexico and the coast of the southern Baja California
Peninsula during the next couple of days. These swells are likely to
cause life-threatening surf and rip current conditions. Please
consult products from your local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 800 AM MST.
 
$$
Forecaster Beven
 
NNNN
 
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
