<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<metadata>
   <idinfo>
      <citation>
         <citeinfo>
            <origin>NHC Storm Surge Unit</origin>
            <pubdate>20240708</pubdate>
            <title>NHC Potential Storm Surge Flooding Map</title>
            <geoform>raster digital data</geoform>
         </citeinfo>
      </citation>
      <descript>
         <abstract>This map is intended to display the National Hurricane Center's Potential Storm Surge Flooding Map for Tropical Storm BERYL Advisory 40 valid at 2024070812.</abstract>
         <purpose>The Potential Storm Surge Flooding Map is an operational product that depicts the risk associated with coastal flooding from storm surge associated with tropical cyclones. Developed over the course of several years in consultation with social scientists, emergency managers, broadcast meteorologists, and others, this map shows:
-Geographical areas where inundation from storm surge could occur
-The heights, above ground, that water could reach in those areas

The Potential Storm Surge Flooding Map is based on the NWS Sea, Lake, and Overland Surges from Hurricanes (SLOSH) model and takes into account forecast uncertainty in the tropical cyclone track, intensity, and wind field. The map is based on probabilistic storm surge guidance developed by the NWS Meteorological Development Laboratory (MDL), in cooperation with NHC, called Probabilistic Hurricane Storm Surge (P-Surge 2.x)

P-Surge 2.x derives storm surge probabilities by statistically evaluating a large set of SLOSH model simulations based on the current NHC offical forecast, and takes into account historical errors in the official NHC track and intensity forecasts. P-Surge 2.x combines the results of hundreds of individual SLOSH simulations to calculate the statistical distribution, or probabilities of possible storm surge heights at locations along the coast. All major factors that influence the amount of storm surge generated by a storm at a given location are accounted for, including the hurricane's landfall location, forward speed, and angle of approach to the coast; the storm intensity and wind field; the shape of the coastline; the slope of the ocean bottom; and local features such as barrier islands, bays, and rivers. The Potential Storm Surge Flooding Map is created by processing the resulting 10 percent exceedance levels from P-Surge 2.x, or storm surge values that have a 1-in-10 chance of being exceeded at each location.

The Potential Storm Surge Flooding Map takes into account:
-Flooding due to storm surge from the ocean, including adjoining tidal rivers, sounds, and bays
-Normal astronomical tides
-Land elevation
-Uncertainties in the landfall location, forward speed, angle of approach to the coast, intensity, and windfield of the cyclone

The Potential Storm Surge Flooding Map does not take into account:
-Wave action
-Freshwater flooding from rainfall, including riverine discharge
-Flooding resulting from levee failures
-For mapped leveed areas - Flooding inside levees, overtopping of levees

Potential storm surge flooding is not depicted within certain levee areas, such as the Hurricane &amp; Storm Damage Risk Reduction System in Louisiana. These areas are highly complex and water levels resulting from overtopping are difficult to predict. Users are urged to consult local officials for flood risk inside these leveed areas. If applicable to the region displayed by the map, these leveed areas will be depicted with a black and white diagonal hatch pattern.

The intertidal zone, or generally speaking, the area that is above water at low tide and under water at high tide, will be displayed with a user selectable mask layer on the Potential Storm Surge Flooding Map.  Locations of estuarine wetlands, or lands that are saturated with water, either permanently or seasonally, are also used to help define this mask layer.  This mask layer will allow users to differentiate between areas that could experience consequential flooding of normally dry ground and areas that routinely flood during typical high tides. The intertidal zone/estuarine wetlands mask will be depicted as gray on the Potential Storm Surge Flooding Map.

</purpose>
      </descript>
      <timeperd>
         <timeinfo>
            <sngdate>20240708</sngdate>
         </timeinfo>
      </timeperd>
      <status>
         <progress>unknown</progress>
         <update>As Needed</update>
      </status>
      <spdom>
         <bounding>
            <westbc>west</westbc>
            <eastbc>east</eastbc>
            <northbc>north</northbc>
            <southbc>south</southbc>
         </bounding>
      </spdom>
      <keywords>
         <theme>
            <themekt>None</themekt>
            <themekey>storm surge</themekey>
            <themekey>storm surge flooding</themekey>
            <themekey>National Hurricane Center</themekey>
            <themekey>SLOSH</themekey>
            <themekey>PSURGE</themekey>
            <themekey>inundation</themekey>
            <themekey>tropical cyclones</themekey>
            <themekey>hurricanes</themekey>
         </theme>
      </keywords>
      <accconst/>
      <useconst>This map should only be used as a general guideline for understanding where storm surge flooding could occur given the current forecast situation.  Regardless of what this map shows, always follow evacuation and other instructions from your local emergency management officials.

This map depicts the potential flooding that could be produced from storm surge during a tropical cyclone.  Storm surge is water from the ocean that is pushed onshore by the force of the winds. Flooding from storm surge depends on many factors, such as the track, intensity, size, and forward speed of the tropical cyclone and the characteristics of the coastline where it comes ashore or passes nearby.  These factors are difficult to predict far in advance of a tropical cyclone affecting a particular area. This map uses the best information available at the time it is issued, including uncertainties in the track, intensity, and size forecast.  It includes many assumptions and has limitations, and it cannot tell you what amount of flooding will definitely occur at any given location.  Conditions and the forecast can change and will be reflected on this map with each new full NHC advisory (but not special advisories).  The actual areas that could become flooded may differ from the areas shown on this map. This map accounts for tides, but not waves and not flooding caused by rainfall.

The dataset illustrates the extent and height of possible storm surge flooding under certain scenarios and does not account for erosion, subsidence, morphological changes,  sea-level rise, or future construction.  The data, maps, and information provided should only be used as a tool for general planning/preparedness of the storm surge hazard at a city/community level (not for a parcel level/grid cell assessment). The data and maps in this tool are provided &quot;as is&quot;, without warranty to their performance, merchantable state, or fitness for any particular purpose. The entire risk associated with the results and performance of these data is assumed by the user. This tool should be used strictly as a planning reference and storm surge risk awareness tool and not for navigation, permitting, legal, or regulatory purposes.</useconst>
      <datacred>NOAA/NWS/National Hurricane Center/Storm Surge Unit</datacred>
   </idinfo>
   <dataqual>
      <logic>Standard methods for determining inundation were used. The vertical accuracy of these data are dependent on the source elevation data.</logic>
      <complete>Inundation computed based on NWS Probabilistic Surge (P-Surge) Guidance 10% exceedance data</complete>
      <lineage>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>NWS Meteorological Development Lab (MDL)</origin>
                  <pubdate/>
                  <title>Probabilistic Surge Guidance</title>
                  <onlink/>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc/>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate/>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr/>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>NWS Probabilistic Surge (Psurge) Guidance</srccitea>
            <srccontr/>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>NOAA Office for Coastal Management (OCM)</origin>
                  <pubdate>2015</pubdate>
                  <title>NOAA OCM Digital Elevation Models</title>
                  <onlink>http://coast.noaa.gov/slr</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>onLine</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>The current OCM DEMs are used as of spring 2020</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr/>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>NOAA OCM Digital Elevation Models</srccitea>
            <srccontr>This digital elevation model (DEM) serves as the primary elevation dataset to compute inundation for this analysis.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>USGS</origin>
                  <pubdate>2014</pubdate>
                  <title>USGS 3D Elevation Program (3DEP)</title>
                  <onlink>http://nationalmap.gov/3DEP/index.html</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>onLine</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>Datasets downloaded spring 2020</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr/>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>USGS 3D Elevation Program (3DEP)</srccitea>
            <srccontr>This digital elevation model (DEM) serves as the elevation dataset to compute inundation outside the extent of the OCM elevation dataset.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>USGS</origin>
                  <pubdate>2009</pubdate>
                  <title>USGS National Hydrography Dataset (NHD)</title>
                  <onlink>http://nhd.usgs.gov</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>onLine</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>Vector data obtained in fall 2020</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr/>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>USGS National Hydrography Dataset (NHD)</srccitea>
            <srccontr>This vector dataset is used to aid in masking out waterbodies in the resampled DEM.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>NOAA Office for Coastal Management (OCM)</origin>
                  <pubdate>2015</pubdate>
                  <title>NOAA OCM MHHW Raster</title>
                  <onlink>http://coast.noaa.gov/slr</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>onLine</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>Raster data obtained in 2015</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr/>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>NOAA OCM 0MHHW Raster</srccitea>
            <srccontr>This raster datset is used as part of the process to generate intertidal zone/estuarine wetlands mask.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>NOAA Office for Coastal Management (OCM)</origin>
                  <pubdate/>
                  <title>NOAA Coastal Change Analysis Program (CCAP)</title>
                  <onlink>https://coast.noaa.gov/digitalcoast/tools/lca</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>onLine</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2020</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr/>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>NOAA Coastal Change Analysis Program (CCAP)</srccitea>
            <srccontr>This raster datset is used as part of the process to generate intertidal zone/estuarine wetlands mask.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <srcinfo>
            <srccite>
               <citeinfo>
                  <origin>South Florida Water Management District (SFWMD)</origin>
                  <pubdate>2014.0</pubdate>
                  <title>South Florida Water Management District (SFWMD)</title>
                  <onlink>http://my.sfwmd.gov/portal/page/portal/levelthree/gis</onlink>
               </citeinfo>
            </srccite>
            <typesrc>onLine</typesrc>
            <srctime>
               <timeinfo>
                  <sngdate>
                     <caldate>2014.0</caldate>
                  </sngdate>
               </timeinfo>
               <srccurr/>
            </srctime>
            <srccitea>SFWMD 50 ft topo</srccitea>
            <srccontr>This dataset is used for portions of the Florida Everglades.</srccontr>
         </srcinfo>
         <procstep>
            <procdesc>NHC processes the 10 percent exceedance values from P-Surge using GIS to create the Potential Storm Surge Flooding Map. To calculate inundation, high-resolution elevation data from NOAA's Office for Coastal Management is utilized. Additional processes are used to depict the intertidal zone, remove values over the open ocean, and account for other geographic features. The map is then displayed on the NHC website in an interactive viewer.</procdesc>
            <procdate>20240708</procdate>
         </procstep>
      </lineage>
   </dataqual>
   <spdoinfo>
      <direct/>
      <rastinfo>
         <rasttype/>
         <rowcount/>
         <colcount/>
      </rastinfo>
   </spdoinfo>
   <spref>
      <horizsys>
         <geograph>
            <latres/>
            <longres/>
            <geogunit/>
         </geograph>
         <geodetic>
            <horizdn/>
            <ellips/>
            <semiaxis/>
            <denflat/>
         </geodetic>
      </horizsys>
   </spref>
   <eainfo>
      <detailed>
         <enttyp>
            <enttypl>BERYL_2024_adv40_e10_ResultRaster.tif.vat</enttypl>
            <enttypd>Table</enttypd>
            <enttypds>Table</enttypds>
         </enttyp>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>OID</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>VALUE</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>storm surge bin code</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>NWS/NHC</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>1.0</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Less than 1 foot above ground</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>NWS/NHC</edomvds>
               </edom>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>2.0</edomv>
                  <edomvd>1 to 3 feet above ground</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>NWS/NHC</edomvds>
               </edom>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>3.0</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Greater than 3 feet above ground</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>NWS/NHC</edomvds>
               </edom>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>4.0</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Greater than 6 feet above ground</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>NWS/NHC</edomvds>
               </edom>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>5</edomv>
                  <edomvd>Greater than 9 feet above ground</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>NWS/NHC</edomvds>
               </edom>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>7.0</edomv>
                  <edomvd>*Levee Areas. See note in entity overview</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>NWS/NHC</edomvds>
               </edom>
               <edom>
                  <edomv>15.0</edomv>
                  <edomvd>High Tide Mask</edomvd>
                  <edomvds>NWS/NHC</edomvds>
               </edom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
         <attr>
            <attrlabl>COUNT</attrlabl>
            <attrdef>Pixel Count.</attrdef>
            <attrdefs>Esri</attrdefs>
            <attrdomv>
               <udom>Count generated with raster attribute table.</udom>
            </attrdomv>
         </attr>
      </detailed>
      <overview>
         <eaover>Integer class values and descriptions.

*The potential storm surge hazard is not depicted within certain levee areas, such as the Hurricane and Storm Damage Risk Reduction System in Louisiana.  These areas are highly complex and water levels resulting from overtopping are difficult to predict. Customers are asked to consult local officials for flood risk inside these leveed areas.</eaover>
         <eadetcit>NWS/NHC</eadetcit>
      </overview>
   </eainfo>
   <distinfo>
      <distrib>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>NOAA/NWS/NHC</cntorg>
               <cntper>Storm Surge Unit Team Lead</cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Storm Surge Unit Team Lead</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
               <address>11691 SW 17th St</address>
               <city>Miami</city>
               <state>Florida</state>
               <postal>33165</postal>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntemail>nhcwebmaster@noaa.gov</cntemail>
         </cntinfo>
      </distrib>
      <distliab>Any conclusions drawn from the analysis of this information are not the responsibility of the NOAA, National Weather Service, National Hurricane Center, or its partners. </distliab>
   </distinfo>
   <metainfo>
      <metd>20240708</metd>
      <metc>
         <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
               <cntorg>NOAA/NWS/NHC</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>Storm Surge Unit</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
               <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
               <address>11691 SW 17th St</address>
               <city>Miami</city>
               <state>Florida</state>
               <postal>33165</postal>
            </cntaddr>
         </cntinfo>
      </metc>
   </metainfo>
</metadata>
