<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL052024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>ROUTINE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>5</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>11</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240814 05:00:00 AM AST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240814 09:00:00 AM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20240814090000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0500 AM AST Wed Aug 14</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1723626000</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL STORM</systemType>
<systemName>ERNESTO</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>19.5</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-66.6</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>19.5N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>66.6W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>70</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>110</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>60</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>996</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.42</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>NW OR 315 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>16</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>26</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>14</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 85 MI...135 KM NNW OF SAN JUAN PUERTO RICO</systemGeoRefPt1>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT5 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Storm Ernesto Advisory Number  11
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL052024
500 AM AST Wed Aug 14 2024
 
...TORRENTIAL RAINFALL OCCURRING OVER EASTERN PUERTO RICO FROM
ERNESTO...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 500 AM AST...0900 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...19.5N 66.6W
ABOUT 85 MI...135 KM NNW OF SAN JUAN PUERTO RICO
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...70 MPH...110 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...NW OR 315 DEGREES AT 16 MPH...26 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...996 MB...29.42 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The Hurricane Watch has been discontinued for the U.S. Virgin
Islands, Vieques and Culebra.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Hurricane Watch is in effect for...
* British Virgin Islands
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* British Virgin Islands
* U.S. Virgin Islands
* Puerto Rico
* Vieques and Culebra
 
A Hurricane Watch means that hurricane conditions are possible
within the watch area, in this case through the morning hours.
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area.
 
Interests in Bermuda should monitor the progress of Ernesto.
 
For storm information specific to your area in the United
States, including possible inland watches and warnings, please
monitor products issued by your local National Weather Service
forecast office. For storm information specific to your area
outside of the United States, please monitor products issued by
your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 500 AM AST (0900 UTC), the center of Tropical Storm Ernesto was
located near latitude 19.5 North, longitude 66.6 West. Ernesto is
moving toward the northwest near 16 mph (26 km/h).  A turn toward
the north-northwest and north with a gradual decrease in forward
speed is expected tonight and Thursday. On the forecast track, the
center of Ernesto will pass to the north of Puerto Rico through
today. Ernesto should then move over the western Atlantic later in
the week and be nearing Bermuda on Saturday.
 
Maximum sustained winds remain near 70 mph (110 km/h) with higher
gusts.  Ernesto is expected to become a hurricane later this
morning and could become a major hurricane in a couple of days.
 
Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 150 miles (240 km) 
from the center. A metar station at the Roosevelt Roads Naval 
Station (TJNR) recently reported a sustained wind of 48 mph (78 
km/h) and a gust of 74 mph (119 km/h).  A NOAA Saildrone located 
about 65 miles north- northeast of San Juan, Puerto Rico, recently 
reported a sustained wind of 61 mph (98 km/h) with a gust to 76 mph 
(122 km/h).
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 996 mb (29.42 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Ernesto can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT5 and WMO header WTNT45 KNHC
and on the web at hurricanes.gov/text/MIATCDAT5.shtml.
 
RAINFALL: Ernesto is expected to produce total rain accumulations of
4 to 6 inches over the U.S and British Virgin Islands. Rainfall
totals of 6 to 8 inches, with maximum amounts of 10 inches, are
expected across southeastern Puerto Rico, with totals of 2 to 4
inches across northwestern Puerto Rico.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall associated with
Ernesto, please see the National Weather Service Storm Total
Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at5.shtml?rainqpf
 
WIND: Tropical storm conditions will continue across the Virgin 
Islands, Puerto Rico, Vieques, and Culebra through the overnight 
hours. Hurricane conditions are possible in portions of the watch 
area during the next few hours.
 
STORM SURGE:  Minor coastal flooding remains possible in areas of
onshore winds along the eastern coast of Puerto Rico, including the
islands of Culebra and Vieques, and in the U.S. Virgin Islands,
including St. Thomas, St. John, and St. Croix.  For information
specific to your area, please see products issued by your local
National Weather Service forecast office.
 
SURF: Swells generated by Ernesto are affecting portions of the
Leeward Islands, the Virgin Islands, Puerto Rico and the Dominican
Republic. These swells will reach the Turks and Caicos Islands and
southeastern Bahamas today, and Bermuda and the rest of the Bahamas
on Thursday. Swells are expected to reach the east coast of the
United States Thursday night and continue into the weekend. These
swells are likely to cause life-threatening surf and rip current
conditions. Please consult products from your local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next intermediate advisory at 800 AM AST.
Next complete advisory at 1100 AM AST.
 
$$
Forecaster Blake
 
NNNN
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
