<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL042024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS WEATHER PREDICTION CENTER COLLEGE PARK MD</issuingUnit>
<messageType>ROUTINE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>4</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>28</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240809 05:00:00 AM EDT</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240809 09:00:00 AM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>202408090900</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0500 AM EDT Fri Aug 09</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1723194000</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>POST-TROPICAL CYCLONE</systemType>
<systemName>DEBBY</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>38.2</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-79.1</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>38.2N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>79.1W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>30</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>45</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>25</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>1003</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.62</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>NNE OR 20 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>35</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>56</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>30</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 110 MI...180 KM N OF DANVILLE VIRGINIA</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 165 MI...270 KM N OF RALEIGH NORTH CAROLINA</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC NFDTCPAT4 ALL
TTAA00 KWNH DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Post-Tropical Cyclone Debby Advisory Number  28
NWS Weather Prediction Center College Park MD   AL042024
500 AM EDT Fri Aug 09 2024
 
...HEAVY RAINFALL AND A SIGNIFICANT FLOOD THREAT GRADUALLY SHIFTS
NORTHWARD TODAY FROM THE NORTHERN MID-ATLANTIC INTO UPSTATE NEW
YORK...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 500 AM EDT...0900 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...38.2N 79.1W
ABOUT 110 MI...180 KM N OF DANVILLE VIRGINIA
ABOUT 165 MI...270 KM N OF RALEIGH NORTH CAROLINA
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...30 MPH...45 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...NNE OR 20 DEGREES AT 35 MPH...56 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...1003 MB...29.62 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
Flood Watches and Warnings are in effect for portions of....
* South Carolina
* North Carolina
* Virginia
* Maryland
 
A Flood Watch is in effect for portions of...
* Eastern West Virginia
* Pennsylvania
* New Jersey
* Delaware
* Upstate New York
* Northern Vermont
* Northern New Hampshire
 
A Tornado Watch is in effect for portions of...
* Eastern North Carolina
* Northern and Eastern Virginia
* Maryland
* District of Columbia
* Eastern West Virginia
 
Coastal Flood Advisories and Warnings are in effect for portions
of...
* Coastal Mid-Atlantic
 
A Gale Warning is in effect for the coastal waters of...
* Mid-Atlantic
* Southern New England
 
Wind Advisories are in effect for portions of...
* Western Virginia
* Eastern Maryland
* Delaware
* Eastern Pennsylvania
* New Jersey
* Southern New York
* Southern Connecticut
* Northeast New York
* Vermont
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 500 AM EDT (0900 UTC), the center of Post-Tropical Cyclone Debby
was located near latitude 38.2 North, longitude 79.1 West. The
post-tropical cyclone is moving toward the north-northeast near 35
mph (56 km/h) and this motion is expected to continue, with a 
gradual turn more to the northeast.
 
Maximum sustained winds are near 30 mph (45 km/h) with higher gusts.
Some increase in winds are possible as the system transitions 
to an extratropical cyclone. 
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 1003 mb (29.62 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Debby can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT4 and WMO header WTNT44 KNHC.
 
RAINFALL: Debby is expected to produce an additional 1 to 3 inches
of rainfall with locally higher amounts, across portions of the
coastal Carolinas today, with areas of considerable flooding
expected.
 
From portions of northern Virginia through Upstate New York, 2 to 4
inches of rainfall, with local amounts to 6 inches, are expected
through Friday night. This will likely result in areas of
considerable flash and urban flooding, as well as river flooding.
 
For portions of Northern New England, 1 to 3 inches of rain with
locally higher amounts are expected through Friday night. This will
result in isolated to scattered instances of flash flooding.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall and flash flooding
associated with  Debby, please see the National Weather Service
Storm Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?rainqpf and the Flash Flood Risk
graphic at hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?ero.  For a list of
rainfall observations (and wind reports) associated this storm, see
the companion storm summary at WBCSCCNS4 with the WMO header ACUS44
KWBC or at the following link:
www.wpc.ncep.noaa.gov/discussions/nfdscc4.html.
 
TORNADOES: The risk for a couple of tornadoes will extend from
eastern North Carolina into Virginia and Maryland early this
morning. The threat for tornadoes will shift northward into New
Jersey, eastern Pennsylvania and eastern New York today.
 
WIND: Wind gusts of 30-50 MPH will be possible today into tonight
across portions of eastern Maryland, Delaware, southeast
Pennsylvania, New Jersey, far southeast New York into Long Island,
coastal Connecticut, and far northeast New York into Vermont. Given
saturated ground conditions these winds may bring down trees and
result in isolated to scattered power outages.
 
SURF:  Large swells will continue to affect the Southeast,
Mid-Atlantic and Southern New England coast. These conditions are
likely to cause life-threatening surf and rip current conditions.
Please consult products from your local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 1100 AM EDT.
 
$$
Forecaster Chenard
 
NNNN

</message>
</cycloneMessage>
