<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL192024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>INTERMEDIATE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>4</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>7A</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20241115 06:00:00 AM CST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20241115 12:00:00 PM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20241115120000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0600 AM CST Fri Nov 15</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1731672000</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL STORM</systemType>
<systemName>SARA</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>16.1</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-85.5</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>16.1N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>85.5W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>50</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>80</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>45</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>998</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.47</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>W OR 280 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>9</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>15</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>8</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 40 MI...60 KM SE OF ISLA GUANAJA HONDURAS</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 205 MI...330 KM ESE OF BELIZE CITY</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT4 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Storm Sara Intermediate Advisory Number 7A
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL192024
600 AM CST Fri Nov 15 2024
 
...SARA NEAR THE NORTH COAST OF HONDURAS...
...HEAVY RAINFALL LIKELY TO CAUSE FLASH FLOODING AND MUDSLIDES INTO 
EARLY NEXT WEEK FOR PORTIONS OF CENTRAL AMERICA... 
 
 
SUMMARY OF 600 AM CST...1200 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...16.1N 85.5W
ABOUT 40 MI...60 KM SE OF ISLA GUANAJA HONDURAS
ABOUT 205 MI...330 KM ESE OF BELIZE CITY
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...50 MPH...80 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...W OR 280 DEGREES AT 9 MPH...15 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...998 MB...29.47 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The government of Honduras has extended the Tropical Storm Warning 
westward from Punta Sal to the border of Honduras and Guatemala. 

The government of Guatemala has issued a Tropical Storm Warning 
from the border of Honduras and Guatemala westward to Punta Barrios.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* The entire northern coast of Honduras
* The Bay Islands of Honduras
* The northern coast of Guatemala from the Honduras/Guatemala 
border westward to Puerto Barrios
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area.
 
Interests elsewhere in Belize, and the Yucatan Peninsula should 
monitor the progress of this system. Tropical Storm Watches or 
Warnings will likely be required for portions of the coast of Belize 
later this morning.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 600 AM CST (1200 UTC), the center of Tropical Storm Sara was
located near latitude 16.1 North, longitude 85.5 West. Sara is
moving toward the west near 9 mph (15 km/h). A continued westward
motion at a slower forward speed is expected over the next day or
so. A slow west-northwestward motion is forecast by late Saturday.
On the forecast track, the center of Sara will continue to move
close to the northern coast of Honduras through early Saturday, then
approach the coast of Belize early Sunday.
 
Maximum sustained winds have increased to near 50 mph (80 km/h) with 
higher gusts. Some slight strengthening is possible during the next 
couple of days if the center of Sara remains over water to the 
north of Honduras.
 
Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 105 miles (165 km)
from the center.
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 998 mb (29.47 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key Messages for Tropical Storm Sara can be found in the Tropical
Cyclone Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT4 and WMO header
WTNT44 KNHC and on the web at hurricanes.gov/text/MIATCDAT4.shtml
 
RAINFALL: Through early next week, rainfall amounts of 10 to 20
inches with isolated storm totals around 30 inches area expected
over northern Honduras. This rainfall will lead to widespread areas
of life-threatening and potentially catastrophic flash flooding and
mudslides, especially along and near the Sierra La Esperanza.
 
Elsewhere across the rest of Honduras, Belize, El Salvador, eastern
Guatemala, western Nicaragua, and the Mexican State of Quintana Roo,
Sara is expected to produce 5 to 10 inches of rain with localized
totals around 15 inches through early next week. This will result in
areas of flash flooding, perhaps significant, along with the
potential of mudslides.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall associated with
Tropical Storm Sara, please see the National Weather Service Storm
Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/refresh/graphics_at4+shtml/205755.shtml?
rainqpf#contents
 
WIND: Tropical storm conditions are expected in the warning area in
Honduras and Guatemala during the next couple of days.
 
STORM SURGE: Storm surge could raise water levels by as much as 1 to 
3 feet above normal tide levels along the immediate coast in areas 
of onshore winds along the northern coast of Honduras and Guatemala. 
Near the coast, the surge will be accompanied by large and 
destructive waves.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 900 AM CST.
 
$$
Forecaster Papin
 
NNNN
 
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
