<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>EP102024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>ROUTINE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>5</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>12</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240925 03:00:00 PM CST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240925 09:00:00 PM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20240925210000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0300 PM CST Wed Sep 25</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1727298000</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL STORM</systemType>
<systemName>JOHN</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>16.8</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-101.5</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>16.8N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>101.5W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>50</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>85</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>45</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>996</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.42</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>N OR 355 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>3</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>6</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>3</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 105 MI...170 KM W OF ACAPULCO MEXICO</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 60 MI...100 KM S OF ZIHUATANEJO MEXICO</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPEP5 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Storm John Advisory Number  12
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       EP102024
300 PM CST Wed Sep 25 2024
 
...JOHN EXPECTED TO BECOME A HURRICANE...
...HURRICANE WARNING ISSUED FOR SOUTHWESTERN MEXICO...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 300 PM CST...2100 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...16.8N 101.5W
ABOUT 105 MI...170 KM W OF ACAPULCO MEXICO
ABOUT 60 MI...100 KM S OF ZIHUATANEJO MEXICO
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...50 MPH...85 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...N OR 355 DEGREES AT 3 MPH...6 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...996 MB...29.42 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The government of Mexico has issued a Hurricane Warning for the
coast of Mexico from Tecpan de Galeana to Lazaro Cardenas.
 
The government of Mexico has issued a Hurricane Watch for
the coast of Mexico from west of Lazaro Cardenas to Punta San Telmo.
 
The government of Mexico has issued a Tropical Storm Warning for
the coast of Mexico from west of Lazaro Cardenas to Punta San Telmo.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Hurricane Warning is in effect for...
* Tecpan de Galeana to Lazaro Cardenas
 
A Hurricane Watch is in effect for...
* Acapulco to Tecpan de Galeana
* Lazaro Cardenas to Punta San Telmo
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* Punta Maldonado to Acapulco
* Lazaro Cardenas to Punta San Telmo
 
A Hurricane Warning means that hurricane conditions are expected
somewhere within the warning area, this is case within 12 to 24
hours.  Preparations to protect life and property should be rushed
to completion.
 
A Hurricane Watch means that hurricane conditions are possible
within the watch area, in this case within 12 hours.
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area, in this case within 12
hours.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 300 PM CST (2100 UTC), the center of Tropical Storm John was
located near latitude 16.8 North, longitude 101.5 West. John is
moving toward the north near 3 mph (6 km/h). This motion should
continue for the next day or so, followed by a gradual turn to the
west-northwest on Friday.  On the forecast track, the center of John
is forecast to approach the southwestern coast of Mexico on early
Thursday and be inland on Friday.
 
Maximum sustained winds have increased to near 50 mph (85 km/h) with
higher gusts.  John is forecast to strengthen as it approaches the
coast of southern Mexico on Thursday.
 
Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 150 miles (240 km)
from the center.
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 996 mb (29.42 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
RAINFALL: Through Friday, Tropical Storm John is expected to produce
additional rainfall amounts of 10 to 20 inches with isolated totals
around 30 inches across portions of the Mexican States of Guerrero,
Oaxaca and Michoacan.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall associated with John,
please see the National Weather Service Storm Total Rainfall
Graphic, available at hurricanes.gov/graphics_ep5.shtml?rainqpf
 
STORM SURGE: A dangerous storm surge is expected to produce coastal
flooding near and to the east of where the center makes landfall.
Near the coast, the surge will be accompanied by large and
destructive waves.
 
WIND: Hurricane conditions are expected along the coast within the
hurricane warning area Thursday.  Winds are expected to first reach
tropical storm strength as early as tonight, making outside
preparations difficult or dangerous.  Preparations to protect life
and property should be rushed to completion.
 
Tropical storm conditions are expected to first reach the coast
within the tropical storm warning area as early as tonight.
 
SURF: Swells associated with John are forecast to continue to
affect the coast of southern Mexico through the week, with the
potential for dangerous surf and rip currents.  Please see local
statements for more information.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next intermediate advisory at 600 PM CST.
Next complete advisory at 900 PM CST.
 
$$
Forecaster Bucci/R. Zelinsky
 
NNNN
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
