<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>EP102024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>INTERMEDIATE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>5</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>13A</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240926 12:00:00 AM CST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240926 06:00:00 AM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20240926060000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>1200 AM CST Thu Sep 26</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1727330400</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL STORM</systemType>
<systemName>JOHN</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>17.0</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-102.4</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>17.0N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>102.4W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>70</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>110</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>60</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>982</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>28.99</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>NW OR 310 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>5</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>7</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>4</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 70 MI...110 KM S OF LAZARO CARDENAS MEXICO</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 75 MI...115 KM SW OF ZIHUATANEJO MEXICO</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPEP5 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Storm John Intermediate Advisory Number 13A
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       EP102024
1200 AM CST Thu Sep 26 2024
 
...JOHN NEARING HURRICANE STRENGTH...
...CATASTROPHIC LIFE-THREATENING FLASH FLOODING AND MUDSLIDES 
CONTINUE OVER PORTIONS OF SOUTHERN MEXICO...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 1200 AM CST...0600 UTC...INFORMATION
-----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...17.0N 102.4W
ABOUT 70 MI...110 KM S OF LAZARO CARDENAS MEXICO
ABOUT 75 MI...115 KM SW OF ZIHUATANEJO MEXICO
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...70 MPH...110 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...NW OR 310 DEGREES AT 5 MPH...7 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...982 MB...28.99 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
None.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Hurricane Warning is in effect for...
* Tecpan de Galeana to Punta San Telmo
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* Punta Maldonado to Tecpan de Galeana
 
A Hurricane Warning means that hurricane conditions are expected
somewhere within the warning area, in this case within 24 to 36
hours.  Preparations to protect life and property should be rushed
to completion.
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area, in this case within 12
hours.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 1200 AM CST (0600 UTC), the center of Tropical Storm John was
located near latitude 17.0 North, longitude 102.4 West.  John is
moving toward the northwest near 5 mph (7 km/h) and this motion is
expected to continue for the next day or two, followed by a gradual
turn to the west-northwest on Friday.  On the forecast track, the
center of John is forecast to approach the southwestern coast of
Mexico by tonight and move along the coast or inland on Friday.
 
Maximum sustained winds have increased to near 70 mph (110 km/h) 
with higher gusts. John is forecast to strengthen to a hurricane 
later today, with additional strengthening expected until the center 
moves along the coast or inland.
 
Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 150 miles (240 km)
from the center.
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 982 mb (28.99 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
RAINFALL: Through Friday, Tropical Storm John is expected to produce
additional rainfall amounts of 10 to 20 inches with isolated totals
around 30 inches across portions of the Mexican States of Guerrero,
Oaxaca and Michoacan.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall associated with John,
please see the National Weather Service Storm Total Rainfall
Graphic, available at hurricanes.gov/graphics_ep5.shtml?rainqpf
 
STORM SURGE: A dangerous storm surge is expected to produce coastal
flooding near and to the east of where the center makes landfall.
Near the coast, the surge will be accompanied by large and
destructive waves.
 
WIND: Hurricane conditions are expected along the coast within the
hurricane warning area by tonight or early Friday.  Winds are 
expected to first reach tropical storm strength later this morning, 
making outside preparations difficult or dangerous.  Preparations 
to protect life and property should be rushed to completion.
 
Tropical storm conditions are currently occurring over portions of
the coast within the tropical storm warning area, and should
continue through today.
 
SURF: Swells associated with John are forecast to continue to
affect the coast of southern and southwestern Mexico through the
week, with the potential for dangerous surf and rip currents.
Please see local statements for more information.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 300 AM CST.
 
$$
Forecaster Roberts
 
NNNN
 
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
