<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL042024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>ROUTINE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>4</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>12</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240805 05:00:00 AM EDT</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240805 09:00:00 AM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20240805090000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0500 AM EDT Mon Aug 05</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1722848400</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>HURRICANE</systemType>
<systemName>DEBBY</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>29.5</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-83.7</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>29.5N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>83.7W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>80</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>130</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>70</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>979</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>28.91</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>CATEGORY 1</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>NNE OR 15 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>10</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>17</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>9</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 45 MI...75 KM NW OF CEDAR KEY FLORIDA</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 70 MI...115 KM SSE OF TALLAHASSEE FLORIDA</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT4 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Hurricane Debby Advisory Number  12
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL042024
500 AM EDT Mon Aug 05 2024
 
...DEBBY VERY NEAR LANDFALL IN THE FLORIDA BIG BEND...
...EXPECTED TO BRING LIFE-THREATENING STORM SURGE IN PORTIONS OF
FLORIDA AND MAJOR FLOODING IN THE SOUTHEASTERN UNITED STATES...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 500 AM EDT...0900 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...29.5N 83.7W
ABOUT 45 MI...75 KM NW OF CEDAR KEY FLORIDA
ABOUT 70 MI...115 KM SSE OF TALLAHASSEE FLORIDA
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...80 MPH...130 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...NNE OR 15 DEGREES AT 10 MPH...17 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...979 MB...28.91 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
None
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Storm Surge Warning is in effect for...
* Florida coast from the middle of Longboat Key northward to Indian
Pass including Tampa Bay
* Georgia and South Carolina coast from the Mouth of the St. Mary's
River to South Santee River South Carolina
 
A Storm Surge Watch is in effect for...
* Florida coast from Englewood northward to the middle of
Longboat Key, including Charlotte Harbor
 
A Hurricane Warning is in effect for...
* Florida coast from the Yankeetown to Indian Pass
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* Florida coast south of Yankeetown to Boca Grande
* Florida coast from west of Indian Pass to Mexico Beach
* St. Augustine to South Santee River South Carolina
 
A Hurricane Warning means that hurricane conditions are expected
somewhere within the warning area.  Preparations to protect life
and property should be rushed to completion.
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area within 36 hours.
 
A Storm Surge Warning means there is a danger of life-threatening
inundation, from rising water moving inland from the coastline. For
a depiction of areas at risk, please see the National Weather
Service Storm Surge Watch/Warning Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov.
 
This is a life-threatening situation.  Persons located within these
areas should take all necessary actions to protect life and property
from rising water and the potential for other dangerous conditions.
Promptly follow evacuation and other instructions from local
officials.
 
A Storm Surge Watch means there is a possibility of life-
threatening inundation, from rising water moving inland from the
coastline. For a depiction of areas at risk, please see the National
Weather Service Storm Surge Watch/Warning Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov.
 
Interests elsewhere along the southeastern coast of the United
States should monitor the progress of this system. Additional
watches and warnings will likely be required later today.
 
For storm information specific to your area, including possible
inland watches and warnings, please monitor products issued by your
local National Weather Service forecast office.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 500 AM EDT (0900 UTC), the center of Hurricane Debby was located
near latitude 29.5 North, longitude 83.7 West. Debby is moving
toward the north-northeast near 12 mph (19 km/h). A gradual decrease
in forward speed with a turn toward the northeast and east is
expected later today and Tuesday.  On the forecast track, the
center will reach the Florida Big Bend coast later this morning.
Debby is then expected to move slowly across northern Florida and
southern Georgia late today and Tuesday, and be near the Georgia
coast by Tuesday night.
 
Maximum sustained winds are near 80 mph (130 km/h) with higher
gusts.  Weakening is expected after Debby moves inland.
 
Hurricane-force winds extend outward up to 25 miles (35 km) from the
center and tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 140 miles
(220 km).
 
The estimated minimum central pressure based on data from the Air
Force Hurricane Hunters is 979 mb (28.91 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Debby can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT4 and WMO header WTNT44 KNHC.
 
WIND: Hurricane conditions are expected in the hurricane warning
area later this morning. Tropical storm conditions will continue to
spread northward over the tropical storm warning area along the
Florida Gulf coast through the morning, and begin along portions of
the tropical storm warning area along the Atlantic coast by this
evening. Tropical storm conditions are expected along the coast of
South Carolina within the tropical storm warning area by late
tonight.
 
STORM SURGE: The combination of storm surge and tide will cause
normally dry areas near the coast to be flooded by rising waters
moving inland from the shoreline. The water could reach the
following heights above ground somewhere in the indicated areas if
the peak surge occurs at the time of high tide...
 
Yankeetown, FL to Ochlockonee River, FL...6-10 ft
Chassahowitzka, FL to Yankeetown, FL...4-6 ft
Ochlockonee River, FL to Indian Pass, FL...4-6 ft
Middle of Longboat Key, FL to Chassahowitzka, FL...3-5 ft
Tampa Bay...3-5 ft
Mouth of the St. Mary's River to South Santee River, SC...2-4 ft
Middle of Longboat Key, FL to Englewood, FL...2-4 ft
 
For a complete depiction of areas at risk of storm surge inundation,
please see the National Weather Service Peak Storm Surge Graphic,
available at hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?peakSurge.
 
RAINFALL: Debby is expected to produce rainfall totals of 6 to 12
inches, with maximum amounts of 18 inches, across portions of
central and northern Florida as well as central and northeast North
Carolina through Saturday morning.  This rainfall will likely result
in areas of considerable flash and urban flooding, with significant
river flooding expected.
 
Across portions of southeast Georgia, the coastal plain of South
Carolina, and southeast North Carolina, 10 to 20 inches of rainfall,
with local amounts to 30 inches, are expected through Saturday
morning.  This potentially historic rainfall will likely result in
areas of catastrophic flooding.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall and flash flooding
associated with Hurricane Debby, please see the National Weather
Service Storm Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?rainqpf and the Flash Flood Risk
graphic at hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?ero.  For a list of
rainfall observations (and wind reports) associated this storm, see
the companion storm summary at WBCSCCNS4 with the WMO header ACUS44
KWBC or at the following link:
www.wpc.ncep.noaa.gov/discussions/nfdscc4.html.
 
TORNADOES: A few tornadoes are possible over central and northern
Florida and southeastern Georgia today.  The threat will spread
northeastward into parts of South Carolina later today and tonight.
 
SURF:  Swells generated by Debby are expected to affect much of the
Gulf coast of Florida through tonight.  Swells will begin to affect
the Southeast U.S. coast later today and continue through the
middle of the week. These conditions are likely to cause
life-threatening surf and rip current conditions. Please consult
products from your local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next intermediate advisory at 800 AM EDT.
Next complete advisory at 1100 AM EDT.
 
$$
Forecaster Cangialosi
 
NNNN
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
