<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL162024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>INTERMEDIATE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>1</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>5A</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20241020 08:00:00 AM EDT</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20241020 12:00:00 PM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20241020120000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0800 AM EDT Sun Oct 20</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1729425600</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>HURRICANE</systemType>
<systemName>OSCAR</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>20.8</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-73.6</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>20.8N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>73.6W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>80</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>130</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>70</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>986</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.12</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>CATEGORY 1</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>WSW OR 250 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>12</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>19</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>10</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 10 MI...20 KM SW OF GREAT INAGUA ISLAND</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 115 MI...185 KM ENE OF GUANTANAMO CUBA</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT1 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Hurricane Oscar Intermediate Advisory Number 5A
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL162024
800 AM EDT Sun Oct 20 2024
 
...AIR FORCE RECONNAISSANCE FINDS OSCAR JUST SOUTHWEST OF THE COAST 
OF GREAT INAGUA ISLAND...
...EXPECTED TO REACH GUANTANAMO OR HOLGUIN CUBA AS A HURRICANE 
LATER TODAY...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 800 AM EDT...1200 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...20.8N 73.6W
ABOUT 10 MI...20 KM SW OF GREAT INAGUA ISLAND
ABOUT 115 MI...185 KM ENE OF GUANTANAMO CUBA
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...80 MPH...130 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...WSW OR 250 DEGREES AT 12 MPH...19 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...986 MB...29.12 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The government of the Bahamas has discontinued the Tropical Storm 
Warning for the the Turks and Caicos Islands. 
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Hurricane Warning is in effect for...
* Southeastern Bahamas
* North coast of the Cuban Provinces of Holguin and Guantanamo to
Punta Maisi
 
A Hurricane Watch is in effect for...
* North coast of the Cuban Province of Las Tunas
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* South coast of Cuban Province of Guantanamo
* North coast of the Cuban Province of Las Tunas
 
A Tropical Storm Watch is in effect for...
* North coast of the Cuban Province of Camaguey
 
A Hurricane Warning means that hurricane conditions are expected
somewhere within the warning area. Preparations to protect life
and property should be rushed to completion.
 
A Hurricane Watch means that hurricane conditions are possible
within the watch area. A watch is typically issued 48 hours
before the anticipated first occurrence of tropical-storm-force
winds, conditions that make outside preparations difficult or
dangerous.
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area within 36 hours.
 
A Tropical Storm Watch means that tropical storm conditions are
possible within the watch area, generally within 48 hours.
 
Interests in the central Bahamas should monitor the progress of
Oscar.  Tropical storm watches could be required for this area
later today.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 800 AM EDT (1200 UTC), the center of Hurricane Oscar was located 
near latitude 20.8 North, longitude 73.6 West.  Oscar is moving 
toward the west-southwest near 12 mph (19 km/h).  A continued  
west-southwestward motion at a slower forward speed is expected 
through tonight, followed by a turn toward the northwest and north 
on Monday and Tuesday.  On the forecast track, the center of Oscar 
will move away from Great Inagua later this morning before making 
landfall along the northeastern coast of Cuba later this afternoon 
or evening. The system is then expected to move across eastern Cuba 
tonight and Monday.  Oscar will then accelerate northeastward across 
the central Bahamas on Tuesday.
 
Maximum sustained winds as recently reported by Air Force 
Reconnaissance data remains near 80 mph (130 km/h) with higher 
gusts.  Oscar is expected to reach the northeastern coast of Cuba as 
a hurricane later this afternoon. Weakening is expected after 
landfall, but Oscar could still be a tropical storm when it moves 
north of Cuba late Monday and moves across the central Bahamas on 
Tuesday.
 
Hurricane-force winds extend outward up to 5 miles (10 km) from the
center and tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 45 miles
(75 km).
 
The minimum central pressure measured by aircraft dropsonde data is 
986 mb (29.12 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Oscar can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT1 and WMO header WTNT41 KNHC
and on the web at hurricanes.gov/text/MIATCDAT1.shtml
 
WIND:  Hurricane conditions will continue across portions of the
warning area in the southeastern Bahamas, particularly Great Inagua
Island, through this morning.  Hurricane conditions are expected in
the warning area in Cuba late this afternoon and evening.
 
Tropical storm conditions are expected in the warning area and
possible in the watch area of Cuba this afternoon into Monday.
 
RAINFALL: Through Tuesday, rainfall amounts of 5 to 10 inches with
isolated amounts of 15 inches are expected across eastern Cuba.
Across the southeastern Bahamas, 2 to 4 inches are expected, with
isolated amounts around 6 inches.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall associated with
Hurricane Oscar, please see the National Weather Service Storm Total
Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at1.shtml?rainqpf .
 
STORM SURGE: A dangerous storm surge is expected to produce
significant coastal flooding on Great Inagua Island in the
southeastern Bahamas, where water levels are expected to be between
2 and 4 feet above normal tide levels.  Water levels of 1 to 3 ft
above normal tide levels are expected along the north shore of Cuba
in areas of onshore winds.  Near the coast, the surge will be
accompanied by large and destructive waves.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 1100 AM EDT.
 
$$
Forecaster Papin
 
NNNN
 
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
