<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL052024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>ROUTINE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>5</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>13</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240814 05:00:00 PM AST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240814 09:00:00 PM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20240814210000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0500 PM AST Wed Aug 14</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1723669200</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>HURRICANE</systemType>
<systemName>ERNESTO</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>21.7</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-68.3</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>21.7N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>68.3W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>75</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>120</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>65</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>989</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.21</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>CATEGORY 1</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>NW OR 325 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>16</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>26</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>14</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 180 MI...290 KM E OF GRAND TURK ISLAND</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 765 MI...1230 KM SSW OF BERMUDA</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT5 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Hurricane Ernesto Advisory Number  13
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL052024
500 PM AST Wed Aug 14 2024
 
...ERNESTO EXPECTED TO STRENGTHEN OVER THE WESTERN ATLANTIC...
...HURRICANE WATCH ISSUED FOR BERMUDA...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 500 PM AST...2100 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...21.7N 68.3W
ABOUT 180 MI...290 KM E OF GRAND TURK ISLAND
ABOUT 765 MI...1230 KM SSW OF BERMUDA
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...75 MPH...120 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...NW OR 325 DEGREES AT 16 MPH...26 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...989 MB...29.21 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The Bermuda Weather Service has issued a Hurricane Watch for
Bermuda.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Hurricane Watch is in effect for...
* Bermuda
 
A Hurricane Watch means that hurricane conditions are possible
within the watch area.  A watch is typically issued 48 hours
before the anticipated first occurrence of tropical-storm-force
winds, conditions that make outside preparations difficult or
dangerous.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 500 PM AST (2100 UTC), the center of Hurricane Ernesto was
located near latitude 21.7 North, longitude 68.3 West.  Ernesto is
moving toward the northwest near 16 mph (26 km/h).  A turn toward 
the north-northwest and north is expected tonight and on Thursday.  
A northward to northeastward motion at a slower forward speed is 
expected Friday and Saturday.  On the forecast track, the center of 
Ernesto is expected to pass near Bermuda on Saturday.
 
Maximum sustained winds are near 75 mph (120 km/h) with higher
gusts.  Strengthening is forecast during the next couple of days, 
and Ernesto could become a major hurricane by Friday.
 
Hurricane-force winds extend outward up to 35 miles (55 km) from the
center and tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 175 miles
(280 km).
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 989 mb (29.21 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Ernesto can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT5 and WMO header WTNT45 KNHC
and on the web at hurricanes.gov/text/MIATCDAT5.shtml.
 
WIND:  Hurricane conditions are possible on Bermuda Saturday, with
tropical storm conditions possible by Friday afternoon.
 
RAINFALL: Ernesto is expected to produce total rain accumulations 
of 3 to 6 inches on Bermuda with isolated maximum amounts of 9 
inches.  This rainfall may result in considerable life-threatening 
flash flooding.

Rainfall is expected to diminish this evening across Puerto Rico and 
the U.S. and British Virgin Islands.  Total rainfall amounts from 
Ernesto are expected to be in the 6 to 10 inch range, with maximum 
amounts of 12 inches across southern to eastern Puerto Rico, 3 to 6 
inches across northwestern Puerto Rico, and 4 to 6 inches across the 
U.S and British Virgin Islands.

For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall associated with 
Hurricane Ernesto, please see the National Weather Service Storm 
Total Rainfall Graphic, available at 
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at5.shtml?rainqpf
 
SURF: Swells generated by Ernesto are affecting portions of the
northern Leeward Islands, the Virgin Islands, Puerto Rico, the
Dominican Republic, and the Turks and Caicos Islands.  These swells
will reach the southeastern Bahamas tonight, and Bermuda and the
rest of the Bahamas on Thursday.  Swells are expected to reach the
east coast of the United States Thursday night and continue into the
weekend. These swells are likely to cause life-threatening surf and
rip current conditions.  Please consult products from your local
weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next intermediate advisory at 800 PM AST.
Next complete advisory at 1100 PM AST.
 
$$
Forecaster Berg
 
NNNN
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
