<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL052024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>ROUTINE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>5</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>23</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240817 05:00:00 AM AST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240817 09:00:00 AM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20240817090000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0500 AM AST Sat Aug 17</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1723885200</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>HURRICANE</systemType>
<systemName>ERNESTO</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>32.3</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-64.8</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>32.3N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>64.8W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>85</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>140</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>75</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>972</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>28.71</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>CATEGORY 1</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>NNE OR 20 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>9</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>15</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>8</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 0 MI...0 KM N OF BERMUDA</systemGeoRefPt1>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT5 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Hurricane Ernesto Advisory Number  23
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL052024
500 AM AST Sat Aug 17 2024
 
...ERNESTO MAKES LANDFALL ON BERMUDA...
...STRONG WINDS, DANGEROUS STORM SURGE, AND LIFE-THREATENING
FLOODING EXPECTED TO CONTINUE ON BERMUDA TODAY...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 500 AM AST...0900 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...32.3N 64.8W
ABOUT 0 MI...0 KM N OF BERMUDA
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...85 MPH...140 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...NNE OR 20 DEGREES AT 9 MPH...15 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...972 MB...28.71 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
None.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Hurricane Warning is in effect for...
* Bermuda
 
A Hurricane Warning means that hurricane conditions are expected
somewhere within the warning area.
 
Interests in Atlantic Canada should monitor the progress of Ernesto.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
Surface observations indicate that Ernesto made landfall on the 
western side of Bermuda around 430 AM AST (0830 UTC). At 500 AM AST 
(0900 UTC), the center of Hurricane Ernesto was located near 
latitude 32.3 North, longitude 64.8 West. Ernesto is moving toward 
the north-northeast near 9 mph (15 km/h), and this general motion is 
expected today.  A faster northeastward motion is then expected late 
this weekend into early next week.  On the forecast track, the 
center of Ernesto is expected to slowly depart Bermuda today and 
move near or east of Newfoundland Monday night.
 
Maximum sustained winds have decreased to near 85 mph (140 km/h)
with higher gusts.  Little change in strength is forecast today.
Some re-intensification is possible late in the weekend before
weakening begins on Monday.
 
Ernesto is a large tropical cyclone. Hurricane-force winds extend
outward up to 70 miles (110 km) from the center and tropical-storm-
force winds extend outward up to 240 miles (390 km).

The estimated minimum central pressure is 972 mb (28.71 inches).  
The National Museum on Bermuda recently reported a central pressure 
of 972 mb (28.71 mb).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Ernesto can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT5 and WMO header WTNT45 KNHC
and on the web at hurricanes.gov/text/MIATCDAT5.shtml.
 
WIND:  Hurricane conditions are expected on Bermuda through the
next several hours.  Due to Ernesto's large size and slow motion,
strong winds will continue on the island through most of today.
 
STORM SURGE: A dangerous storm surge is expected to produce
significant coastal flooding on Bermuda in areas of onshore winds.
Near the coast, the surge will be accompanied by large and
destructive waves.
 
RAINFALL: Ernesto is expected to produce total rain accumulations of
6 to 9 inches or 150 to 225 mm on Bermuda. This rainfall will likely
result in considerable life-threatening flash flooding, especially
in low-lying areas on the island.
 
SURF: Swells generated by Ernesto are affecting portions of the the 
Bahamas, Bermuda, and the east coast of the United States. These 
swells will likely reach portions of Atlantic Canada by tonight.  
Life-threatening surf and rip current conditions are likely in these 
areas during the next couple of days.  Please consult products from 
your local weather office, and stay out of the water if advised by 
lifeguards.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next intermediate advisory at 800 AM AST.
Next complete advisory at 1100 AM AST.
 
$$
Forecaster Blake
 
NNNN
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
