<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL022024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>INTERMEDIATE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>2</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>7A</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240630 08:00:00 AM AST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240630 12:00:00 PM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>202406301200</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0800 AM AST Sun Jun 30</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1719748800</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>HURRICANE</systemType>
<systemName>BERYL</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>10.6</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-53.9</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>10.6N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>53.9W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>115</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>185</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>100</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>968</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>28.58</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>CATEGORY 3</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>W OR 280 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>21</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>33</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>18</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 420 MI...675 KM ESE OF BARBADOS</systemGeoRefPt1>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT2 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM CCA
 
BULLETIN
Hurricane Beryl Intermediate Advisory Number 7A...Corrected
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL022024
800 AM AST Sun Jun 30 2024

Corrected maximum sustained winds in Summary

...BERYL IS NOW A VERY DANGEROUS CATEGORY 3 HURRICANE...
...LIFE-THREATENING WINDS AND STORM SURGE EXPECTED IN THE 
WINDWARD ISLANDS BEGINNING EARLY MONDAY...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 800 AM AST...1200 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...10.6N 53.9W
ABOUT 420 MI...675 KM ESE OF BARBADOS
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...115 MPH...185 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...W OR 280 DEGREES AT 21 MPH...33 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...968 MB...28.58 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The government of Trinidad has upgraded the Tropical Storm Warning 
to a Hurricane Warning for Tobago.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Hurricane Warning is in effect for...
* Barbados
* St. Lucia
* St. Vincent and the Grenadine Islands
* Grenada
* Tobago
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* Martinique
 
A Tropical Storm Watch is in effect for...
* Dominica
 
A Hurricane Warning means that hurricane conditions are expected
somewhere within the warning area.  Preparations to protect life
and property should be rushed to completion.
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area within 36 hours.
 
A Tropical Storm Watch means that tropical storm conditions are
possible within the watch area, generally within 48 hours.
 
Interests elsewhere in the Lesser Antilles should closely monitor
the progress of Beryl.  Additional watches and warnings may be
required later today.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 800 AM AST (1200 UTC), the eye of Hurricane Beryl was located
near latitude 10.6 North, longitude 53.9 West. Beryl is moving
toward the west near 21 mph (33 km/h).  A continued quick westward
to west-northwestward motion is expected during the next few days.
On the forecast track, the center of Beryl is expected to move
across the Windward Islands early on Monday and across the
southeastern Caribbean Sea Monday night and Tuesday.
 
Aircraft data indicate that the maximum sustained winds have 
increased to near 115 mph (185 km/h) with higher gusts, making 
Beryl a very dangerous category 3 hurricane.  Continued rapid 
strengthening is forecast over the next day or so, and Beryl is 
expected to become an extremely dangerous category 4 hurricane 
before it reaches the Windward Islands.
 
Hurricane-force winds extend outward up to 15 miles (30 km) from
the center and tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 80
miles (130 km).
 
The minimum central pressure based on data from the Air Force 
Hurricane Hunters is 968 mb (28.58 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Beryl can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT2 and WMO header WTNT42 KNHC.
 
WIND: Hurricane conditions are expected in the hurricane warning
area beginning early on Monday.  Devastating wind damage is expected
where the eyewall of Beryl moves through portions of the Windward
Islands.
 
Tropical storm conditions are expected in the tropical storm warning
area starting late tonight, making outside preparations difficult or
dangerous.
 
Tropical storm conditions are possible within the watch area
starting late tonight.
 
Wind speeds atop and on the windward sides of hills and mountains
are often up to 30 percent stronger than the near-surface winds
indicated in this advisory, and in some elevated locations could be
even greater.
 
STORM SURGE:  A life-threatening storm surge will raise water levels
by as much as 6 to 9 feet above normal tide levels in areas of
onshore flow near where Beryl makes landfall in the hurricane
warning area.  Near the coast, the surge will be accompanied by
large and destructive waves.
 
RAINFALL:  Hurricane Beryl is expected to produce rainfall totals of
3 to 6 inches across Barbados and the Windward Islands tonight
and Monday. This rainfall may cause flash flooding in vulnerable
areas.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall and flash flooding
associated with Hurricane Beryl, please see the National Weather
Service Storm Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at2.shtml?rainqpf
 
SURF:  Large swells generated by Beryl are expected across 
Windward and southern Leeward Islands during the next couple of 
days.  These swells are expected to cause life-threatening surf and 
rip current conditions. Please consult products from your local 
weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 1100 AM AST.
 
$$
Forecaster Cangialosi
 
NNNN
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
