<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL182024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>ROUTINE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>3</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>7</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20241105 04:00:00 AM EST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20241105 09:00:00 AM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20241105090000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0400 AM EST Tue Nov 05</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1730797200</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL STORM</systemType>
<systemName>RAFAEL</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>17.0</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-78</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>17.0N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>78.0W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>60</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>95</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>50</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>993</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.33</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>NW OR 325 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>13</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>20</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>11</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 105 MI...170 KM SW OF KINGSTON JAMAICA</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 265 MI...425 KM SE OF GRAND CAYMAN</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT3 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Storm Rafael Advisory Number   7
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL182024
400 AM EST Tue Nov 05 2024
 
...RAFAEL STRENGTHENING WHILE IT MOVES NEAR JAMAICA...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 400 AM EST...0900 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...17.0N 78.0W
ABOUT 105 MI...170 KM SW OF KINGSTON JAMAICA
ABOUT 265 MI...425 KM SE OF GRAND CAYMAN
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...60 MPH...95 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...NW OR 325 DEGREES AT 13 MPH...20 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...993 MB...29.33 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
None.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Hurricane Warning is in effect for...
* Cayman Islands
* Cuban provinces of Pinar del Rio, Artemisa, La Habana,
Mayabeque, Matanzas, and the Isle of Youth
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* Jamaica
* Cuban provinces of Villa Clara, Cienfuegos, Sancti Spiritus,
and Ciego de Avila
 
A Tropical Storm Watch is in effect for...
* Cuban provinces of Camaguey and Las Tunas
* Lower and Middle Florida Keys from Key West to west of the
Channel 5 Bridge
* Dry Tortugas
 
A Hurricane Warning means that hurricane conditions are expected
somewhere within the warning area.  A warning is typically issued 36
hours before the anticipated first occurrence of
tropical-storm-force winds, conditions that make outside
preparations difficult or dangerous.  Preparations to protect life
and property should be rushed to completion.
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area.
 
A Tropical Storm Watch means that tropical storm conditions are
possible within the watch area, generally within 48 hours.
 
Interests elsewhere in Cuba should closely monitor this system.
 
For storm information specific to your area in the United
States, including possible inland watches and warnings, please
monitor products issued by your local National Weather Service
forecast office. For storm information specific to your area
outside of the United States, please monitor products issued by
your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 400 AM EST (0900 UTC), the center of Tropical Storm Rafael was
located near latitude 17.0 North, longitude 78.0 West.  Rafael is
moving toward the northwest near 13 mph (20 km/h).  A generally
northwestward motion is anticipated over the next few days.  On the
forecast track, the storm is expected to move near Jamaica this
morning, be near or over the Cayman Islands tonight, and be near or
over western Cuba on Wednesday.
 
Maximum sustained winds have increased to near 60 mph (95 km/h) 
with higher gusts.  Steady to rapid intensification is forecast 
over the next 24 to 36 hours, and Rafael is forecast to become a 
hurricane in the northwestern Caribbean near the Cayman Islands 
with further strengthening before it makes landfall in Cuba.

Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 105 miles (165 km)
from the center.
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 993 mb (29.33 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Tropical Storm Rafael can be found in the
Tropical Cyclone Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT3 and WMO
header WTNT43 KNHC and on the web at
hurricanes.gov/text/MIATCDAT3.shtml
 
WIND:  Hurricane conditions are expected in the Cayman Islands by
this afternoon and are also expected in western Cuba and the Isle
of Youth on Wednesday.  Tropical storm conditions are expected in
Jamaica through early this afternoon and are expected in parts of
west-central Cuba, possible farther east in central Cuba, and in
the lower and middle Florida Keys on Wednesday.
 
RAINFALL: Heavy rainfall will impact areas of the Western Caribbean 
through early Thursday, particularly across Jamaica and the Cayman 
Islands into southern and western portions of Cuba where rainfall 
totals between 3 to 6 inches are expected. Isolated higher totals up 
to 10 inches are anticipated across the higher terrain in Jamaica 
and Cuba, which could lead to areas of flash flooding and mudslides.

Heavy rainfall will spread north into Florida and adjacent areas of 
the Southeast United States during the middle to latter part of the 
week. Rainfall totals of 1 to 3 inches are expected for the Lower 
and Middle Florida Keys. 

For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall associated with 
Tropical Storm Rafael, please see the National Weather Service Storm 
Total Rainfall Graphic, available at 
https://www.nhc.noaa.gov/graphics_at3.shtml?rainqpf

STORM SURGE:  Minor coastal flooding is possible in Jamaica tonight.
Storm surge could raise water levels by 1 to 3 feet above normal
tide levels in the Cayman Islands on Tuesday, and could raise water
levels by as much as 6 to 9 feet above normal tide levels in areas
of onshore winds along the southern coast of Cuba in the Hurricane
Warning area, including the Isle of Youth.
 
The combination of a storm surge and the tide will cause normally
dry areas near the coast to be flooded by rising waters moving
inland from the shoreline.  The water could reach the following
heights above ground somewhere in the indicated areas if the peak
surge occurs at the time of high tide...
 
Dry Tortugas...1-3 ft
Lower Florida Keys...1-2 ft
 
TORNADOES: A few tornadoes are possible Wednesday over the Keys and
southwesternmost Florida mainland.
 
SURF:  Swells generated by Rafael are expected to affect much of
the western Caribbean during the next few days. These swells are
likely to cause life-threatening surf and rip current conditions.
Please consult products from your local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next intermediate advisory at 700 AM EST.
Next complete advisory at 1000 AM EST.
 
$$
Forecaster Pasch/Roberts
 
NNNN
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
