<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL042024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>ROUTINE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>4</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>2</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240802 05:00:00 PM EDT</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240802 09:00:00 PM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20240802210000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0500 PM EDT Fri Aug 02</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1722632400</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>POTENTIAL TROPICAL CYCLONE</systemType>
<systemName>FOUR</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>21.4</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-78.3</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>21.4N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>78.3W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>30</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>45</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>25</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>1012</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.89</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>80</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>90</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>WNW OR 290 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>16</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>26</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>14</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 25 MI...40 KM W OF CAMAGUEY CUBA</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 315 MI...505 KM SE OF KEY WEST FLORIDA</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT4 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Potential Tropical Cyclone Four Advisory Number   2
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL042024
500 PM EDT Fri Aug 02 2024
 
...DISTURBANCE NOW PASSING OVER CENTRAL CUBA...
...NEW WATCHES AND WARNINGS ISSUED FOR PORTIONS OF THE FLORIDA
PENINSULA...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 500 PM EDT...2100 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...21.4N 78.3W
ABOUT 25 MI...40 KM W OF CAMAGUEY CUBA
ABOUT 315 MI...505 KM SE OF KEY WEST FLORIDA
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...30 MPH...45 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...WNW OR 290 DEGREES AT 16 MPH...26 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...1012 MB...29.89 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The Tropical Storm Warning has been extended northward along the
west coast of the Florida Peninsula from Bonita Beach to Boca
Grande.
 
The Tropical Storm Watch has been extended northward along the west
coast of the Florida peninsula from Aripeka to the mouth of the
Suwannee River.
 
A Storm Surge Watch has been issued for the west coast of the
Florida peninsula from Bonita Beach northward to the mouth of the
Suwannee River, including Tampa Bay and Charlotte Harbor.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* Southwest coast of the Florida peninsula from East Cape Sable to
Boca Grande
 
A Tropical Storm Watch is in effect for...
* The Florida Keys south of the Card Sound Bridge including the Dry
Tortugas
* The southern coast of the Florida peninsula east of East Cape
Sable to the Card Sound Bridge
* The west coast of the Florida peninsula north of Boca Grande to
the mouth of the Suwannee River
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area within 36 hours.
 
A Tropical Storm Watch means that tropical storm conditions are
possible within the watch area, generally within 48 hours.
 
A Storm Surge Watch means there is a possibility of life-
threatening inundation, from rising water moving inland from the
coastline, in the indicated locations during the next 48 hours.
For a depiction of areas at risk, please see the National Weather
Service Storm Surge Watch/Warning Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov.
 
Interests elsewhere in the Florida Peninsula and the southeastern
coast of the United States should monitor the progress of this
system. Additional warnings and watches may be required for a
portion of this area tonight and Saturday.
 
For storm information specific to your area, including possible
inland watches and warnings, please monitor products issued by your
local National Weather Service forecast office.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 500 PM EDT (2100 UTC), the disturbance was centered near latitude
21.4 North, longitude 78.3 West. The system is moving toward the
west-northwest near 16 mph (26 km/h).  A turn toward the northwest
at a slower forward speed is expected tonight or Saturday, followed
by a turn toward the north on Sunday.  On the forecast track, the
disturbance is expected to move over Cuba tonight, cross the Straits
of Florida into the southeastern Gulf of Mexico on Saturday, and 
then move near or over the west coast of Florida Saturday night 
through Sunday night.
 
Maximum sustained winds are near 30 mph (45 km/h) with higher gusts.
The disturbance is expected to develop into a tropical depression 
on Saturday as it moves across the Straits of Florida, followed by 
intensification into a tropical storm by Saturday night.
* Formation chance through 48 hours...high...80 percent.
* Formation chance through 7 days...high...90 percent.
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 1012 mb (29.89 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
WINDS: Tropical storm conditions are expected in the warning area
late Saturday and Saturday night.  Tropical storm conditions are
possible in the watch area in the Florida Keys and the southern
Florida peninsula by Saturday or Saturday night. Tropical storm
conditions are possible in the watch area along the Florida west
coast Saturday night or Sunday.
 
STORM SURGE: The combination of storm surge and tide will cause
normally dry areas near the coast to be flooded by rising waters
moving inland from the shoreline.  The water could reach the
following heights above ground somewhere in the indicated areas if
the peak surge occurs at the time of high tide...
 
Bonita Beach, FL to Suwannee River, FL...2-4 ft
Tampa Bay...2-4 ft
Charlotte Harbor...2-4 ft
Card Sound Bridge, FL to Bonita Beach, FL...1-3 ft
 
RAINFALL: Potential Tropical Cyclone Four is expected to produce
rainfall totals of 4 to 8 inches, with maximum rainfall totals up to
12 inches, across portions of Florida and along the Southeast U.S.
coast this weekend through Wednesday morning. This rainfall may
result in areas of flash and urban flooding, with isolated river
flooding possible.
 
For Cuba, rainfall amounts of 1 to 2 inches, with localized higher
amounts, will be possible today into Saturday. This may result in
isolated to scattered areas of flooding.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall and flash flooding
associated with Potential Tropical Cyclone Four, please see the
National Weather Service Storm Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?rainqpf

TORNADOES: A tornado or two is possible across the Florida Keys and 
the western Florida Peninsula Saturday night through Sunday morning.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next intermediate advisory at 800 PM EDT.
Next complete advisory at 1100 PM EDT.
 
$$
Forecaster Beven
 
NNNN
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
