<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL142024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>INTERMEDIATE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>4</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>20A</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20241010 02:00:00 AM EDT</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20241010 06:00:00 AM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20241010060000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0200 AM EDT Thu Oct 10</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1728540000</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>HURRICANE</systemType>
<systemName>MILTON</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>28.1</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-81.3</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>28.1N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>81.3W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>90</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>150</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>80</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>975</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>28.79</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>CATEGORY 1</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>ENE OR 60 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>16</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>26</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>14</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 30 MI...45 KM S OF ORLANDO FLORIDA</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 45 MI...75 KM WSW OF CAPE CANAVERAL FLORIDA</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT4 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Hurricane Milton Intermediate Advisory Number 20A
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL142024
200 AM EDT Thu Oct 10 2024
 
...VERY HEAVY RAINS AND DAMAGING WINDS CONTINUE ACROSS MUCH OF 
CENTRAL FLORIDA...
...FLASH FLOOD EMERGENCIES REMAIN IN EFFECT...

 
SUMMARY OF 200 AM EDT...0600 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...28.1N 81.3W
ABOUT 30 MI...45 KM S OF ORLANDO FLORIDA
ABOUT 45 MI...75 KM WSW OF CAPE CANAVERAL FLORIDA
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...90 MPH...150 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...ENE OR 60 DEGREES AT 16 MPH...26 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...975 MB...28.79 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
None.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Storm Surge Warning is in effect for...
* Florida west coast from Flamingo northward to Anclote River,
including Charlotte Harbor and Tampa Bay
* Sebastian Inlet Florida to Altamaha Sound Georgia, including the
St. Johns River
 
A Hurricane Warning is in effect for...
* Florida west coast from Bonita Beach northward to Suwannee River,
including Tampa Bay
* Florida east coast from the St. Lucie/Martin County Line northward
to Ponte Vedra Beach
 
A Hurricane Watch is in effect for...
* Lake Okeechobee
* Florida east coast from the St. Lucie/Martin County Line to the
Palm Beach/Martin County Line
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* Florida Keys, including Dry Tortugas and Florida Bay
* Lake Okeechobee
* Florida west coast from Flamingo to south of Bonita Beach
* Florida west coast from north of Suwanee River to Indian Pass
* Florida east coast south of the St. Lucie/Martin County Line to
Flamingo
* North of Ponte Vedra Beach Florida to Edisto Beach South Carolina
* Extreme northwestern Bahamas, including Grand Bahama Island, the
Abacos, and Bimini
 
A Storm Surge Warning means there is a danger of life-threatening
inundation, from rising water moving inland from the coastline in
the indicated locations. For a depiction of areas at risk, please
see the National Weather Service Storm Surge Watch/Warning Graphic,
available at hurricanes.gov.  This is a life-threatening situation.
Persons located within these areas should take all necessary actions
to protect life and property from rising water and the potential for
other dangerous conditions.  Promptly follow evacuation and other
instructions from local officials.
 
A Hurricane Warning means that hurricane conditions are expected
somewhere within the warning area.
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area.
 
A Hurricane Watch means that hurricane conditions are possible
within the watch area.
 
For storm information specific to your area in the United
States, including possible inland watches and warnings, please
monitor products issued by your local National Weather Service
forecast office. For storm information specific to your area
outside of the United States, please monitor products issued by
your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 200 AM EDT (0600 UTC), the center of Hurricane Milton was located
inland near latitude 28.1 North, longitude 81.3 West. Milton is
moving toward the east-northeast near 16 mph (26 km/h), and this
general motion is expected to continue through this afternoon, 
followed by a turn toward the east tonight.  On the forecast track, 
the center of Milton will continue to move across the central part 
of the Florida during the next few hours, and emerge off the east 
coast of Florida around sunrise.
 
Maximum sustained winds are near 90 mph (150 km/h) with higher
gusts.  Milton is forecast to maintain hurricane intensity while
crossing Florida this morning.  After moving into the Atlantic, 
Milton is expected to gradually lose tropical characteristics and 
slowly weaken.
 
Hurricane-force winds extend outward up to 35 miles (55 km) from the 
center and tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 255 miles 
(405 km).  A sustained wind of 59 mph (95 km/h) and a gust of 76 mph 
(122 km/h) was recently reported at a NASA weather station at Cape 
Canaveral.  A sustained wind of 58 mph (93 km/h) and a gust of 75 
mph (121 km/h) was recently reported at Daytona Beach International 
Airport.  A sustained wind of 39 mph (63 km/h) and a gust of 63 mph 
(101 km/h was recently reported at Melbourne International Airport. 
A sustained wind of 33 mph (53 km/h) and a gust to 54 mph (87 km/h) 
was recently reported at Orlando International Airport.
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 975 mb (28.79 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key Messages for Milton can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT4 and WMO header WTNT44 KNHC
and on the web at hurricanes.gov/text/MIATCDAT4.shtml
 
STORM SURGE: The combination of a dangerous storm surge and the
tide will cause normally dry areas near the coast to be flooded by
rising waters moving inland from the shoreline.  The water could
reach the following heights above ground somewhere in the indicated
areas if the peak surge occurs at the time of high tide...
 
Anna Maria Island, FL to Bonita Beach, FL...4-7 ft
Charlotte Harbor...4-7 ft
Anclote River, FL to Anna Maria Island, FL...3-5 ft
Tampa Bay...3-5 ft
Bonita Beach, FL to Flamingo, FL...3-5 ft
Sebastian Inlet, FL to Altamaha Sound, GA...3-5 ft
St. Johns River...2-4 ft
 
The deepest water will occur along the immediate coast near and to
the south of the landfall location, where the surge will be
accompanied by large and dangerous waves.  Surge-related flooding
depends on the relative timing of the surge and the tidal cycle,
and can vary greatly over short distances.  For information
specific to your area, please see products issued by your local
National Weather Service forecast office.
 
For a complete depiction of areas at risk of storm surge
inundation, please see the National Weather Service Peak Storm
Surge Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?peakSurge.
 
RAINFALL: Rainfall amounts of 8 to 14 inches, with localized totals
up to 18 inches, are expected across central to northern portions of
the Florida Peninsula today.  This rainfall will continue
to bring the risk of catastrophic and life-threatening flash and
urban flooding, along with moderate to major river flooding.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall associated with
Hurricane Milton, please see the National Weather Service Storm
Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?rainqpf and the Flash Flood Risk
graphic at hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?ero.
 
WIND: Hurricane conditions are occurring within the hurricane
warning area in Florida.  Hurricane conditions are possible in the
hurricane watch area through midday today.  Tropical storm
conditions in the tropical storm warning area in Florida and will 
spread to the Georgia and South Carolina coasts later this morning.
 
Tropical storm conditions are expected in portions of the
northwestern Bahamas later today.
 
TORNADOES: A tornado or two is possible this morning over parts of 
central and eastern Florida.
 
SURF:  Swells generated by Milton are expected to continue to affect
much of the Gulf Coast today and along the southeastern U.S.
coast during the next day or two.  These swells are likely to cause
life-threatening surf and rip current conditions.  Please consult
products from your local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 500 AM EDT.
 
$$
Forecaster Cangialosi/Bucci/Reinhart/Mahoney/Sardi
 
NNNN
 
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
