<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL022024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>INTERMEDIATE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>2</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>4A</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240629 02:00:00 PM AST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240629 06:00:00 PM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>202406291800</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0200 PM AST Sat Jun 29</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1719684000</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL STORM</systemType>
<systemName>BERYL</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>10.0</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-48.4</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>10.0N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>48.4W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>65</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>100</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>55</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>998</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.47</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>W OR 275 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>23</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>37</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>20</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 785 MI...1260 KM ESE OF BARBADOS</systemGeoRefPt1>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT2 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Storm Beryl Intermediate Advisory Number 4A
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL022024
200 PM AST Sat Jun 29 2024
 
...BERYL EXPECTED TO BECOME A DANGEROUS MAJOR HURRICANE BEFORE
REACHING THE WINDWARD ISLANDS...


SUMMARY OF 200 PM AST...1800 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...10.0N 48.4W
ABOUT 785 MI...1260 KM ESE OF BARBADOS
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...65 MPH...100 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...W OR 275 DEGREES AT 23 MPH...37 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...998 MB...29.47 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The government of Dominica has issued a Tropical Storm Watch for 
the island.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Hurricane Watch is in effect for...
* Barbados
* St Lucia
* St. Vincent and the Grenadine Islands
* Grenada
 
A Tropical Storm Watch is in effect for...
* Martinique
* Dominica
* Tobago
 
Interests elsewhere in the Lesser Antilles should closely monitor
the progress of Beryl.  Additional watches and warnings will likely
be required for portions of this area this evening.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 200 PM AST (1800 UTC), the center of Tropical Storm Beryl was
located near latitude 10.0 North, longitude 48.4 West. Beryl is
moving toward the west near 23 mph (37 km/h).  A relatively quick
westward to west-northwestward motion is expected during the next
few days.  On the forecast track, the system is expected to move
across the Windward Islands late Sunday night and Monday.
 
Maximum sustained winds are near 65 mph (100 km/h) with higher 
gusts.  Rapid strengthening is forecast, and Beryl is expected 
to become a major hurricane before it reaches the Windward Islands.
 
Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 45 miles (75 km)
from the center.
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 998 mb (29.47 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Tropical Storm Beryl can be found in the
Tropical Cyclone Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT2 and WMO
header WTNT42 KNHC.
 
WIND: Hurricane conditions are possible in the hurricane watch areas
Sunday night or Monday morning, with tropical storm conditions
possible by late Sunday.  Tropical storm conditions are possible in
the tropical storm watch areas by Monday morning.
 
STORM SURGE:  A life-threatening storm surge will raise water
levels by as much as 5 to 7 feet above normal tide levels in areas
of onshore flow in the hurricane watch areas.  Near the coast, the
surge will be accompanied by large and destructive waves.
 
RAINFALL: Tropical Storm Beryl is expected to produce rainfall
totals of 3 to 6 inches across Barbados and the Windward Islands
Sunday night into Monday. This rainfall may cause flooding in
vulnerable areas.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall and flash flooding
associated with Tropical Storm Beryl, please see the National
Weather Service Storm Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at2.shtml?rainqpf
 
SURF:  Swells generated by the storm are expected to reach the
Windward and southern Leeward Islands by late Sunday.  These swells
are likely to cause life-threatening surf and rip current
conditions.  Please consult products from your local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 500 PM AST.
 
$$
Forecaster Cangialosi
 
NNNN
 
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
