<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL142024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>ROUTINE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>4</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>8</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20241007 04:00:00 AM CDT</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20241007 09:00:00 AM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20241007090000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0400 AM CDT Mon Oct 07</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1728291600</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>HURRICANE</systemType>
<systemName>MILTON</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>22.1</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-92.6</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>22.1N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>92.6W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>100</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>155</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>85</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>972</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>28.71</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>CATEGORY 2</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>ESE OR 105 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>8</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>13</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>7</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 195 MI...310 KM WNW OF PROGRESO MEXICO</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 750 MI...1210 KM WSW OF TAMPA FLORIDA</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT4 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Hurricane Milton Advisory Number   8
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL142024
400 AM CDT Mon Oct 07 2024
 
...MILTON STRENGTHENING OVER THE SOUTHERN GULF OF MEXICO...
...STORM SURGE AND HURRICANE WATCHES ISSUED FOR PORTIONS OF 
FLORIDA...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 400 AM CDT...0900 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...22.1N 92.6W
ABOUT 195 MI...310 KM WNW OF PROGRESO MEXICO
ABOUT 750 MI...1210 KM WSW OF TAMPA FLORIDA
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...100 MPH...155 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...ESE OR 105 DEGREES AT 8 MPH...13 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...972 MB...28.71 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The Government of Mexico has issued a Hurricane Warning for the
coast of the Yucatan Peninsula from Celestun to Rio Lagartos.
 
A Hurricane Watch is now in effect for the Gulf coast of Florida
from Chokoloskee northward to the mouth of the Suwanee River,
including Tampa Bay, and the Dry Tortugas.

A Storm Surge Watch has been issued for the Florida Gulf Coast from 
Flamingo northward to the Suwannee River, including Charlotte Harbor 
and Tampa Bay.
 
A Tropical Storm Watch is now in effect for the Florida Gulf Coast
west of the Suwannee River to Indian Pass, and south of Chokoloskee
to Flamingo.  A Tropical Storm Watch has also been issued for the
Lower, Middle, and Upper Florida Keys, including Florida Bay
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Hurricane Warning is in effect for...
* Coast of the Yucatan Peninsula of Mexico from Celestun to Rio 
Lagartos
 
A Hurricane Watch is in effect for...
* Coast of the Yucatan Peninsula of Mexico from  Rio Lagartos to 
Cabo Catoche
* Florida Gulf coast from Chokoloskee to the mouth of the Suwanee 
River, including Tampa Bay
* Dry Tortugas

A Storm Surge Watch is in effect for...
* Florida Gulf coast from Flamingo northward to the Suwannee River, 
including Charlotte Harbor and Tampa Bay
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* Coast of the Yucatan Peninsula of Mexico from Rio Lagartos to 
Cancun
 
A Tropical Storm Watch is in effect for...
* Florida Gulf coast from Flamingo to south of Chokoloskee
* Florida Gulf coast north of the mouth of the Suwanee River to 
Indian Pass
* Lower, Middle, and Upper Florida Keys, including Florida Bay
 
A Hurricane Warning means that hurricane conditions are expected
somewhere within the warning area.  A warning is typically issued
36 hours before the anticipated first occurrence of
tropical-storm-force winds, conditions that make outside
preparations difficult or dangerous.  Preparations to protect life
and property should be rushed to completion.
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area within 36 hours.
 
A Storm Surge Watch means there is a possibility of life-
threatening inundation, from rising water moving inland from the
coastline, in the indicated locations during the next 48 hours.
For a depiction of areas at risk, please see the National Weather
Service Storm Surge Watch/Warning Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov.
 
A Hurricane Watch means that hurricane conditions are possible
within the watch area.  A watch is typically issued 48 hours
before the anticipated first occurrence of tropical-storm-force
winds, conditions that make outside preparations difficult or
dangerous.
 
A Tropical Storm Watch means that tropical storm conditions are
possible within the watch area, generally within 48 hours.
 
Interests in the remainder of the Yucatan peninsula of Mexico, the
Florida Peninsula, the Florida Keys, and the northwestern Bahamas
should monitor the progress of this system. Additional watches and
warnings will likely be issued later today.
 
For storm information specific to your area in the United
States, including possible inland watches and warnings, please
monitor products issued by your local National Weather Service
forecast office. For storm information specific to your area
outside of the United States, please monitor products issued by
your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 400 AM CDT (0900 UTC), the center of Hurricane Milton was located
near latitude 22.1 North, longitude 92.6 West. Milton is moving
toward the east-southeast near 8 mph (13 km/h).  An eastward to
east-southeastward motion is forecast through tonight, followed by a
turn toward the east and northeast on Tuesday and Wednesday.  On the
forecast track, Milton is forecast to move near or just north of 
the Yucatan Peninsula today and Tuesday, then cross the eastern 
Gulf of Mexico and approach the west coast of the Florida Peninsula 
by Wednesday.
 
Maximum sustained winds are now near 100 mph (155 km/h) with higher
gusts.  Milton is forecast to intensify rapidly and become a major
hurricane later today.
 
Hurricane-force winds extend outward up to 25 miles (35 km) from the
center and tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 80 miles
(130 km).
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 972 mb (28.71 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key Messages for Hurricane Milton can be found in the Tropical
Cyclone Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT4 and WMO header
WTNT44 KNHC and on the web at hurricanes.gov/text/MIATCDAT4.shtml
 
STORM SURGE:  A storm surge will raise water levels by as much as 2
to 4 feet above ground level along the northern coast of the
Yucatan Peninsula in areas of onshore winds.  Near the coast, the
surge will be accompanied by large and destructive waves.

The combination of a dangerous storm surge and the tide will cause 
normally dry areas near the coast to be flooded by rising waters 
moving inland from the shoreline.  The water could reach the 
following heights above ground somewhere in the indicated areas if 
the peak surge occurs at the time of high tide...

Anclote River, FL to Englewood, FL...8-12 ft
Tampa Bay...8-12 ft
Yankeetown, FL to Anclote River, FL...5-10 ft
Englewood, FL to Bonita Beach, FL...5-10 ft
Charlotte Harbor...5-10 ft
Bonita Beach, FL to Chokoloskee, FL...4-7 ft
Suwannee River, FL to Yankeetown, FL...3-5 ft

The deepest water will occur along the immediate coast near and to
the south of the landfall location, where the surge will be
accompanied by large and dangerous waves.  Surge-related flooding 
depends on the relative timing of the surge and the tidal cycle, 
and can vary greatly over short distances.  For information
specific to your area, please see products issued by your local
National Weather Service forecast office.

For a complete depiction of areas at risk of storm surge 
inundation, please see the National Weather Service Peak Storm 
Surge Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?peakSurge.
 
RAINFALL: Rainfall amounts of 5 to 10 inches, with localized totals 
up to 15 inches, are expected across portions of the Florida 
Peninsula and the Keys through Wednesday night. This rainfall brings 
the risk of considerable flash, urban, and areal flooding, along 
with the potential for moderate to major river flooding.

Milton will also produce rainfall totals of 2 to 4 inches across 
portions of the northern Yucatan Peninsula..

For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall associated with 
Hurricane Milton, please see the National Weather Service Storm 
Total Rainfall Graphic, available at 
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?rainqpf and the Flash Flood Risk 
graphic at hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?ero. 
 
WIND:  Hurricane conditions are expected in the warning area in 
Mexico beginning late today or tonight, with tropical storm 
conditions expected to begin as early as this morning. Hurricane 
conditions are possible in the watch area in Mexico beginning 
tonight and Tuesday, and tropical storm conditions are expected in 
the tropical storm warning area beginning later today. Hurricane 
conditions are possible in the Hurricane Watch area in Florida on 
Wednesday, and tropical storm conditions are possible in the 
Tropical Storm Watch area on Wednesday.
 
SURF:  Swells generated by the system are affecting the coast of the
southwestern Gulf of Mexico.  These swells are expected to spread
northward and eastward along much of the Gulf Coast within the next
day or two, and are likely to cause life-threatening surf and rip
current conditions.  Please consult products from your local
weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next intermediate advisory at 700 AM CDT.
Next complete advisory at 1000 AM CDT.
 
$$
Forecaster Beven
 
NNNN
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
