<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL052024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>INTERMEDIATE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>5</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>9A</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240813 08:00:00 PM AST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240814 12:00:00 AM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20240814000000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0800 PM AST Tue Aug 13</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1723593600</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL STORM</systemType>
<systemName>ERNESTO</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>18.4</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-64.7</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>18.4N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>64.7W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>65</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>100</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>55</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>998</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.47</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>WNW OR 300 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>18</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>30</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>16</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 20 MI...30 KM E OF ST. THOMAS</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 90 MI...145 KM E OF SAN JUAN PUERTO RICO</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT5 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Storm Ernesto Intermediate Advisory Number 9A
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL052024
800 PM AST Tue Aug 13 2024
 
...ERNESTO MOVING OVER THE VIRGIN ISLANDS...
...EXPECTED TO BECOME A HURRICANE OVERNIGHT WHILE PASSING NORTHEAST
OF PUERTO RICO...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 800 PM AST...0000 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...18.4N 64.7W
ABOUT 20 MI...30 KM E OF ST. THOMAS
ABOUT 90 MI...145 KM E OF SAN JUAN PUERTO RICO
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...65 MPH...100 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...WNW OR 300 DEGREES AT 18 MPH...30 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...998 MB...29.47 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The government of France has discontinued the Tropical Storm Warning 
for St. Martin and St. Barthelemy.

The government of Antigua and Barbuda has discontinued the Tropical 
Storm Warning for St. Kitts, Nevis, and Anguilla.

The government of Sint Maarten has discontinued the Tropical Storm 
Warning for Sint Maarten.

The government of the Netherlands has discontinued the Tropical 
Storm Warning for Saba and St. Eustatius.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Hurricane Watch is in effect for...
* U.S. Virgin Islands
* British Virgin Islands
* Vieques and Culebra
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* British Virgin Islands
* U.S. Virgin Islands
* Puerto Rico
* Vieques and Culebra
 
A Hurricane Watch means that hurricane conditions are possible
within the watch area, in this case through tonight.
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area within 36 hours.
 
Interests in Bermuda should monitor the progress of Ernesto.
 
For storm information specific to your area in the United States, 
including possible inland watches and warnings, please monitor 
products issued by your local National Weather Service forecast 
office. For storm information specific to your area outside of the 
United States, please monitor products issued by your national 
meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 800 PM AST (0000 UTC), the center of Tropical Storm Ernesto was 
located near latitude 18.4 North, longitude 64.7 West. Ernesto is 
moving toward the west-northwest near 18 mph (30 km/h). A turn 
toward the northwest with a gradual decrease in forward speed is 
expected overnight, followed by a turn toward the north-northwest 
and north Wednesday night and Thursday. On the forecast track, the 
center of Ernesto should pass just to the northeast and north of 
Puerto Rico tonight and on Wednesday. Ernesto should then move over 
the western Atlantic later in the week and approach Bermuda on 
Friday and Friday night.
 
Aircraft data indicate that maximum sustained winds have increased 
to near 65 mph (100 km/h) with higher gusts. Strengthening is 
forecast during the next several days. Ernesto is expected to become 
a hurricane later tonight or early Wednesday to the north of the 
Virgin Islands and Puerto Rico.
 
Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 115 miles (185 km) 
from the center. A National Ocean Service station in Charlotte 
Amalie, St. Thomas, recently reported a wind gust of 43 mph (69 
km/h).
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 998 mb (29.47 inches) 
based on Hurricane Hunter aircraft data.
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Ernesto can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT5 and WMO header WTNT45 KNHC
and on the web at hurricanes.gov/text/MIATCDAT5.shtml.
 
RAINFALL: Tropical Storm Ernesto is expected to produce total rain 
accumulations of 4 to 6 inches over portions of the Leeward Islands 
from St. Kitts and Nevis to St. Martin and across the U.S. and 
British Virgin Islands. Rainfall totals of 6 to 8 inches, with 
maximum amounts of 10 inches, are expected across southeastern 
Puerto Rico, with totals of 2 to 4 inches across northwestern Puerto 
Rico.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall associated with
Tropical Storm Ernesto, please see the National Weather Service
Storm Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at5.shtml?rainqpf
 
WIND: Tropical storm conditions are occurring over the Virgin 
Islands and will spread over Puerto Rico, Vieques, and Culebra 
during the next several hours. Hurricane conditions are possible 
over the Virgin Islands, Vieques, and Culebra tonight.
 
STORM SURGE: A storm surge will raise water levels by as much as 1
to 3 feet above ground level for the eastern coast of Puerto Rico
from San Juan to Guayama, including the islands of Culebra and
Vieques and in the U.S. Virgin Islands, including St. Thomas, St.
John, and St. Croix.
 
A storm surge will raise water levels by as much as 1 to 3 feet
above normal tide levels in the British Virgin Islands. Near the
coast, the surge will be accompanied by large and destructive waves.
 
SURF: Swells generated by Ernesto are affecting portions of the
Leeward Islands, the Virgin Islands, and Puerto Rico. These swells
will reach the Dominican Republic tonight, the Turks and Caicos
Islands and southeastern Bahamas on Wednesday, and Bermuda and the
rest of the Bahamas on Thursday. Swells are also expected to reach
the east coast of the United States Thursday night and continue into
the weekend. These swells are likely to cause life-threatening surf
and rip current conditions. Please consult products from your local
weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 1100 PM AST.
 
$$
Forecaster Reinhart
 
NNNN
 
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
