<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL022024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>INTERMEDIATE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>2</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>28A</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240705 01:00:00 PM CDT</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240705 06:00:00 PM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20240705180000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0100 PM CDT Fri Jul 05</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1720202400</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL STORM</systemType>
<systemName>BERYL</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>20.8</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-88.8</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>20.8N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>88.8W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>70</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>115</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>60</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>986</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.12</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>WNW OR 290 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>15</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>24</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>13</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 65 MI...105 KM ESE OF PROGRESO MEXICO</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 650 MI...1045 KM ESE OF BROWNSVILLE TEXAS</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT2 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Storm Beryl Intermediate Advisory Number 28A
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL022024
100 PM CDT Fri Jul 05 2024
 
...BERYL WEAKENS TO A TROPICAL STORM...
...TROPICAL STORM CONDITIONS CONTINUE OVER PORTIONS OF THE NORTHERN 
YUCATAN PENINSULA...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 100 PM CDT...1800 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...20.8N 88.8W
ABOUT 65 MI...105 KM ESE OF PROGRESO MEXICO
ABOUT 650 MI...1045 KM ESE OF BROWNSVILLE TEXAS
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...70 MPH...115 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...WNW OR 290 DEGREES AT 15 MPH...24 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...986 MB...29.12 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The Meteorological Service of Mexico has discontinued all watches 
and warnings for the east coast of the Yucatan Peninsula south of 
Cabo Catoche.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* The coast of the Yucatan Peninsula of Mexico west of Cabo 
Catoche to Campeche
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area.
 
Interests in northeastern Mexico and the lower and middle Texas
coast should closely monitor the progress of Beryl. Hurricane and
Tropical Storm Watches will likely be issued for that region later
today.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 100 PM CDT (1800 UTC), the center of Tropical Storm Beryl was 
located near latitude 20.8 North, longitude 88.8 West. Beryl is 
moving toward the west-northwest near 15 mph (24 km/h). A west-
northwestward motion is expected during the next day or so, with the
center forecast to cross the northern Yucatan Peninsula this 
afternoon. Beryl is expected to emerge over the southwestern Gulf 
of Mexico tonight and then move northwestward toward northeastern 
Mexico and southern Texas by the end of the weekend.
 
Maximum sustained winds have decreased to near 70 mph (115 km/h)
with higher gusts. Continued weakening is expected as Beryl 
crosses the Yucatan Peninsula today, but re-intensification is 
expected once the center moves back over the Gulf of Mexico.
 
Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 105 miles (165 km) 
from the center.
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 986 mb (29.12 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Beryl can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT2, WMO header WTNT42 KNHC,
and on the NHC website at hurricanes.gov/text/MIATCDAT2.shtml.
 
WIND: Tropical storm conditions are occurring over portions of 
the northern Yucatan Peninsula and should spread westward along the 
Gulf coast of the peninsula this afternoon.
 
STORM SURGE: Storm surge could raise water levels by as much as 1 to
3 feet above ground level in areas of onshore winds along the west
and north coasts of the Yucatan Peninsula in the tropical storm 
warning area. Near the coast, the surge will be accompanied by 
large and destructive waves.
 
RAINFALL:  Through today Beryl is expected to produce rainfall
totals of 4 to 6 inches, with localized amounts of 10 inches, across
the Yucatan Peninsula, with scattered instances of flash flooding
anticipated.
 
Heavy rainfall of 4 to 8 inches with locally higher amounts is
expected across portions of northeastern Mexico and South Texas by
Sunday into the coming week. This rainfall is expected to produce
areas of flash and urban flooding.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall and flash flooding
associated with Tropical Storm Beryl, please see the National 
Weather Service Storm Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at2.shtml?rainqpf and the Flash Flood Risk
graphic at hurricanes.gov/graphics_at2.shtml?ero
 
SURF:  Large swells generated by Beryl are currently impacting
portions of the coast of Cuba, the Cayman Islands, and the
Yucatan Peninsula. The swells are expected to reach eastern Mexico
and much of the Gulf Coast of the U.S. by late today. These swells
are expected to cause life-threatening surf and rip current
conditions. Please consult products from your local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 400 PM CDT.
 
$$
Forecaster Beven
 
NNNN
 
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
