<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>EP092024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>INTERMEDIATE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>4</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>8A</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240914 05:00:00 AM MST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240914 12:00:00 PM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20240914120000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0500 AM MST Sat Sep 14</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1726315200</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL STORM</systemType>
<systemName>ILEANA</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>24.7</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-109.2</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>24.7N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>109.2W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>40</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>65</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>35</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>1003</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.62</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>N OR 360 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>7</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>11</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>6</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 70 MI...110 KM S OF LOS MOCHIS MEXICO</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 85 MI...135 KM ENE OF LA PAZ MEXICO</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPEP4 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Storm Ileana Intermediate Advisory Number 8A
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       EP092024
500 AM MST Sat Sep 14 2024
 
...ILEANA CONTINUES NORTHWARD OVER THE SOUTHERN GULF OF
CALIFORNIA...
...TROPICAL STORM CONDITIONS OCCURRING ALONG PORTIONS OF THE 
COAST OF MEXICO...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 500 AM MST...1200 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...24.7N 109.2W
ABOUT 70 MI...110 KM S OF LOS MOCHIS MEXICO
ABOUT 85 MI...135 KM ENE OF LA PAZ MEXICO
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...40 MPH...65 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...N OR 360 DEGREES AT 7 MPH...11 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...1003 MB...29.62 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
None. 
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* Altata to Huatabampito Mexico
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area, in this case within
12 hours.
 
Interests elsewhere in the Mexican states of Baja California Sur,
Sinaloa, and Sonora should closely monitor the progress of Ileana.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 500 AM MST (1200 UTC), the center of Tropical Storm Ileana was
located near latitude 24.7 North, longitude 109.2 West.  Ileana is
moving toward the north near 7 mph (11 km/h), and this general
motion is expected to continue today.  A slower motion toward the
north-northwest and northwest is expected tonight and on Sunday.  On
the forecast track, the center of Ileana will move near or over the
coasts of northern Sinaloa and southern Sonora later today, and then
move over the Gulf of California roughly parallel to the coast on
Sunday.
 
Maximum sustained winds are near 40 mph (65 km/h) with higher
gusts. Weakening is forecast to begin later this afternoon or
evening, and Ileana is likely to degenerate into a remnant low
tonight.  The remnant low is expected to dissipate by early Monday.
 
Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 60 miles (95 km)
from the center.  The Mexican Navy station at Topolobampo recently 
reported sustained winds of 40 mph (65 km/h) and a wind gust of 48 
mph (77 km/h).
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 1003 mb (29.62 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Ileana can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDEP4 and WMO header WTPZ44 KNHC.
 
RAINFALL: Tropical Storm Ileana is expected to bring rainfall of 6
to 8 inches, with localized higher amounts up to 12 inches, across
northwest coastal Sinaloa through this weekend.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall associated with
Ileana, please see the National Weather Service Storm Total Rainfall
Graphic, available at hurricanes.gov/graphics_ep4.shtml?rainqpf
 
WIND: Tropical storm conditions are expected across portions of the
warning area in northern Sinaloa and southern Sonora later this
morning and afternoon.
 
SURF: Swells generated by Ileana will affect portions of the
Gulf of California coasts of Sinaloa, southern Sonora, and southern
Baja California Sur during the next day or so.  These swells could
cause life-threatening surf and rip current conditions. Please
consult products from your local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 800 AM MST.
 
$$
Forecaster Beven
 
NNNN
 
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
