<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL152024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>ROUTINE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>5</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>3</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20241019 04:00:00 AM CDT</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20241019 09:00:00 AM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20241019090000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0400 AM CDT Sat Oct 19</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1729328400</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL STORM</systemType>
<systemName>NADINE</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>17.4</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-87.1</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>17.4N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>87.1W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>40</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>65</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>35</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>1004</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.65</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>W OR 270 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>9</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>15</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>8</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 75 MI...115 KM E OF BELIZE CITY</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 110 MI...175 KM SE OF CHETUMAL MEXICO</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT5 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Storm Nadine Advisory Number   3
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL152024
400 AM CDT Sat Oct 19 2024
 
...TROPICAL STORM CONDITIONS AND HEAVY RAINS SPREADING OVER
PORTIONS OF BELIZE AND THE YUCATAN PENINSULA OF MEXICO...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 400 AM CDT...0900 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...17.4N 87.1W
ABOUT 75 MI...115 KM E OF BELIZE CITY
ABOUT 110 MI...175 KM SE OF CHETUMAL MEXICO
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...40 MPH...65 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...W OR 270 DEGREES AT 9 MPH...15 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...1004 MB...29.65 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The government of Mexico has extended the Tropical Storm Warning
northward to Cancun.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* Belize City, Belize to Cancun, Mexico, including Cozumel
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area, in this case within the
next 12 hours.
 
Interests elsewhere in Belize and the Yucatan Peninsula of Mexico
should monitor the progress of this system.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 400 AM CDT (0900 UTC), the center of Tropical Storm Nadine was
located near latitude 17.4 North, longitude 87.1 West.  Nadine is
moving toward the west near 9 mph (15 km/h), and this general
motion with an increase in forward speed is expected through today
and tonight.  On the forecast track, the center of Nadine is
forecast to make landfall along the coast of Belize late this
morning or around midday, and then continue across northern
Guatemala and southeastern Mexico late this afternoon into tonight.
 
Maximum sustained winds are near 40 mph (65 km/h) with higher gusts.
Some slight strengthening is possible this morning before Nadine
makes landfall.  Weakening is forecast to begin this afternoon once
Nadine is inland, and the system is likely to dissipate over
southeastern Mexico by early Sunday.
 
Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 230 miles (370 km)
north of the center.  A WeatherFlow station in Cancun, Mexico,
recently reported a sustained wind of 41 mph (67 km/h) and a gust
to 51 mph (81 km/h).
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 1004 mb (29.65 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Nadine can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT5 and WMO header WTNT45 KNHC
and on the web at hurricanes.gov/text/MIATCDAT5.shtml
 
RAINFALL: Widespread 4 to 8 inch rainfall amounts are expected with
Nadine across northern Belize, northern Guatemala, and southern
Mexican states from Quintana Roo westward to Veracruz.  Isolated
areas of amounts exceeding 12 inches are also possible through late
Tuesday.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall associated with
Tropical Storm Nadine, please see the National Weather Service Storm
Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at5.shtml?rainqpf.
 
WIND: Tropical storm conditions are expected within the warning area
through this afternoon.
 
STORM SURGE: Minor coastal flooding is possible in areas of onshore
winds near and to the north of where the center moves inland.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next intermediate advisory at 700 AM CDT.
Next complete advisory at 1000 AM CDT.
 
$$
Forecaster Berg
 
NNNN
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
