<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL022024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>ROUTINE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>2</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>9</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240630 05:00:00 PM AST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240630 09:00:00 PM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>202406302100</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0500 PM AST Sun Jun 30</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1719781200</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>HURRICANE</systemType>
<systemName>BERYL</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>11.1</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-56.5</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>11.1N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>56.5W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>130</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>215</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>115</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>960</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>28.35</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>CATEGORY 4</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>WNW OR 285 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>18</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>30</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>16</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 250 MI...400 KM SE OF BARBADOS</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 350 MI...565 KM ESE OF ST. VINCENT</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT2 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Hurricane Beryl Advisory Number   9
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL022024
500 PM AST Sun Jun 30 2024
 
...EXTREMELY DANGEROUS CATEGORY 4 BERYL APPROACHING THE WINDWARD
ISLANDS...
...LIFE-THREATENING WINDS AND STORM SURGE EXPECTED THERE BEGINNING
EARLY MONDAY MORNING...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 500 PM AST...2100 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...11.1N 56.5W
ABOUT 250 MI...400 KM SE OF BARBADOS
ABOUT 350 MI...565 KM ESE OF ST. VINCENT
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...130 MPH...215 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...WNW OR 285 DEGREES AT 18 MPH...30 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...960 MB...28.35 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The government of the Dominican Republic has issued a Tropical
Storm Watch from Punta Palenque westward to the border with Haiti.
 
A Tropical Storm Watch has also been issued for the entire south
coast of Haiti from the border of the Dominican Republic to Anse
d'Hainault.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Hurricane Warning is in effect for...
* Barbados
* St. Lucia
* St. Vincent and the Grenadine Islands
* Grenada
* Tobago
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* Martinique
 
A Tropical Storm Watch is in effect for...
* Dominica
* Trinidad
* South coast of Dominican Republic from Punta Palenque westward
to the border with Haiti
* South coast of Haiti from the border with the Dominican
Republic to Anse d'Hainault
 
A Hurricane Warning means that hurricane conditions are expected
somewhere within the warning area.  Preparations to protect life
and property should be rushed to completion.
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area within 36 hours.
 
A Tropical Storm Watch means that tropical storm conditions are
possible within the watch area, generally within 48 hours.
 
Interests elsewhere in the Lesser Antilles, Hispaniola, Jamaica,
the Cayman Islands, and the remainder of the northwestern Caribbean
should closely monitor the progress of Beryl.  Additional watches
or warnings may be required tonight or on Monday.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 500 PM AST (2100 UTC), the center of Hurricane Beryl was located
near latitude 11.1 North, longitude 56.5 West. Beryl is moving
toward the west-northwest near 18 mph (30 km/h). A continued quick 
westward to west-northwestward motion is expected during the next 
few days. On the forecast track, the center of Beryl is expected to 
move across the Windward Islands Monday morning and across the
southeastern and central Caribbean Sea late Monday through
Wednesday.
 
Maximum sustained winds are near 130 mph (215 km/h) with higher
gusts.  Beryl is a category 4 hurricane on the Saffir-Simpson
Hurricane Wind Scale.  Fluctuations in strength are likely during 
the next day or so, and Beryl is expected to remain an extremely 
dangerous category 4 hurricane through landfall in the Windward 
Islands.
 
Hurricane-force winds extend outward up to 30 miles (45 km) from the
center and tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 115 miles
(185 km).
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 960 mb (28.35 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Beryl can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT2 and WMO header WTNT42 KNHC.
 
WIND: Hurricane conditions are expected in the hurricane warning
area beginning early Monday morning.  Potentially catastrophic wind
damage is expected where the eyewall of Beryl moves through portions
of the Windward Islands, with the highest risk of the core in St.
Vincent and the Grenadines, and Grenada.
 
Wind speeds atop and on the windward sides of hills and mountains
are often up to 30 percent stronger than the near-surface winds
indicated in this advisory, and in some elevated locations could be
even greater.
 
Tropical storm conditions are expected in the tropical storm warning
area starting late tonight, making outside preparations difficult or
dangerous.
 
Tropical storm conditions are possible within the watch area
starting late tonight for Dominica, Trinidad, and by Tuesday
afternoon for parts of the southern coast of Hispaniola.
 
STORM SURGE:  A life-threatening storm surge will raise water levels
by as much as 6 to 9 feet above normal tide levels in areas of
onshore flow near where the eye makes landfall in the hurricane
warning area.  Near the coast, the surge will be accompanied by
large and destructive waves.
 
RAINFALL: Hurricane Beryl is expected to produce rainfall totals of 
3 to 6 inches across Barbados and the Windward Islands through 
Monday. Localized maxima of 10 inches is possible, especially in the 
Grenadines. This rainfall may cause flash flooding in vulnerable 
areas.

For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall and flash flooding 
associated with Hurricane Beryl, please see the National Weather 
Service Storm Total Rainfall Graphic, available at 
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at2.shtml?rainqpf 
 
SURF:  Large swells generated by Beryl are expected across
Windward and southern Leeward Islands during the next couple of
days.  Swells are also expected to reach the southern coasts
of Puerto Rico and Hispaniola in the next day or so. These swells
are expected to cause life-threatening surf and rip current
conditions. Please consult products from your local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next intermediate advisory at 800 PM AST.
Next complete advisory at 1100 PM AST.
 
$$
Forecaster Cangialosi
 
NNNN
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
