<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>EP092024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>ROUTINE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>4</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>10</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240914 02:00:00 PM MST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240914 09:00:00 PM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20240914210000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0200 PM MST Sat Sep 14</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1726347600</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL STORM</systemType>
<systemName>ILEANA</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>25.5</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-108.9</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>25.5N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>108.9W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>40</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>65</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>35</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>1002</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.59</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>N OR 0 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>6</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>9</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>5</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 20 MI...35 KM SSE OF LOS MOCHIS MEXICO</systemGeoRefPt1>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPEP4 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Storm Ileana Advisory Number  10
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       EP092024
200 PM MST Sat Sep 14 2024
 
...CENTER OF ILEANA MAKES LANDFALL ALONG THE COAST OF MEXICO
SOUTHEAST OF TOPOLOBAMPO...
...TROPICAL STORM CONDITIONS AND HEAVY RAINS SPREADING ONSHORE...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 200 PM MST...2100 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...25.5N 108.9W
ABOUT 20 MI...35 KM SSE OF LOS MOCHIS MEXICO
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...40 MPH...65 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...N OR 0 DEGREES AT 6 MPH...9 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...1002 MB...29.59 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
None.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* Altata to Huatabampito Mexico
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area, in this case within
12 hours.
 
Interests elsewhere in the Mexican states of Baja California Sur,
Sinaloa, and Sonora should closely monitor the progress of Ileana.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 200 PM MST (2100 UTC), the center of Tropical Storm Ileana was
located near latitude 25.5 North, longitude 108.9 West. Ileana is
moving toward the north near 6 mph (9 km/h). A turn toward the 
northwest and a slow forward speed are expected tonight and on 
Sunday.  On the forecast track, the center of Ileana will move near 
over the coastal region of northern Sinaloa during the next several 
hours, and then move over the Gulf of California roughly parallel to 
the coast on Sunday.
 
Maximum sustained winds are near 40 mph (65 km/h) with higher gusts.
Weakening is forecast to begin later this afternoon or evening, and 
Ileana is likely to degenerate into a remnant low tonight or on 
Sunday.  The remnant low is expected to dissipate by Monday.
 
Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 60 miles (95 km)
from the center. The Mexican Navy station at Topolobampo recently
reported sustained winds of 34 mph (54 km/h) and a wind gust of
47 mph (76 km/h).
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 1002 mb (29.59 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Ileana can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDEP4 and WMO header WTPZ44 KNHC.
 
RAINFALL: Tropical Storm Ileana is expected to bring additional 
rainfall amounts of 3 to 6 inches, with localized higher amounts up 
to 10 inches, across northwest coastal Sinaloa through this weekend.

For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall associated with 
Tropical Storm Ileana, please see the National Weather Service Storm 
Total Rainfall Graphic, available at 
hurricanes.gov/graphics_ep4.shtml?rainqpf 
 
WIND: Tropical storm conditions are expected across portions of the
warning area in northern Sinaloa and southern Sonora through this
afternoon.
 
SURF: Swells generated by Ileana will affect portions of the
Gulf of California coasts of Sinaloa, southern Sonora, and southern
Baja California Sur during the next day or so.  These swells could
cause life-threatening surf and rip current conditions. Please
consult products from your local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next intermediate advisory at 500 PM MST.
Next complete advisory at 800 PM MST.
 
$$
Forecaster Beven
 
NNNN
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
