<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL022024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>INTERMEDIATE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>2</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>37A</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240707 07:00:00 PM CDT</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240708 12:00:00 AM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20240708000000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0700 PM CDT Sun Jul 07</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1720396800</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL STORM</systemType>
<systemName>BERYL</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>27.1</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-95.6</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>27.1N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>95.6W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>70</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>110</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>60</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>987</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.15</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>NNW OR 340 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>12</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>19</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>10</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 105 MI...170 KM SSE OF MATAGORDA TEXAS</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 120 MI...195 KM ESE OF CORPUS CHRISTI TEXAS</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT2 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Storm Beryl Intermediate Advisory Number 37A
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL022024
700 PM CDT Sun Jul 07 2024
 
...HURRICANE HUNTERS FIND BERYL SLIGHTLY STRONGER...
...DANGEROUS STORM SURGE, FLASH FLOODING, AND STRONG WINDS EXPECTED 
OVERNIGHT IN PORTIONS OF TEXAS...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 700 PM CDT...0000 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...27.1N 95.6W
ABOUT 105 MI...170 KM SSE OF MATAGORDA TEXAS
ABOUT 120 MI...195 KM ESE OF CORPUS CHRISTI TEXAS
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...70 MPH...110 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...NNW OR 340 DEGREES AT 12 MPH...19 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...987 MB...29.15 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The Hurricane Warning south of Port Aransas has been changed to a 
Tropical Storm Warning.

The Storm Surge Warning south of Port Aransas, including Corpus 
Christi Bay, has been discontinued.
 
The Tropical Storm Warning south of Port Mansfield has been 
discontinued.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Storm Surge Warning is in effect for...
* Port Aransas to Sabine Pass, including Matagorda Bay and 
Galveston Bay
 
A Hurricane Warning is in effect for...
* The Texas coast from Port Aransas northward to San Luis Pass
 
A Hurricane Watch is in effect for...
* The Texas coast north of San Luis Pass to Port Bolivar
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* The Texas coast south of Port Aransas to Port Mansfield
* The Texas coast north of San Luis Pass to Sabine Pass
 
A Hurricane Warning means that hurricane conditions are expected
somewhere within the warning area.
 
A Hurricane Watch means that hurricane conditions are possible
within the watch area.
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected within the warning area.
 
A Storm Surge Warning means there is a danger of life-threatening
inundation, from rising water moving inland from the coastline,
during the next 36 hours in the indicated locations. For a
depiction of areas at risk, please see the National Weather
Service Storm Surge Watch/Warning Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov.  This is a life-threatening situation.  Persons
located within these areas should take all necessary actions to
protect life and property from rising water and the potential for
other dangerous conditions.  Promptly follow evacuation and other
instructions from local officials.
 
For storm information specific to your area, including possible
inland watches and warnings, please monitor products issued by your
local National Weather Service forecast office.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 700 PM CDT (0000 UTC), the center of Tropical Storm Beryl was 
located near latitude 27.1 North, longitude 95.6 West. Beryl is 
moving toward the north-northwest near 12 mph (19 km/h). This 
general motion is expected to continue through tonight, with a turn 
toward the north forecast on Monday. On the forecast track, the 
center of Beryl is expected to make landfall on the middle Texas 
coast early Monday. Beryl is forecast to turn northeastward and move 
farther inland over eastern Texas and Arkansas late Monday and 
Tuesday.
 
Data from the Air Force Hurricane Hunters indicate that maximum 
sustained winds have increased to near 70 mph (110 km/h) with higher 
gusts. Strengthening is expected, and Beryl is forecast to become a 
hurricane again tonight. Additional strengthening is expected before 
Beryl reaches the Texas coast early Monday.
 
Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 115 miles (185 km)
from the center. NOAA buoy 42019 recently reported a sustained wind 
of 33 mph (54 km/h) and a gust of 42 mph (68 km/h).
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 987 mb (29.15 inches)
based on Air Force Reserve dropsonde data.
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Beryl can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT2, WMO header WTNT42 KNHC,
and on the NHC website at hurricanes.gov/text/MIATCDAT2.shtml.
 
WIND: Hurricane conditions are expected in the hurricane warning 
area by early Monday. Winds are first expected to reach tropical 
storm strength within the next few hours, making outdoor 
preparations difficult or dangerous.
 
Hurricane conditions are possible in the hurricane watch area by
early Monday, with tropical storm conditions beginning by tonight.
 
Tropical storm conditions are expected in the tropical storm
warning area in south Texas starting within the next few hours.
 
Tropical storm conditions are expected in the tropical storm
warning area along the upper Texas coast early Monday.
 
STORM SURGE: The combination of storm surge and tide will cause
normally dry areas near the coast to be flooded by rising waters
moving inland from the shoreline. The water could reach the
following heights above ground somewhere in the indicated areas if
the peak surge occurs at the time of high tide...
 
Port O'Connor, TX to San Luis Pass, TX...4-7 ft
Matagorda Bay...4-7 ft
San Luis Pass, TX to High Island, TX...4-6 ft
Galveston Bay...4-6 ft
Mesquite Bay, TX to Port O'Connor, TX...3-5 ft
High Island, TX to Sabine Pass, TX...3-5 ft
 
The deepest water will occur along the immediate coast near and to
the right of the center, where the surge will be accompanied by
large and destructive waves. Surge-related flooding depends on the
relative timing of the surge and the tidal cycle, and can vary
greatly over short distances.  For information specific to your
area, please see products issued by your local National Weather
Service forecast office.
 
For a complete depiction of areas at risk of storm surge inundation,
please see the National Weather Service Peak Storm Surge Graphic,
available at hurricanes.gov/graphics_at2.shtml?peakSurge.
 
RAINFALL:  Heavy rainfall of 5 to 10 inches with localized amounts
of 15 inches is expected across portions of the middle and upper
Texas Gulf Coast and eastern Texas through Monday night.
Considerable flash and urban flooding as well as minor to isolated
major river flooding is expected.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall and flash flooding
associated with Tropical Storm Beryl, please see the National
Weather Service Storm Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at2.shtml?rainqpf and the Flash Flood Risk
graphic at hurricanes.gov/graphics_at2.shtml?ero
 
TORNADOES: A few tornadoes could occur along the middle and upper
Texas Coast through tonight, and across eastern Texas into Louisiana
and Arkansas on Monday.
 
SURF:  Swells generated by Beryl are expected to affect eastern
Mexico and much of the Gulf Coast of the U.S. during the next day
or two. These swells are expected to cause life-threatening
surf and rip current conditions. Please consult products from your
local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 1000 PM CDT.
 
$$
Forecaster Reinhart
 
NNNN
 
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
