<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL062024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>ROUTINE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>1</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>1</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240908 04:00:00 PM CDT</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240908 09:00:00 PM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20240908210000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0400 PM CDT Sun Sep 08</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1725829200</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>POTENTIAL TROPICAL CYCLONE</systemType>
<systemName>SIX</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>21.6</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-94.6</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>21.6N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>94.6W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>50</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>85</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>45</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>1003</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.62</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>90</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>90</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>NW OR 320 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>5</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>7</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>4</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 340 MI...545 KM SSE OF MOUTH OF THE RIO GRANDE</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 575 MI...925 KM S OF PORT ARTHUR TEXAS</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT1 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Potential Tropical Cyclone Six Advisory Number   1
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL062024
400 PM CDT Sun Sep 08 2024
 
...SYSTEM IN GULF OF MEXICO LIKELY TO STRENGTHEN BEGINNING ON 
TUESDAY...
...INCREASING RISK OF LIFE-THREATENING STORM SURGE AND DAMAGING 
WINDS ALONG THE UPPER TEXAS AND LOUISIANA COASTS BY MID-WEEK...

 
SUMMARY OF 400 PM CDT...2100 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...21.6N 94.6W
ABOUT 340 MI...545 KM SSE OF MOUTH OF THE RIO GRANDE
ABOUT 575 MI...925 KM S OF PORT ARTHUR TEXAS
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...50 MPH...85 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...NW OR 320 DEGREES AT 5 MPH...7 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...1003 MB...29.62 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The Government of Mexico has issued a Tropical Storm Watch from
Barra del Tordo northward to the Mouth of the Rio Grande.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Tropical Storm Watch is in effect for...
* Barra del Tordo northward to the Mouth of the Rio Grande
 
A Tropical Storm Watch means that tropical storm conditions are
possible within the watch area, generally within 48 hours.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by your national meteorological service. 

Interests along the Texas and Louisiana coastline should monitor 
the progress of Potential Tropical Cyclone Six, and additional 
watches or warnings could be required later tonight or tomorrow.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 400 PM CDT (2100 UTC), the elongated disturbance was centered 
near latitude 21.6 North, longitude 94.6 West. The system is moving 
toward the northwest near 5 mph (7 km/h) and a slow northwestward  
motion followed by a turn more northward is expected over the next 
day or two. On the forecast track, the disturbance is expected to 
move near the northern Gulf Coast of Mexico on Tuesday, and 
approach the Upper Texas and Louisiana coastline on Wednesday.
 
Air Force reconnaissance data indicate that maximum sustained 
winds are near 50 mph (85 km/h) with higher gusts. The system is 
expected to become a tropical storm on Monday, with more 
significant intensification forecast to occur on Tuesday.  The 
system is forecast to become a hurricane before it reaches the 
northwestern U.S. Gulf Coast.
* Formation chance through 48 hours...high...90 percent.
* Formation chance through 7 days...high...90 percent.
 
Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 185 miles (295 km), 
primarily west of the center.
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 1003 mb (29.62 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
WIND:  Tropical storm conditions are possible within the watch
area along the northern coast of Mexico beginning Tuesday.

RAINFALL: Potential Tropical Cyclone Six is expected to bring 
storm total rainfall of 4 to 8 inches, with local amounts to 12 
inches, from the coast of far northeast Mexico northward along 
portions of the Texas Coast and into Louisiana through Thursday. 
This rainfall would lead to the risk of flash and urban flooding. 

For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall associated with 
Potential Tropical Cyclone Six, please see the National Weather 
Service Storm Total Rainfall Graphic, available at 
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at1.shtml?rainqpf and the Flash Flood Risk 
graphic at hurricanes.gov/graphics_at1.shtml?ero.

STORM SURGE: Minor coastal flooding is possible along the Mexico 
coast within areas of onshore flow. 

SURF:  Swells generated by this system are affecting portions of the 
Gulf coast of Mexico and are expected to spread northwestward across 
the northwestern Gulf of Mexico coastline through midweek.  These 
swells are likely to cause life-threatening surf and rip current 
conditions .  Please consult products from your local weather 
office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next intermediate advisory at 700 PM CDT.
Next complete advisory at 1000 PM CDT.
 
$$
Forecaster Papin
 
NNNN
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
