<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL042024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>INTERMEDIATE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>4</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>16A</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240806 08:00:00 AM EDT</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240806 12:00:00 PM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20240806120000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0800 AM EDT Tue Aug 06</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1722945600</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL STORM</systemType>
<systemName>DEBBY</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>31.9</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-81.3</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>31.9N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>81.3W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>45</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>75</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>40</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>999</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.50</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>NE OR 50 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>6</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>9</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>5</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 20 MI...35 KM SW OF SAVANNAH GEORGIA</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 105 MI...165 KM SW OF CHARLESTON SOUTH CAROLINA</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT4 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Storm Debby Intermediate Advisory Number 16A
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL042024
800 AM EDT Tue Aug 06 2024

...DEBBY EXPECTED TO MOVE OFFSHORE OF THE GEORGIA COAST LATER 
TODAY...
...MAJOR FLOOD THREAT OVER PORTIONS OF GEORGIA, SOUTH CAROLINA, AND 
NORTH CAROLINA OVER THE NEXT FEW DAYS...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 800 AM EDT...1200 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...31.9N 81.3W
ABOUT 20 MI...35 KM SW OF SAVANNAH GEORGIA
ABOUT 105 MI...165 KM SW OF CHARLESTON SOUTH CAROLINA
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...45 MPH...75 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...NE OR 50 DEGREES AT 6 MPH...9 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...999 MB...29.50 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The Tropical Storm Warning south of Altamaha Sound is discontinued.

SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Storm Surge Warning is in effect for...
* Altamaha Sound, Georgia to South Santee River, South Carolina
 
A Storm Surge Watch is in effect for...
* North of South Santee River, South Carolina to Cape Fear, North
Carolina
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* Altamaha Sound, Georgia to Little River Inlet, South Carolina
 
A Tropical Storm Watch is in effect for...
* North of Little River Inlet, South Carolina to Surf City, North
Carolina
 
A Storm Surge Warning means there is a danger of life-threatening
inundation, from rising water moving inland from the coastline. For
a depiction of areas at risk, please see the National Weather
Service Storm Surge Watch/Warning Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov.
 
This is a life-threatening situation.  Persons located within these
areas should take all necessary actions to protect life and property
from rising water and the potential for other dangerous conditions.
Promptly follow evacuation and other instructions from local
officials.
 
A Storm Surge Watch means there is a possibility of life-
threatening inundation, from rising water moving inland from the
coastline, in the indicated locations during the next 48 hours.
For a depiction of areas at risk, please see the National Weather
Service Storm Surge Watch/Warning Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov.
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area.
 
A Tropical Storm Watch means that tropical storm conditions are
possible within the watch area, generally within 48 hours.
 
Interests elsewhere along the southeastern coast of the United
States should monitor the progress of this system. Additional
watches or warnings may be required later today.
 
For storm information specific to your area, including possible
inland watches and warnings, please monitor products issued by your
local National Weather Service forecast office.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 800 AM EDT (1200 UTC), the center of Tropical Storm Debby was
located inland over southeastern Georgia near latitude 31.9 North,
longitude 81.3 West. Debby is moving toward the northeast near 6 mph
(9 km/h).  A slow motion toward the east and then north is expected 
through Thursday night.  On the forecast track, the center of Debby 
is expected to move offshore the coast of Georgia later today, drift 
offshore through early Thursday, and then move inland over South 
Carolina on Thursday.
 
Maximum sustained winds are near 45 mph (75 km/h) with higher
gusts. Some strengthening is forecast on Wednesday and Thursday
while Debby drifts offshore.
 
Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 205 miles (335 km)
to the east of the center.  Sustained winds of 39 mph (63 km/h)  
and a gust to 48 mph (78 km/h) were recently reported at Winyah Bay 
Light near Georgetown, South Carolina.
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 999 mb (29.50 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Debby can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT4 and WMO header WTNT44 KNHC.
 
WIND:  Tropical storm conditions are expected over portions of the
tropical storm warning area along the Georgia coast through this 
morning.  Tropical storm conditions are expected to continue along 
the coast of South Carolina within the tropical storm warning area 
through Thursday night.  Tropical storm conditions are possible 
within the tropical storm watch area in North Carolina beginning 
Wednesday night.
 
STORM SURGE: The combination of storm surge and tide will cause
normally dry areas near the coast to be flooded by rising waters
moving inland from the shoreline. The water could reach the
following heights above ground somewhere in the indicated areas if
the peak surge occurs at the time of high tide...
 
Altamaha Sound, GA to Cape Fear, NC...2-4 ft
 
For a complete depiction of areas at risk of storm surge inundation,
please see the National Weather Service Peak Storm Surge Graphic,
available at hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?peakSurge.
 
RAINFALL: Debby is expected to produce potentially historic rainfall
totals of 10 to 20 inches, with maximum amounts of 25 inches,
bringing areas of catastrophic flooding across portions of southeast
Georgia, the eastern half of South Carolina, and southeast North
Carolina through Friday.
 
From northern North Carolina through portions of the Mid-Atlantic
States, 4 to 8 inches of rainfall, with local amounts to 12 inches,
are expected through Sunday morning. This rainfall will likely
result in areas of considerable flash and urban flooding, with river
flooding possible.
 
An additional scattered 1 to 2 inches of rainfall, with maximum
amounts of 4 inches is possible across western portion of the
Central Florida Peninsula today which may aggravate any ongoing
flooding conditions across that vicinity.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall and flash flooding
associated with  Debby, please see the National Weather Service
Storm Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?rainqpf and the Flash Flood Risk
graphic at hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?ero.  For a list of
rainfall observations (and wind reports) associated this storm, see
the companion storm summary at WBCSCCNS4 with the WMO header ACUS44
KWBC or at the following link:
www.wpc.ncep.noaa.gov/discussions/nfdscc4.html.
 
TORNADOES: A few tornadoes are possible over coastal South Carolina
tonight through early Wednesday morning.
 
SURF:  Swells generated by Debby are expected to affect much of the
Gulf coast of Florida through tonight.  Swells will continue to
affect the Southeast U.S. coast through the end of the week.
These conditions are likely to cause life-threatening surf and rip
current conditions. Please consult products from your local weather
office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 1100 AM EDT.
 
$$
Forecaster Pasch
 
NNNN
 
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
