<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL152024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>INTERMEDIATE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>5</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>2A</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20241019 01:00:00 AM CDT</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20241019 06:00:00 AM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20241019060000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0100 AM CDT Sat Oct 19</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1729317600</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL STORM</systemType>
<systemName>NADINE</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>17.3</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-86.4</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>17.3N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>86.4W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>40</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>65</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>35</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>1004</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.65</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>W OR 270 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>8</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>13</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>7</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 120 MI...190 KM E OF BELIZE CITY</systemGeoRefPt1>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT5 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Storm Nadine Intermediate Advisory Number 2A
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL152024
100 AM CDT Sat Oct 19 2024
 
...TROPICAL STORM NADINE FORMS EAST OF BELIZE...
...TROPICAL STORM WARNINGS ISSUED FOR PORTIONS OF BELIZE AND THE 
YUCATAN PENINSULA OF MEXICO...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 100 AM CDT...0600 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...17.3N 86.4W
ABOUT 120 MI...190 KM E OF BELIZE CITY
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...40 MPH...65 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...W OR 270 DEGREES AT 8 MPH...13 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...1004 MB...29.65 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The government of Belize has issued a Tropical Storm Warning from 
Belize City northward to the border with Mexico.

The government of Mexico has issued a Tropical Storm Warning from 
Tulum southward to the border with Belize, including Cozumel.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* Belize City, Belize to Tulum, Mexico, including Cozumel
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area, in this case within the 
next 12 to 24 hours.
 
Interests elsewhere in Belize and the Yucatan Peninsula of Mexico
should monitor the progress of this system.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor products 
issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
Recent satellite-derived wind data indicate that the disturbance 
over the northwestern Caribbean Sea has become a tropical storm.  
At 100 AM CDT (0600 UTC), the center of Tropical Storm Nadine was 
centered near latitude 17.3 North, longitude 86.4 West.  Nadine is 
moving toward the west near 8 mph (13 km/h), and this general motion 
should continue through tonight.  On the forecast track, Nadine is
expected to move inland along the coast of Belize later today.
 
Maximum sustained winds are near 40 mph (65 km/h) with higher gusts. 
Some additional slight strengthening is possible before Nadine makes 
landfall later today.

Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 195 miles (315 km) 
north of the center.  A WeatherFlow station at Xel-Ha Park near 
Tulum, Mexico, recently measured a wind gust to 40 mph (65 km/h).

The estimated minimum central pressure is 1004 mb (29.65 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Nadine can be found in the Tropical Cyclone 
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT5 and WMO header WTNT45 KNHC 
and on the web at hurricanes.gov/text/MIATCDAT5.shtml
 
RAINFALL: Widespread 4 to 8 inch rainfall amounts are expected 
across northern Belize, northern Guatemala, and the southern states 
of Mexico from Quintana Roo westward to Veracruz. Isolated areas of
amounts exceeding 12 inches are also possible through late Tuesday.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall associated with
Tropical Storm Nadine, please see the National Weather Service Storm 
Total Rainfall Graphic, available at 
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at5.shtml?rainqpf
 
WIND: Tropical storm conditions are expected within the warning area
today.
 
STORM SURGE: Minor coastal flooding is possible in areas of onshore
winds near and to the north of where the center moves inland.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 400 AM CDT.
 
$$
Forecaster Berg
 
NNNN
 
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
