<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL022024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>INTERMEDIATE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>2</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>3A</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240629 08:00:00 AM AST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240629 12:00:00 PM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>202406291200</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0800 AM AST Sat Jun 29</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1719662400</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL STORM</systemType>
<systemName>BERYL</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>9.8</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-46.8</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>9.8N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>46.8W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>60</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>95</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>50</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>999</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.50</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>W OR 280 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>21</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>33</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>18</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 975 MI...1570 KM ESE OF BARBADOS</systemGeoRefPt1>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT2 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Storm Beryl Intermediate Advisory Number 3A
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL022024
800 AM AST Sat Jun 29 2024
 
...BERYL STRENGTHENING...
...EXPECTED TO BECOME A HURRICANE BEFORE IT REACHES THE WINDWARD 
ISLANDS...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 800 AM AST...1200 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...9.8N 46.8W
ABOUT 975 MI...1570 KM ESE OF BARBADOS
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...60 MPH...95 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...W OR 280 DEGREES AT 21 MPH...33 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...999 MB...29.50 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
None
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Hurricane Watch is in effect for...
* Barbados
 
Interests elsewhere in the Lesser Antilles should closely monitor
the progress of Beryl.  Additional watches and warnings will likely
be required for portions of this area later this morning.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 800 AM AST (1200 UTC), the center of Tropical Storm Beryl was
located near latitude 9.8 North, longitude 46.8 West. Beryl is
moving toward the west near 21 mph (33 km/h).  A relatively quick
westward to west-northwestward motion is expected during the next
few days.  On the forecast track, the system is expected to move
across the Windward Islands late Sunday night and Monday.
 
Maximum sustained winds have increased to near 60 mph (95 km/h) 
with higher gusts. Steady to rapid strengthening is expected during 
the next couple of days, and Beryl is forecast to become a 
hurricane tonight or early Sunday with additional strengthening 
expected after that.
 
Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 45 miles (75 km)
from the center.
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 999 mb (29.50 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Tropical Storm Beryl can be found in the
Tropical Cyclone Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT2 and WMO
header WTNT42 KNHC.
 
WIND: Hurricane conditions are possible in the hurricane watch area
by Sunday night or Monday morning, with tropical storm conditions
possible on Sunday.

STORM SURGE:  A dangerous storm surge will raise water levels by
as much as 2 to 4 feet above normal tide levels in areas of 
onshore flow in the Hurricane Watch area.  Near the coast, the 
surge will be accompanied by large and destructive waves.
 
RAINFALL:  Tropical Storm Beryl is expected to produce rainfall
totals of 3 to 6 inches across Barbados and the Windward Islands.
This rainfall may produce localized flooding in vulnerable areas.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall and flash flooding
associated with Tropical Storm Beryl, please see the National
Weather Service Storm Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at2.shtml?rainqpf and the Flash Flood Risk
graphic at hurricanes.gov/graphics_at2.shtml?ero
 
SURF:  Swells generated by the storm are expected to reach the
Windward and southern Leeward Islands by late Sunday.  These swells
are likely to cause life-threatening surf and rip current
conditions.  Please consult products from your local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 1100 AM AST.
 
$$
Forecaster Cangialosi
 
NNNN
 
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
