<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL042024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>ROUTINE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>4</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>24</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240808 05:00:00 AM EDT</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240808 09:00:00 AM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20240808090000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0500 AM EDT Thu Aug 08</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1723107600</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL STORM</systemType>
<systemName>DEBBY</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>33.2</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-79.7</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>33.2N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>79.7W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>50</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>85</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>45</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>994</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.36</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>NW OR 325 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>5</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>7</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>4</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 30 MI...50 KM NNE OF CHARLESTON SOUTH CAROLINA</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 60 MI...95 KM SW OF MYRTLE BEACH SOUTH CAROLINA</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT4 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Storm Debby Advisory Number  24
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL042024
500 AM EDT Thu Aug 08 2024
 
...DEBBY'S CENTER CREEPING INLAND OVER SOUTH CAROLINA...
...MAJOR FLOOD THREAT CONTINUES FOR PORTIONS OF THE CAROLINAS AND
WESTERN VIRGINIA...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 500 AM EDT...0900 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...33.2N 79.7W
ABOUT 30 MI...50 KM NNE OF CHARLESTON SOUTH CAROLINA
ABOUT 60 MI...95 KM SW OF MYRTLE BEACH SOUTH CAROLINA
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...50 MPH...85 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...NW OR 325 DEGREES AT 5 MPH...7 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...994 MB...29.36 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
A Tropical Storm Warning has been issued for the coast of North
Carolina east of Surf City to Ocracoke Inlet.
 
The Tropical Storm Warning has been discontinued south of South
Santee River, South Carolina.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* North of South Santee River, South Carolina to Ocracoke Inlet,
North Carolina
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area, in this case during the
next 12 hours.
 
For storm information specific to your area, including possible
inland watches and warnings, please monitor products issued by your
local National Weather Service forecast office.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 500 AM EDT (0900 UTC), the center of Tropical Storm Debby was
located inland over South Carolina near latitude 33.2 North,
longitude 79.7 West.  Debby is moving toward the northwest near 5
mph (7 km/h) but is expected to accelerate toward the
north-northwest and north across eastern South Carolina and central
North Carolina through tonight.  Debby is then expected to move
faster toward the northeast across the U.S. Mid-Atlantic and
Northeast on Friday and Atlantic Canada on Saturday.
 
Maximum sustained winds are near 50 mph (85 km/h) with higher gusts.
Weakening is forecast during the next day or so, and Debby is
likely to become a tropical depression by this afternoon or
evening.  Debby should then merge with a front and become
extratropical on Friday.
 
Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 185 miles (295 km)
to the east of the center.  A sustained wind of 36 mph (57 km/h) 
and a gust to 39 mph (63 km/h) was recently reported at Cape 
Lookout, North Carolina.
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 994 mb (29.36 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Debby can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT4 and WMO header WTNT44 KNHC.
 
WIND: Tropical storm conditions are expected to continue along the
coasts of South Carolina and North Carolina within the tropical
storm warning area through today.
 
STORM SURGE: The combination of storm surge and tide will cause
normally dry areas near the coast to be flooded by rising waters
moving inland from the shoreline. The water could reach the
following heights above ground somewhere in the indicated areas if
the peak surge occurs at the time of high tide...
 
South Santee River to Ocracoke Inlet including the Neuse and
Pamlico Rivers...1 to 3 ft
 
For a complete depiction of areas at risk of storm surge inundation,
please see the National Weather Service Peak Storm Surge Graphic,
available at hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?peakSurge.
 
RAINFALL: Debby is expected to produce an additional 3 to 6 inches
of rainfall with locally higher amounts, across portions of
southeastern North Carolina leading to maximum storm total amounts
as high as 15 inches.  Additional rainfall of 1 to 3 inches over
portions of eastern South Carolina will bring maximum storm total
amounts as high as 20 to 25 inches. Considerable flooding is
expected across portions of eastern South Carolina and southeast
North Carolina through Friday.
 
From central North Carolina northward across portions of Virginia, 3
to 7 inches with local amounts to 10 inches, are expected through
Friday. This rainfall will likely result in areas of considerable
flash and urban flooding, with river flooding possible.
 
From portions of Maryland north through Upstate New York and
Vermont, 2 to 4 inches, with local amounts to 6 inches, are expected
through Friday night. This will likely result in areas of
considerable flash and urban flooding as well as river flooding.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall and flash flooding
associated with  Debby, please see the National Weather Service
Storm Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?rainqpf and the Flash Flood Risk
graphic at hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?ero.  For a list of
rainfall observations (and wind reports) associated this storm, see
the companion storm summary at WBCSCCNS4 with the WMO header ACUS44
KWBC or at the following link:
www.wpc.ncep.noaa.gov/discussions/nfdscc4.html.
 
TORNADOES: A few tornadoes may occur over parts of eastern North
Carolina this morning.  The tornado threat will shift northward
today into central North Carolina and southern to central Virginia.
 
SURF:  Large swells will continue to affect the Southeast U.S.
coast through the end of the week. These conditions are likely to
cause life-threatening surf and rip current conditions. Please
consult products from your local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next intermediate advisory at 800 AM EDT.
Next complete advisory at 1100 AM EDT.
 
$$
Forecaster Berg
 
NNNN
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
