<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL042024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>INTERMEDIATE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>4</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>18A</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240806 08:00:00 PM EDT</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240807 12:00:00 AM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20240807000000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0800 PM EDT Tue Aug 06</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1722988800</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL STORM</systemType>
<systemName>DEBBY</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>31.8</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-80.6</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>31.8N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>80.6W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>40</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>65</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>35</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>997</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.44</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>ENE OR 75 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>3</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>6</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>3</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 30 MI...50 KM SE OF SAVANNAH GEORGIA</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 85 MI...135 KM SSW OF CHARLESTON SOUTH CAROLINA</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT4 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Storm Debby Intermediate Advisory Number 18A
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL042024
800 PM EDT Tue Aug 06 2024
 
...CENTER OF DEBBY NOW OFFSHORE OF THE COASTS OF GEORGIA AND SOUTH 
CAROLINA...
...MAJOR FLOOD THREAT FOR PORTIONS OF THE SOUTHEASTERN UNITED
STATES THIS WEEK...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 800 PM EDT...0000 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...31.8N 80.6W
ABOUT 30 MI...50 KM SE OF SAVANNAH GEORGIA
ABOUT 85 MI...135 KM SSW OF CHARLESTON SOUTH CAROLINA
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...40 MPH...65 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...ENE OR 75 DEGREES AT 3 MPH...6 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...997 MB...29.44 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
None.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Storm Surge Watch is in effect for...
* North of South Santee River, South Carolina to Cape Fear, North
Carolina
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* Altamaha Sound, Georgia to Surf City, North Carolina
 
A Tropical Storm Watch is in effect for...
* North of Surf City, North Carolina to Beaufort Inlet, North
Carolina
 
A Storm Surge Watch means there is a possibility of life-
threatening inundation, from rising water moving inland from the
coastline, in the indicated locations during the next 48 hours.
For a depiction of areas at risk, please see the National Weather
Service Storm Surge Watch/Warning Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov.
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area.
 
A Tropical Storm Watch means that tropical storm conditions are
possible within the watch area, generally within 48 hours.
 
Interests elsewhere along the southeastern coast of the United
States should monitor the progress of this system. Additional
watches or warnings may be required tonight or Wednesday.
 
For storm information specific to your area, including possible
inland watches and warnings, please monitor products issued by your
local National Weather Service forecast office.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 800 PM EDT (0000 UTC), the center of Tropical Storm Debby was
located near latitude 31.8 North, longitude 80.6 West.  Debby is
moving toward the east-northeast near 3 mph (6 km/h).  A slow motion
toward the east and then north is expected through Thursday night.
On the forecast track, the center of Debby is expected to slowly 
move away from the coast of Georgia and South Carolina tonight, 
continue to drift offshore through early Thursday, and then
move inland over South Carolina on Thursday morning.
 
Maximum sustained winds are near 40 mph (65 km/h) with higher 
gusts. Some strengthening is forecast on Wednesday while Debby
drifts offshore.
 
Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 205 miles (335 km)
from the center.
 
The estimated minimum central pressure based on surface 
observations is 997 mb (29.44 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Debby can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT4 and WMO header WTNT44 KNHC.
 
WIND:  Tropical storm conditions are expected over portions of the
tropical storm warning area along the Georgia coast for the next
few hours.  Tropical storm conditions are expected to continue along
the coast of South Carolina within the tropical storm warning area
through Thursday night.  Tropical storm conditions are expected
within the tropical storm warning area in North Carolina beginning
early Wednesday.  Tropical Storm conditions are possible within the
Tropical Storm Watch area in North Carolina beginning Wednesday.
 
STORM SURGE: The combination of storm surge and tide will cause
normally dry areas near the coast to be flooded by rising waters
moving inland from the shoreline. The water could reach the
following heights above ground somewhere in the indicated areas if
the peak surge occurs at the time of high tide...
 
South Santee River, SC to Cape Fear, NC...2-4 ft
 
For a complete depiction of areas at risk of storm surge inundation,
please see the National Weather Service Peak Storm Surge Graphic,
available at hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?peakSurge.
 
RAINFALL: Debby is expected to produce potentially historic rainfall
totals of 10 to 20 inches, with maximum amounts of 25 inches,
bringing areas of catastrophic flooding across portions of the
eastern half of South Carolina, and southeast North Carolina through
Friday.
 
From central South Carolina to the Update of South Carolina,
northward into Southwest Virginia,  portions of the Mid-Atlantic
States, western and northern New York State into Northern New
England, 3 to 6 inches with local amounts to 8 inches, are expected
through Saturday. This rainfall will likely result in areas of
considerable flash and urban flooding, with river flooding possible.
 
An additional scattered 1 to 3 inches of rainfall is possible across
southeast Georgia through tonight, which may aggravate any ongoing 
flooding conditions across that vicinity.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall and flash flooding
associated with  Debby, please see the National Weather Service
Storm Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?rainqpf and the Flash Flood Risk
graphic at hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?ero.  For a list of
rainfall observations (and wind reports) associated this storm, see
the companion storm summary at WBCSCCNS4 with the WMO header ACUS44
KWBC or at the following link:
www.wpc.ncep.noaa.gov/discussions/nfdscc4.html.
 
TORNADOES: A few tornadoes are possible over portions of coastal
South Carolina and North Carolina this afternoon through Wednesday
morning.
 
SURF:  Large swells will continue to affect the Southeast U.S.
coast through the end of the week. These conditions are likely to
cause life-threatening surf and rip current conditions. Please
consult products from your local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 1100 PM EDT.
 
$$
Forecaster Beven
 
NNNN
 
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
