<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL022024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>ROUTINE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>2</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>5</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240629 05:00:00 PM AST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240629 09:00:00 PM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>202406292100</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0500 PM AST Sat Jun 29</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1719694800</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>HURRICANE</systemType>
<systemName>BERYL</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>10.1</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-49.3</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>10.1N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>49.3W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>75</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>120</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>65</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>992</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.30</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>CATEGORY 1</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>W OR 275 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>22</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>35</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>19</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 720 MI...1160 KM ESE OF BARBADOS</systemGeoRefPt1>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT2 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Hurricane Beryl Advisory Number   5
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL022024
500 PM AST Sat Jun 29 2024
 
...BERYL IS NOW A HURRICANE AND FORECAST TO INTENSIFY QUICKLY...
...EXPECTED TO BRING LIFE-THREATENING WINDS AND STORM SURGE 
TO THE WINDWARD ISLANDS AS A MAJOR HURRICANE...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 500 PM AST...2100 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...10.1N 49.3W
ABOUT 720 MI...1160 KM ESE OF BARBADOS
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...75 MPH...120 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...W OR 275 DEGREES AT 22 MPH...35 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...992 MB...29.30 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The government of Barbados has issued a Hurricane Warning for the
island.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Hurricane Warning is in effect for...
* Barbados
 
A Hurricane Watch is in effect for...
* St Lucia
* St. Vincent and the Grenadine Islands
* Grenada
 
A Tropical Storm Watch is in effect for...
* Martinique
* Dominica
* Tobago

A Hurricane Warning means that hurricane conditions are expected
somewhere within the warning area.  A warning is typically issued
36 hours before the anticipated first occurrence of
tropical-storm-force winds, conditions that make outside
preparations difficult or dangerous.  Preparations to protect life
and property should be rushed to completion.

A Hurricane Watch means that hurricane conditions are possible
within the watch area.  A watch is typically issued 48 hours
before the anticipated first occurrence of tropical-storm-force
winds, conditions that make outside preparations difficult or
dangerous.

A Tropical Storm Watch means that tropical storm conditions are
possible within the watch area, generally within 48 hours.
 
Interests elsewhere in the Lesser Antilles should closely monitor
the progress of Beryl.  Additional watches and warnings will likely
be required for portions of this area this evening.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 500 PM AST (2100 UTC), the center of Hurricane Beryl was located
near latitude 10.1 North, longitude 49.3 West. Beryl is moving
toward the west near 22 mph (35 km/h). A relatively quick
westward to west-northwestward motion is expected during the next
few days.  On the forecast track, the center of Beryl is expected 
to move across the Windward Islands late Sunday night and Monday.
 
Maximum sustained winds have increased to near 75 mph (120 km/h) 
with higher gusts.  Continued steady to rapid strengthening is 
forecast, and Beryl is expected to become a dangerous major 
hurricane before it reaches the Windward Islands.
 
Hurricane-force winds extend outward up to 10 miles (20 km) from the
center and tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 60 miles
(95 km).
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 992 mb (29.30 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Beryl can be found in the Tropical Cyclone 
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT2 and WMO header WTNT42 KNHC.
 
WIND: Hurricane conditions are expected in the hurricane warning 
area beginning Sunday night.  Hurricane conditions are possible in 
the hurricane watch areas Sunday night or Monday morning. 
Devastating wind damage is expected where the eyewall of Beryl 
moves through portions of the Windward Islands. 

Wind speeds atop and on the windward sides of hills and mountains 
are often up to 30 percent stronger than the near-surface winds 
indicated in this advisory, and in some elevated locations could be 
even greater.

Tropical storm conditions are possible in the tropical storm watch 
areas by Monday morning.  
 
STORM SURGE:  A life-threatening storm surge will raise water levels 
by as much as 5 to 7 feet above normal tide levels in areas of 
onshore flow near where Beryl makes landfall in the hurricane 
warning and watch areas.  Near the coast, the surge will be 
accompanied by large and destructive waves.
 
RAINFALL: Beryl is expected to produce rainfall totals of 3 to 6 
inches across Barbados and the Windward Islands Sunday night into 
Monday. This rainfall may cause flooding in vulnerable areas.

Showers and thunderstorms well north of Beryl may produce 1 to 4
inches of rain over portions of southeastern Puerto Rico Monday
night into Tuesday.
 
Rainfall from Beryl may impact portions of southern Hispaniola
Tuesday into Wednesday, with 2 to 6 inches of rain possible.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall and flash flooding
associated with Beryl, please see the National Weather Service 
Storm Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at2.shtml?rainqpf
 
SURF:  Swells generated by Beryl are expected to reach the 
Windward and southern Leeward Islands by late Sunday.  These swells 
are likely to cause life-threatening surf and rip current 
conditions.  Please consult products from your local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next intermediate advisory at 800 PM AST.
Next complete advisory at 1100 PM AST.
 
$$
Forecaster Cangialosi
 
NNNN
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
