<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>CP012024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS CENTRAL PACIFIC HURRICANE CENTER HONOLULU HI</issuingUnit>
<messageType>INTERMEDIATE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>1</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>8A</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240824 02:00:00 AM HST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240824 12:00:00 PM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>202408241200</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0200 AM HST Sat Aug 24</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1724500800</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL STORM</systemType>
<systemName>HONE</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>17.5</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-151.3</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>17.5N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>151.3W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>65</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>105</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>55</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>998</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.47</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>WNW OR 280 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>15</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>24</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>13</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 290 MI...465 KM ESE OF HILO HAWAII</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 500 MI...805 KM ESE OF HONOLULU HAWAII</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC HFOTCPCP1 ALL
TTAA00 PHFO DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Storm Hone Intermediate Advisory Number 8A
NWS Central Pacific Hurricane Center Honolulu HI   CP012024
200 AM HST Sat Aug 24 2024
 
...HONE STRENGTHENS SLIGHTLY AS IT CONTINUES WESTWARD TOWARD
HAWAII...
...TROPICAL STORM WARNING REMAINS IN EFFECT FOR THE BIG ISLAND...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 200 AM HST...1200 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...17.5N 151.3W
ABOUT 290 MI...465 KM ESE OF HILO HAWAII
ABOUT 500 MI...805 KM ESE OF HONOLULU HAWAII
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...65 MPH...105 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...WNW OR 280 DEGREES AT 15 MPH...24 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...998 MB...29.47 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
None.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* Hawaii County
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area within 36 hours.
 
Interests elsewhere in Hawaii should monitor the progress of Hone.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by the National Weather Service office in
Honolulu Hawaii.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 200 AM HST (1200 UTC), the center of Tropical Storm Hone was
located near latitude 17.5 North, longitude 151.3 West. Hone is
moving toward the west near 15 mph (24 km/h). This motion slightly 
north of due west is expected to continue over the next several days
with a gradual decrease in forward speed. On the forecast track, the
center of Hone is expected to pass near or south of the Big Island
tonight into early Sunday.
 
Maximum sustained winds measured by Hurricane Hunter Aircraft are 
near 65 mph (105 km/h) with higher gusts. Strengthening is forecast 
during the next 48 hours, and Hone is expected to be a hurricane 
Sunday through Monday southwest of the Big Island of Hawaii.
 
Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 115 miles (185 km)
from the center.
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 998 mb (29.47 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Tropical Storm Hone can be found in the Tropical 
Cyclone Discussion under AWIPS header TCDCP1 and WMO header WTPA41 
PHFO, and on the web at hurricanes.gov/text/HFOTCDCP1.shtml.
 
WIND: Tropical storm conditions are expected in the warning area as
early as Saturday afternoon and continuing into Sunday. Winds are
expected to be strongest where they blow downslope from higher
terrain, over headlands, and through passes.
 
RAINFALL: Hone is expected to produce storm total rainfall of 5 to
10 inches over mainly windward and southeast facing slopes of the
Big Island, with locally higher amounts possible. Rainfall totals
of 2 to 4 inches will be possible over portions of the smaller
islands, mainly windward.
 
SURF: Swells generated by Tropical Storm Hone will begin
impact eastern portions of the Hawaiian Islands later tonight,
then spread to the remainder of the state through the rest of
the weekend. These swells will produce life-threatening surf and
rip currents.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 500 AM HST.
 
$$
Forecaster Jelsema
 
NNNN
 
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
