<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL152024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>INTERMEDIATE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>5</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>3A</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20241019 07:00:00 AM CDT</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20241019 12:00:00 PM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20241019120000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0700 AM CDT Sat Oct 19</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1729339200</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL STORM</systemType>
<systemName>NADINE</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>17.3</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-87.3</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>17.3N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>87.3W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>45</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>70</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>40</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>1002</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.58</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>W OR 270 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>9</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>15</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>8</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 60 MI...95 KM E OF BELIZE CITY</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 105 MI...165 KM SE OF CHETUMAL MEXICO</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT5 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Storm Nadine Intermediate Advisory Number 3A
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL152024
700 AM CDT Sat Oct 19 2024
 
...TROPICAL STORM NADINE NEARING LANDFALL IN BELIZE...
...HEAVY RAINS AND TROPICAL STORM CONDITIONS SPREADING OVER PARTS 
OF BELIZE AND THE YUCATAN PENINSULA OF MEXICO...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 700 AM CDT...1200 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...17.3N 87.3W
ABOUT 60 MI...95 KM E OF BELIZE CITY
ABOUT 105 MI...165 KM SE OF CHETUMAL MEXICO
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...45 MPH...70 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...W OR 270 DEGREES AT 9 MPH...15 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...1002 MB...29.58 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
None.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* Belize City, Belize to Cancun, Mexico, including Cozumel
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area, in this case later this 
morning.
 
Interests elsewhere in Belize and the Yucatan Peninsula of Mexico
should monitor the progress of this system.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 700 AM CDT (1200 UTC), the center of Tropical Storm Nadine was 
located near latitude 17.3 North, longitude 87.3 West.  Nadine is 
moving toward the west near 9 mph (15 km/h), and this general motion 
with an increase in forward speed is expected today and tonight.  On 
the forecast track, the center of Nadine is forecast to make 
landfall along the coast of Belize later this morning or early 
afternoon, and then continue across northern Guatemala and 
southeastern Mexico late this afternoon into tonight.
 
Maximum sustained winds have increased to 45 mph (70 km/h) with 
higher gusts. Some slight additional strengthening is possible this 
morning before Nadine makes landfall.  Weakening is forecast to 
begin this afternoon once Nadine is inland, and the system is likely 
to dissipate over southeastern Mexico by early Sunday.
 
Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 230 miles (370 km)
north of the center. 
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 1002 mb (29.58 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Nadine can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT5 and WMO header WTNT45 KNHC
and on the web at hurricanes.gov/text/MIATCDAT5.shtml
 
RAINFALL: Widespread 4 to 8 inch rainfall amounts are expected with
Nadine across northern Belize, northern Guatemala, and southern
Mexican states from Quintana Roo westward to Veracruz.  Isolated
areas of amounts exceeding 12 inches are also possible through late
Tuesday.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall associated with
Tropical Storm Nadine, please see the National Weather Service Storm
Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at5.shtml?rainqpf.
 
WIND: Tropical storm conditions are expected within the warning area
through this afternoon.
 
STORM SURGE: Minor coastal flooding is possible in areas of onshore
winds near and to the north of where the center moves inland.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 1000 AM CDT.
 
$$
Forecaster Papin
 
NNNN
 
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
