<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL092024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>INTERMEDIATE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>4</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>15A</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240927 02:00:00 AM EDT</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240927 06:00:00 AM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20240927060000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0200 AM EDT Fri Sep 27</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1727416800</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>HURRICANE</systemType>
<systemName>HELENE</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>31.2</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-83.3</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>31.2N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>83.3W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>90</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>145</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>80</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>955</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>28.20</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>CATEGORY 1</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>NNE OR 15 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>26</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>42</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>23</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 30 MI...50 KM N OF VALDOSTA GEORGIA</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 85 MI...135 KM NE OF TALLAHASSEE FLORIDA</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT4 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Hurricane Helene Intermediate Advisory Number 15A
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL092024
200 AM EDT Fri Sep 27 2024
 
...HELENE WEAKENING AS IT MOVES QUICKLY NORTH-NORTHEASTWARD NEAR 
VALDOSTA GEORGIA...
...LIFE-THREATENING STORM SURGE, WINDS, AND HEAVY RAINS 
CONTINUE...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 200 AM EDT...0600 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...31.2N 83.3W
ABOUT 30 MI...50 KM N OF VALDOSTA GEORGIA
ABOUT 85 MI...135 KM NE OF TALLAHASSEE FLORIDA
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...90 MPH...145 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...NNE OR 15 DEGREES AT 26 MPH...42 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...955 MB...28.20 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The Tropical Storm Warning has been discontinued for the Florida 
Keys, including the Dry Tortugas.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Storm Surge Warning is in effect for...
* Mexico Beach eastward and southward to Flamingo
* Tampa Bay
* Charlotte Harbor
 
A Hurricane Warning is in effect for...
* Anclote River to Mexico Beach
 
A Hurricane Watch is in effect for...
* Englewood to Anclote River, including Tampa Bay
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* Flamingo to Anclote River, including Tampa Bay
* West of Mexico Beach to the Okaloosa/Walton County Line
* Flamingo northward to Little River Inlet
* Lake Okeechobee
 
A Storm Surge Warning means there is a danger of life-threatening
inundation, from rising water moving inland from the coastline. For
a depiction of areas at risk, please see the National Weather
Service Storm Surge Watch/Warning Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov.  This is a life-threatening situation.  Persons
located within these areas should take all necessary actions to
protect life and property from rising water and the potential for
other dangerous conditions.  Promptly follow evacuation and other
instructions from local officials.
 
A Hurricane Warning means that hurricane conditions are expected
somewhere within the warning area.
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area.
 
A Hurricane Watch means that hurricane conditions are possible
within the watch area.
 
For storm information specific to your area in the United
States, including possible inland watches and warnings, please
monitor products issued by your local National Weather Service
forecast office. 
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 200 AM EDT (0600 UTC), the center of Hurricane Helene was located
near latitude 31.2 North, longitude 83.3 West. Helene is moving
toward the north-northeast near 26 mph (42 km/h).  A turn toward the
north is expected overnight, taking the center over central and 
northern Georgia this morning.  After that, Helene is expected to 
turn northwestward and slow down over the Tennessee Valley later 
today and Saturday.
 
Maximum sustained winds have decreased to near near 90 mph      
(145 km/h) with higher gusts.  Continued weakening is expected, but 
the fast forward speed will allow strong, damaging winds, 
especially in gusts, to penetrate well inland across the 
southeastern United States, including over the higher terrain of
the southern Appalachians.
 
Hurricane-force winds extend outward up to 30 miles (50 km) from
the center and tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 310
miles (500 km), mainly to the east of the center.  A automated 
station at Grassy Pond, Georgia, just south of Valdosta, recently 
reported a wind gust of 96 mph (154 km/h).  On the Atlantic 
coast of Georgia, Savannah International Airport recently reported 
a wind gust of 75 mph (120 km/h.)
 
The minimum central pressure based on surface observations in the 
Valdosta area is 955 mb (28.20 inches).
 
A NOAA National Ocean Service tide gauge located on Cedar Key
recently reported a water level of 9.30 feet above mean higher high
water.
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key Messages for Helene can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT4 and WMO header WTNT44 KNHC
and on the web at hurricanes.gov/text/MIATCDAT4.shtml
 
STORM SURGE: The combination of a life-threatening storm surge and
the tide will cause normally dry areas near the coast to be flooded
by rising waters moving inland from the shoreline.  The water could
reach the following heights above ground somewhere in the indicated
areas if the peak surge occurs at the time of high tide...
 
Carrabelle, FL to Suwannee River, FL...15-20 ft
Apalachicola, FL to Carrabelle, FL...10-15 ft
Suwannee River, FL to Chassahowitzka, FL...10-15 ft
Chassahowitzka, FL to Anclote River, FL...8-12 ft
Indian Pass, FL to Apalachicola, FL...6-10 ft
Anclote River, FL to Middle of Longboat Key, FL...5-8 ft
Tampa Bay...5-8 ft
Middle of Longboat Key, FL to Englewood, FL...4-7 ft
East of Mexico Beach, FL to Indian Pass, FL...3-5 ft
Englewood, FL to Flamingo, FL...3-5 ft
Charlotte Harbor...3-5 ft
 
The deepest water will occur along the immediate coast near and to
the east of the landfall location, where the surge will be
accompanied by large and dangerous waves.  Surge-related flooding
depends on the relative timing of the surge and the tidal cycle,
and can vary greatly over short distances.  For information
specific to your area, please see products issued by your local
National Weather Service forecast office.
 
For a complete depiction of areas at risk of storm surge inundation,
please see the National Weather Service Peak Storm Surge Graphic,
available at hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?peakSurge.
 
WIND: Hurricane conditions are occurring within the hurricane
warning area.  When the eye passes over, people are reminded to not
venture out into the relative calm, as hazardous winds will increase
very quickly when the eye passes.  Tropical storm conditions are
occurring from southern Florida to southeastern Georgia, and these 
conditions will continue spreading northward across the tropical 
storm warning areas in the Southeastern U.S. through today.  
Strong, damaging winds,  especially in gusts, will likely penetrate 
as far inland as the higher terrain of the southern Appalachians.
 
RAINFALL: Over portions of the Southeastern U.S. into the Southern
Appalachians, Helene is expected to produce total rain accumulations
of 6 to 12 inches, with isolated totals around 20 inches. This
rainfall will likely result in catastrophic and potentially
life-threatening flash and urban flooding, along with significant
river flooding. Numerous significant landslides are expected in
steep terrain across the southern Appalachians.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall associated with
Hurricane Helene, please see the National Weather Service Storm
Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?rainqpf and the Flash Flood Risk
graphic at hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?ero.
 
For a list of rainfall observations (and wind reports) associated
this storm, see the companion storm summary at WBCSCCNS4 with the
WMO header ACUS44 KWBC or at the following link:
www.wpc.ncep.noaa.gov/discussions/nfdscc4.html.
 
TORNADOES: The risk for several tornadoes continues tonight through
this morning over parts of north/central Florida, Georgia, South 
Carolina, and southern North Carolina. The tornado risk will 
persist today across the Carolinas and southern Virginia.
 
SURF: Swells generated by Helene will affect much of Florida and
the coasts of Georgia and the Carolinas during the next couple of
days.  These swells are likely to cause life-threatening surf and
rip current conditions.  Please consult products from your local
weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 500 AM EDT.
Next Tropical Cyclone Update at 300 and 400 AM EDT.
 
$$
Forecaster Beven

 
NNNN
 
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
