<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL022024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>ROUTINE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>2</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>13</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240701 05:00:00 PM AST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240701 09:00:00 PM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>202407012100</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0500 PM AST Mon Jul 01</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1719867600</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>HURRICANE</systemType>
<systemName>BERYL</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>13.2</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-63.2</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>13.2N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>63.2W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>150</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>240</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>130</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>944</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>27.88</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>CATEGORY 4</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>WNW OR 290 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>21</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>33</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>18</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 125 MI...205 KM NW OF GRENADA</systemGeoRefPt1>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT2 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Hurricane Beryl Advisory Number  13
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL022024
500 PM AST Mon Jul 01 2024
 
...MAJOR HURRICANE BERYL MOVING OVER THE SOUTHEASTERN CARIBBEAN...
...TROPICAL STORM CONDITIONS, DANGEROUS WAVES, AND HEAVY RAINFALL
PERSIST OVER THE SOUTHERN WINDWARD ISLANDS...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 500 PM AST...2100 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...13.2N 63.2W
ABOUT 125 MI...205 KM NW OF GRENADA
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...150 MPH...240 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...WNW OR 290 DEGREES AT 21 MPH...33 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...944 MB...27.88 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The government of St. Vincent and the Grenadines has changed the
Hurricane Warning to a Tropical Storm Warning for those islands.
 
The government of the Dominican Republic has changed the Tropical
Storm Watch to a Tropical Storm Warning for the south coast from
Punta Palenque westward to the border of Haiti.
 
The Tropical Storm Watch for the south coast of Haiti has been
changed to a Tropical Storm Warning.
 
The government of Trinidad and Tobago has changed the Hurricane
Warning to a Tropical Storm Warning for the island.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Hurricane Watch is in effect for...
* Jamaica
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* Grenada
* St. Vincent and the Grenadine Islands
* St. Lucia
* Martinique
* South coast of Dominican Republic from Punta Palenque westward
to the border with Haiti
* South coast of Haiti from the border with the Dominican
Republic to Anse d'Hainault
 
A Hurricane Watch means that hurricane conditions are possible
within the watch area. A watch is typically issued 48 hours
before the anticipated first occurrence of tropical-storm-force
winds, conditions that make outside preparations difficult or
dangerous.
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area within 36 hours.
 
Interests elsewhere in the Lesser Antilles, the Cayman Islands, and
the remainder of the northwestern Caribbean should closely monitor
the progress of Beryl. Additional watches or warnings may be
required tonight or on Tuesday.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 500 PM AST (2100 UTC), the center of Hurricane Beryl was located
near latitude 13.2 North, longitude 63.2 West. Beryl is moving
toward the west-northwest near 21 mph (33 km/h). The center of Beryl
will continue moving away from the southern Windward Islands 
tonight and move quickly westward to west-northwestward during the 
next few days. On the forecast track, the center of Beryl will move 
across the southeastern and central Caribbean Sea tonight through 
Tuesday and is forecast to pass near Jamaica on Wednesday.
 
Maximum sustained winds are near 150 mph (240 km/h) with higher
gusts. Beryl is a category 4 hurricane on the Saffir-Simpson
Hurricane Wind Scale. Fluctuations in strength are likely during the
next day or so, but Beryl is expected to remain an extremely
dangerous major hurricane as its moves over the eastern Caribbean.
Some weakening is expected in the central Caribbean by midweek,
though Beryl is forecast to remain a hurricane.
 
Hurricane-force winds extend outward up to 40 miles (65 km) from the 
center and tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 125 miles 
(205 km). The Hewanorra International Airport on St. Lucia recently 
reported sustained winds of 47 mph (76 km/h) and a gust of 64 mph 
(104 km/h). 
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 944 mb (27.88 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Beryl can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT2 and WMO header WTNT42 KNHC.
 
WIND:  Hurricane conditions are possible on Jamaica by Wednesday.
 
Tropical storm conditions will continue in the southern Windward 
Islands over the next few hours. Tropical storm conditions are 
expected in the warning area along the south coast of Hispaniola by 
late Tuesday.
 
STORM SURGE:  Water levels should recede into the evening over the
southern Windward Islands.
 
Storm surge could raise water levels by as much as 2 to 4 feet above
normal tide levels in areas of onshore winds along the immediate
coast of Jamaica.
 
Storm surge could raise water levels by as much as 1 to 3 feet above
ground level in areas of onshore winds along the southern coast of
Hispaniola.
 
RAINFALL:  Hurricane Beryl is expected to produce rainfall totals of
3 to 6 inches across the Windward Islands through this evening.
Localized maxima of 10 inches are possible, especially in the
Grenadines and Grenada. This rainfall may cause flash flooding in
vulnerable areas.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall and flash flooding
associated with Hurricane Beryl, please see the National Weather
Service Storm Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at2.shtml?rainqpf
 
SURF:  Large swells generated by Beryl will continue across the
Windward and southern Leeward Islands during the next couple of
days. Swells are also expected to reach the southern coasts of
Puerto Rico and Hispaniola late tonight into Tuesday. These swells
are expected to cause life-threatening surf and rip current
conditions. Please consult products from your local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next intermediate advisory at 800 PM AST.
Next complete advisory at 1100 PM AST.
 
$$
Forecaster Reinhart
 
NNNN
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
