<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL042024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>INTERMEDIATE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>4</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>14A</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240805 08:00:00 PM EDT</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240806 12:00:00 AM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20240806000000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0800 PM EDT Mon Aug 05</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1722902400</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL STORM</systemType>
<systemName>DEBBY</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>30.7</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-82.4</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>30.7N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>82.4W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>45</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>75</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>40</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>996</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>29.41</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>NE OR 50 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>6</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>9</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>5</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 50 MI...80 KM E OF VALDOSTA GEORGIA</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 50 MI...80 KM WNW OF JACKSONVILLE FLORIDA</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT4 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Storm Debby Intermediate Advisory Number 14A
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL042024
800 PM EDT Mon Aug 05 2024
 
...SLOW-MOVING DEBBY BRINGING TORRENTIAL RAINS TO PORTIONS OF 
THE SOUTHEASTERN UNITED STATES...
...MAJOR FLOOD THREAT FOR THE SOUTHEASTERN UNITED STATES TO 
CONTINUE FOR THE NEXT SEVERAL DAYS...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 800 PM EDT...0000 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...30.7N 82.4W
ABOUT 50 MI...80 KM E OF VALDOSTA GEORGIA
ABOUT 50 MI...80 KM WNW OF JACKSONVILLE FLORIDA
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...45 MPH...75 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...NE OR 50 DEGREES AT 6 MPH...9 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...996 MB...29.41 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
None
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Storm Surge Warning is in effect for...
* Georgia and South Carolina coast from the Mouth of the St. Mary's
River to South Santee River South Carolina
 
A Storm Surge Watch is in effect for...
* South Carolina and North Carolina coast from north of South
Santee River to Cape Fear, North Carolina
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* St. Augustine, Florida to South Santee River, South Carolina
 
A Tropical Storm Watch is in effect for...
* North of South Santee River, South Carolina to Cape Fear, North
Carolina
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area.
 
A Tropical Storm Watch means that tropical storm conditions are
possible within the watch area, generally within 48 hours.
 
A Storm Surge Warning means there is a danger of life-threatening
inundation, from rising water moving inland from the coastline. For
a depiction of areas at risk, please see the National Weather
Service Storm Surge Watch/Warning Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov.
 
This is a life-threatening situation.  Persons located within these
areas should take all necessary actions to protect life and property
from rising water and the potential for other dangerous conditions.
Promptly follow evacuation and other instructions from local
officials.
 
A Storm Surge Watch means there is a possibility of life-
threatening inundation, from rising water moving inland from the
coastline, in the indicated locations during the next 48 hours.
For a depiction of areas at risk, please see the National Weather
Service Storm Surge Watch/Warning Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov.
 
Interests elsewhere along the southeastern coast of the United
States should monitor the progress of this system. Additional
watches and warnings will likely be required later tonight or 
Tuesday.
 
For storm information specific to your area, including possible
inland watches and warnings, please monitor products issued by your
local National Weather Service forecast office.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 800 PM EDT (0000 UTC), the center of Tropical Storm Debby was
located near latitude 30.7 North, longitude 82.4 West.  Debby is
moving toward the northeast near 6 mph (9 km/h).  A turn toward the
east is expected on Tuesday, followed by a turn to the north at a
slow forward speed on Wednesday. On the forecast track, the center
will move across southeastern Georgia tonight and Tuesday, move
offshore of the South Carolina coast by late Tuesday and Wednesday,
and approach the South Carolina coast on Thursday.
 
Maximum sustained winds have decreased to near 45 mph (75 km/h)
with higher gusts.  Some slight additional weakening is forecast 
tonight and Tuesday.  Some re-strengthening is possible on Wednesday 
and Thursday when Debby moves off the southeastern U.S. coast.
 
Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 140 miles (220 km)
from the center.
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 996 mb (29.41 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Debby can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT4 and WMO header WTNT44 KNHC.
 
WIND:  Tropical storm conditions are expected over portions of the
tropical storm warning area along the Florida and Georgia Atlantic
coast through tonight.  Tropical storm conditions are expected along
the coast of South Carolina within the tropical storm warning area
by late tonight or early Tuesday. Tropical storm conditions are 
possible within the tropical storm watch area in South and North 
Carolina beginning Wednesday. 
 
STORM SURGE: The combination of storm surge and tide will cause
normally dry areas near the coast to be flooded by rising waters
moving inland from the shoreline. The water could reach the
following heights above ground somewhere in the indicated areas if
the peak surge occurs at the time of high tide...
 
Mouth of the St. Mary's River to Cape Fear, NC...2-4 ft
 
For a complete depiction of areas at risk of storm surge inundation,
please see the National Weather Service Peak Storm Surge Graphic,
available at hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?peakSurge.
 
RAINFALL: Debby is expected to produce rainfall totals of 6 to 12
inches, with maximum amounts of 18 inches, across portions of
central and northern Florida as well as central and northeast North
Carolina through Wednesday morning.  This rainfall will likely
result in areas of considerable flash and urban flooding, with
significant river flooding expected.
 
Across portions of southeast Georgia, the coastal plain of South
Carolina, and southeast North Carolina, 10 to 20 inches of rainfall,
with local amounts to 30 inches, are expected through Saturday
morning.  This potentially historic rainfall will likely result in
areas of catastrophic flooding.
 
For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall and flash flooding
associated with Hurricane Debby, please see the National Weather
Service Storm Total Rainfall Graphic, available at
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?rainqpf and the Flash Flood Risk
graphic at hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?ero.  For a list of
rainfall observations (and wind reports) associated this storm, see
the companion storm summary at WBCSCCNS4 with the WMO header ACUS44
KWBC or at the following link:
www.wpc.ncep.noaa.gov/discussions/nfdscc4.html.
 
TORNADOES: A few tornadoes are possible over southeastern Georgia
and coastal South Carolina this evening through Tuesday.
 
SURF:  Swells generated by Debby are expected to affect much of the
Gulf coast of Florida through tonight.  Swells will continue to
affect the Southeast U.S. coast through the middle of the week.
These conditions are likely to cause life-threatening surf and rip
current conditions. Please consult products from your local weather
office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next complete advisory at 1100 PM EDT.
 
$$
Forecaster Brown
 
NNNN
 
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
