<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL092024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>ROUTINE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>4</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>17</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240927 11:00:00 AM EDT</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240927 03:00:00 PM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20240927150000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>1100 AM EDT Fri Sep 27</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1727449200</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>TROPICAL STORM</systemType>
<systemName>HELENE</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>35.1</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-83.8</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>35.1N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>83.8W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>45</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>75</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>40</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>975</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>28.80</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>N/A</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>N OR 350 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>32</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>52</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>28</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 30 MI...50 KM SW OF BRYSON CITY NORTH CAROLINA</systemGeoRefPt1>
<systemGeoRefPt2>ABOUT 105 MI...165 KM NNE OF ATLANTA GEORGIA</systemGeoRefPt2>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT4 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Tropical Storm Helene Advisory Number  17
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL092024
1100 AM EDT Fri Sep 27 2024
 
...HELENE PRODUCING HISTORIC AND CATASTROPHIC FLOODING OVER PORTIONS 
OF THE SOUTHEAST AND SOUTHERN APPALACHIANS...
...FLASH FLOOD EMERGENCIES IN EFFECT FOR METROPOLITAN ATLANTA, AND 
MUCH OF UPSTATE SOUTH CAROLINA AND WESTERN NORTH CAROLINA...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 1100 AM EDT...1500 UTC...INFORMATION
-----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...35.1N 83.8W
ABOUT 30 MI...50 KM SW OF BRYSON CITY NORTH CAROLINA
ABOUT 105 MI...165 KM NNE OF ATLANTA GEORGIA
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...45 MPH...75 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...N OR 350 DEGREES AT 32 MPH...52 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...975 MB...28.80 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The Tropical Storm Warning for the Georgia coast has been
discontinued.
 
All Storm Surge Warnings have been discontinued.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Tropical Storm Warning is in effect for...
* Savannah River northward to Little River Inlet
 
A Tropical Storm Warning means that tropical storm conditions are
expected somewhere within the warning area.
 
For storm information specific to your area, including possible
inland watches and warnings, please monitor products issued by your
local National Weather Service forecast office.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 1100 AM EDT (1500 UTC), the center of Tropical Storm Helene was 
located near latitude 35.1 North, longitude 83.8 West. Helene is 
moving toward the north near 32 mph (52 km/h).  A slowdown in 
forward speed is expected soon, and the storm is forecast to stall 
over the Tennessee Valley tonight and through the weekend.
 
Maximum sustained winds have decreased to near 45 mph (75 km/h) 
with higher gusts.  Continued weakening is expected, and Helene is 
forecast to become extratropical later today.
 
Tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 345 miles 
(555 km) east of the center.
 
The estimated minimum central pressure based on surface 
observations is 975 mb (28.80 inches).  A weather station on 
Sassafras Mountain reported a sustained wind of 41 mph (67 km/h) 
with a gust of 61 mph (98 km/h).  A coastal observation at Murrells 
Inlet recently reported a sustained wind of 38 mph (61 km/h) with a 
gust of 46 mph (74 km/h).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key Messages for Helene can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT4 and WMO header WTNT44 KNHC
and on the web at hurricanes.gov/text/MIATCDAT4.shtml
 
STORM SURGE: Water levels will continue to receed along the Florida 
Gulf Coast and portions of the southeast U.S. coast throughout the 
day.
 
WIND: Tropical storm conditions are occurring along much of the
South Carolina coast, and these conditions will continue for the 
next several hours. Strong, damaging winds, especially in gusts, 
will also continue as far inland as the higher terrain of the 
southern Appalachians.
 
RAINFALL: Over portions of the Central and Southern Appalachians, 
Helene is expected to produce additional rainfall amounts of 3 to 6 
inches leading to total rain accumulations of 6 to 12 inches, with 
isolated totals around 20 inches. This rainfall will result in 
catastrophic and potentially life-threatening flash and urban 
flooding, along with significant and record river flooding. Numerous 
significant landslides are expected in steep terrain across the 
Southern Appalachians.

For a complete depiction of forecast rainfall associated with 
Tropical Storm Helene, please see the National Weather Service Storm 
Total Rainfall Graphic, available at 
hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?rainqpf and the Flash Flood Risk 
graphic at hurricanes.gov/graphics_at4.shtml?ero. 

For a list of rainfall observations (and wind reports) associated 
this storm, see the companion storm summary at WBCSCCNS4 with the 
WMO header ACUS44 KWBC or at the following link:
www.wpc.ncep.noaa.gov/discussions/nfdscc4.html
 
TORNADOES: Tornadoes are possible today across eastern South 
Carolina, central and eastern North Carolina, and southern Virginia.
 
SURF: Swells generated by Helene will affect the coasts of Georgia
and the Carolinas during the next day or so.  These swells are
likely to cause life-threatening surf and rip current conditions.
Please consult products from your local weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next intermediate advisory at 200 PM EDT.
Next complete advisory at 500 PM EDT.
 
$$
Forecaster Cangialosi/Rosado
 
NNNN
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
