<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cycloneMessage>
<!-- System Advisory Meta Information -->
<atcfID>AL052024</atcfID>
<issuingUnit>NWS NATIONAL HURRICANE CENTER MIAMI FL</issuingUnit>
<messageType>ROUTINE ADVISORY</messageType>
<messageBinNumber>5</messageBinNumber>
<advisoryNumber>15</advisoryNumber>
<!-- System Date/Time Information -->
<messageDateTimeLocal>20240815 05:00:00 AM AST</messageDateTimeLocal>
<messageDateTimeUTC>20240815 09:00:00 AM UTC</messageDateTimeUTC>
<messageDateTimeUTC24>20240815090000</messageDateTimeUTC24>
<messageDateTimeLocalStr>0500 AM AST Thu Aug 15</messageDateTimeLocalStr>
<timeEpochSeconds>1723712400</timeEpochSeconds>
<!-- System state defined -->
<systemType>HURRICANE</systemType>
<systemName>ERNESTO</systemName>
<!-- Center Location of the System -->
<!-- Lattitude: North is positive; South is negative -->
<!-- Longitude: East is positive; West is negative -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitude>23.9</centerLocLatitude>
<centerLocLongitude>-69.1</centerLocLongitude>
<!-- Lattitude: North is N; South is S -->
<!-- Longitude: East is E; West is W -->
<!-- units: decimal degrees (tenths) -->
<centerLocLatitudeExpanded>23.9N</centerLocLatitudeExpanded>
<centerLocLongitudeExpanded>69.1W</centerLocLongitudeExpanded>
<!-- Maximum Intensity of the System -->
<!-- units: MPH, KPH, KTS, MB and/or INCHES HG -->
<systemIntensityMph>85</systemIntensityMph>
<systemIntensityKph>140</systemIntensityKph>
<systemIntensityKts>75</systemIntensityKts>
<systemMslpMb>979</systemMslpMb>
<systemMslpInHg>28.91</systemMslpInHg>
<systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>CATEGORY 1</systemSaffirSimpsonCategory>
<formationChancePct48h>N/A</formationChancePct48h>
<formationChancePct7d>N/A</formationChancePct7d>
<!-- Current System Movement -->
<!-- units: Degrees, MPH and KPH -->
<systemDirectionOfMotion>N OR 360 DEGREES</systemDirectionOfMotion>
<systemSpeedMph>13</systemSpeedMph>
<systemSpeedKph>20</systemSpeedKph>
<systemSpeedKts>11</systemSpeedKts>
<!-- Current System Location from known Reference Point -->
<systemGeoRefPt1>ABOUT 635 MI...1025 KM SSW OF BERMUDA</systemGeoRefPt1>
<!-- Relevant Message -->
<message>
ZCZC MIATCPAT5 ALL
TTAA00 KNHC DDHHMM
 
BULLETIN
Hurricane Ernesto Advisory Number  15
NWS National Hurricane Center Miami FL       AL052024
500 AM AST Thu Aug 15 2024
 
...HURRICANE WARNING ISSUED FOR BERMUDA...
 
 
SUMMARY OF 500 AM AST...0900 UTC...INFORMATION
----------------------------------------------
LOCATION...23.9N 69.1W
ABOUT 635 MI...1025 KM SSW OF BERMUDA
MAXIMUM SUSTAINED WINDS...85 MPH...140 KM/H
PRESENT MOVEMENT...N OR 360 DEGREES AT 13 MPH...20 KM/H
MINIMUM CENTRAL PRESSURE...979 MB...28.91 INCHES
 
 
WATCHES AND WARNINGS
--------------------
CHANGES WITH THIS ADVISORY:
 
The Bermuda Weather Service has issued a Hurricane Warning for 
Bermuda.
 
SUMMARY OF WATCHES AND WARNINGS IN EFFECT:
 
A Hurricane Warning is in effect for...
* Bermuda
 
A Hurricane Warning means that hurricane conditions are expected
somewhere within the warning area.  A warning is typically issued
36 hours before the anticipated first occurrence of
tropical-storm-force winds, conditions that make outside
preparations difficult or dangerous.  Preparations to protect life
and property should be rushed to completion.
 
For storm information specific to your area, please monitor
products issued by your national meteorological service.
 
 
DISCUSSION AND OUTLOOK
----------------------
At 500 AM AST (0900 UTC), the center of Hurricane Ernesto was
located near latitude 23.9 North, longitude 69.1 West. Ernesto is
moving toward the north near 13 mph (20 km/h).  This general motion 
is expected today, followed by a slower northeastward or northward 
motion on Friday and Saturday. On the forecast track, the center of 
Ernesto is expected to pass near or over Bermuda on Saturday.
 
Maximum sustained winds remain near 85 mph (140 km/h) with higher
gusts.  Strengthening is forecast during the next day or two, and 
Ernesto could become a major hurricane by Friday.  Ernesto is 
forecast to be a large hurricane near Bermuda on Saturday.
 
Hurricane-force winds extend outward up to 45 miles (75 km) from the
center and tropical-storm-force winds extend outward up to 175 miles
(280 km).  
 
The estimated minimum central pressure is 979 mb (28.91 inches).  
NOAA buoy 41046, located about 20 miles north of Ernesto, recently 
reported a minimum central pressure of 987.4 mb (29.16 inches).
 
 
HAZARDS AFFECTING LAND
----------------------
Key messages for Ernesto can be found in the Tropical Cyclone
Discussion under AWIPS header MIATCDAT5 and WMO header WTNT45 KNHC
and on the web at hurricanes.gov/text/MIATCDAT5.shtml.
 
WIND: Hurricane conditions are expected on Bermuda Saturday, with
tropical storm conditions likely beginning Friday afternoon.

STORM SURGE: A dangerous storm surge is expected to produce 
significant coastal flooding on Bermuda in areas of onshore winds.  
Near the coast, the surge will be accompanied by large and 
destructive waves.
 
RAINFALL: Ernesto is expected to produce total rain accumulations of 
4 to 8 inches in Bermuda with isolated maximum amounts up to 12 
inches.  This rainfall may result in considerable life-threatening 
flash flooding.
 
SURF: Swells generated by Ernesto are affecting portions of the
northern Leeward Islands, the Virgin Islands, Puerto Rico, the
Dominican Republic, the Turks and Caicos Islands, and the
southeastern Bahamas. These swells will spread toward Bermuda and
the rest of the Bahamas later today. Swells are expected to reach
the east coast of the United States tonight and continue into
the weekend. These swells are likely to cause life-threatening surf
and rip current conditions. Please consult products from your local
weather office.
 
 
NEXT ADVISORY
-------------
Next intermediate advisory at 800 AM AST.
Next complete advisory at 1100 AM AST.
 
$$
Forecaster Blake
 
NNNN
</message>
</cycloneMessage>
